Jeremiah

7 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: 2 “Stand in the gate of the house of Jehovah, and you must proclaim there this word, and you must say, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah, all YOU of Judah, who are entering into these gates to bow down to Jehovah. 3 This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “Make YOUR ways and YOUR dealings good, and I will keep YOU people residing in this place. 4 Do not put YOUR trust in fallacious words, saying, ‘The temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah, the temple of Jehovah they are!’ 5 For if YOU will positively make YOUR ways and YOUR dealings good, if YOU will positively carry out justice between a man and his companion, 6 if no alien resident, no fatherless boy and no widow YOU will oppress, and innocent blood YOU will not shed in this place, and after other gods YOU will not walk for calamity to yourselves, 7 I, in turn, shall certainly keep YOU residing in this place, in the land that I gave to YOUR forefathers, from time indefinite even to time indefinite.”’”

8 “Here YOU are putting YOUR trust in fallacious words—it will certainly be of no benefit at all. 9 Can there be stealing, murdering and committing adultery and swearing falsely and making sacrificial smoke to Ba′al and walking after other gods whom YOU had not known, 10 and must YOU come and stand before me in this house upon which my name has been called, and must YOU say, ‘We shall certainly be delivered,’ in the face of doing all these detestable things? 11 Has this house upon which my name has been called become a mere cave of robbers in YOUR eyes? Here I myself also have seen it,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

12 “‘However, GO, now, to my place that was in Shi′loh, where I caused my name to reside at first, and see what I did to it because of the badness of my people Israel. 13 And now for the reason that YOU kept doing all these works,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and I kept speaking to YOU, getting up early and speaking, but YOU did not listen, and I kept calling YOU, but YOU did not answer, 14 I will do also to the house upon which my name has been called, in which YOU are trusting, and to the place that I gave to YOU and to YOUR forefathers, just as I did to Shi′loh. 15 And I will throw YOU out from before my face, just as I threw out all YOUR brothers, the whole offspring of E′phra·im.’

16 “And as for you, do not pray in behalf of this people, neither raise in their behalf an entreating cry or a prayer nor beseech me, for I shall not be listening to you. 17 Are you not seeing what they are doing in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem? 18 The sons are picking up sticks of wood, and the fathers are lighting the fire, and the wives are kneading flour dough in order to make sacrificial cakes to the ‘queen of the heavens’; and there is a pouring out of drink offerings to other gods for the purpose of offending me. 19 ‘Is it I whom they are offending?’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘Is it not they themselves, for the purpose of shame to their faces?’ 20 Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Look! My anger and my rage are being poured forth upon this place, upon mankind and upon domestic animal, and upon the tree of the field and upon the fruitage of the ground; and it must burn, and it will not be extinguished.’

21 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Add those whole burnt offerings of YOURS to YOUR sacrifices and eat flesh. 22 For I did not speak with YOUR forefathers, nor did I command them in the day of my bringing them out from the land of Egypt concerning the matters of whole burnt offering and sacrifice. 23 But this word I did express in command upon them, saying: “Obey my voice, and I will become YOUR God, and YOU yourselves will become my people; and YOU must walk in all the way that I shall command YOU, in order that it may go well with YOU.”’ 24 But they did not listen, neither did they incline their ear, but they went walking in the counsels in the stubbornness of their bad heart, so that they became backward in direction and not forward, 25 from the day that YOUR forefathers came forth out of the land of Egypt until this day; and I kept sending to YOU all my servants the prophets, daily getting up early and sending them. 26 But they did not listen to me, and they did not incline their ear, but they kept hardening their neck. They acted worse than their forefathers!

27 “And you must speak to them all these words, but they will not listen to you; and you must call to them, but they will not answer you. 28 And you must say to them, ‘This is the nation whose people have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah its God, and have not taken discipline. Faithfulness has perished, and it has been cut off from their mouth.’

29 “Shear off your uncut hair and throw it away, and upon the bare hills raise a dirge, for Jehovah has rejected and will desert the generation with which he is furious. 30 ‘For the sons of Judah have done what is bad in my eyes,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘They have set their disgusting things in the house upon which my name has been called, in order to defile it. 31 And they have built the high places of To′pheth, which is in the valley of the son of Hin′nom, in order to burn their sons and their daughters in the fire, a thing that I had not commanded and that had not come up into my heart.’

32 “‘Therefore, look! days are coming,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘when it will no more be said to be To′pheth and the valley of the son of Hin′nom, but the valley of the killing; and they will have to bury in To′pheth without there being enough place. 33 And the dead bodies of this people must become food for the flying creatures of the heavens and for the beasts of the earth, with nobody to make them tremble. 34 And I will cause to cease from the cities of Judah and from the streets of Jerusalem the voice of exultation and the voice of rejoicing, the voice of the bridegroom and the voice of the bride; for the land will become nothing but a devastated place.’”

Jeremiah

8 “At that time,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “people will also bring forth the bones of the kings of Judah and the bones of its princes and the bones of the priests and the bones of the prophets and the bones of the inhabitants of Jerusalem from their graves. 2 And they will actually spread them out to the sun and to the moon and to all the army of the heavens that they have loved and that they have served and that they have walked after and that they have sought and that they have bowed down to. They will not be gathered, nor will they be buried. As manure upon the face of the ground they will become.”

3 “And death will certainly be chosen rather than life on the part of all the remnant of those remaining out of this bad family in all the places of the remaining ones, where I will have dispersed them,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies.

4 “And you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Will they fall and not get up again? If one would turn back, will the other not also turn back? 5 Why is it that this people, Jerusalem, is unfaithful with an enduring unfaithfulness? They have taken hold of trickiness; they have refused to turn back. 6 I have paid attention, and I kept listening. It was not right the way they kept speaking. There was not a man repenting over his badness, saying, ‘What have I done?’ Each one is going back into the popular course, like a horse that is dashing into the battle. 7 Even the stork in the heavens—it well knows its appointed times; and the turtledove and the swift and the bulbul—they observe well the time of each one’s coming in. But as for my people, they have not come to know the judgment of Jehovah.”’

8 “‘How can YOU men say: “We are wise, and the law of Jehovah is with us”? Surely, now, the false stylus of the secretaries has worked in sheer falsehood. 9 The wise ones have become ashamed. They have become terrified and will be caught. Look! They have rejected the very word of Jehovah, and what wisdom do they have? 10 Therefore I shall give their wives to other men, their fields to those taking possession; for, from the least one even to the greatest one, each one is making unjust gain; from the prophet even to the priest, each one is acting falsely. 11 And they try to heal the breakdown of the daughter of my people lightly, saying: “There is peace! There is peace!” when there is no peace. 12 Did they feel shame because they had done even what was detestable? For one thing, they positively could not feel ashamed; for another thing, they did not know even how to feel humiliated.

“‘Therefore they will fall among those who are falling. In the time of their being given attention, they will stumble,’ Jehovah has said.

13 “‘When doing the gathering, I shall bring them to their finish,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘There will be no grapes on the vine, and there will be no figs on the fig tree, and the foliage itself will certainly wither. And things that I give to them will pass by them.’”

14 “Why are we sitting still? Gather yourselves together, and let us enter into the fortified cities and be silent there. For Jehovah our God has himself put us to silence, and he gives us poisoned water to drink, because we have sinned against Jehovah. 15 There was a hoping for peace, but no good came; for a time of healing, but, look! terror! 16 From Dan has been heard the snorting of his horses. Due to the sound of the neighing of his stallions the whole land has begun to rock. And they come in and eat up the land and what fills it, the city and its inhabitants.”

17 “For here I am sending in among YOU serpents, poisonous snakes, for which there is no charming, and they will certainly bite YOU,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

18 A grief that is beyond curing has come up into me. My heart is ill. 19 Here there is the sound of the cry for help of the daughter of my people from a land far away: “Is Jehovah not in Zion? Or is her king not in her?”

“Why is it that they have offended me with their graven images, with their vain foreign gods?”

20 “The harvest has passed, the summer has come to an end; but as for us, we have not been saved!”

21 Over the breakdown of the daughter of my people I have become shattered. I have grown sad. Outright astonishment has seized hold of me. 22 Is there no balsam in Gil′e·ad? Or is there no healer there? Why is it, then, that the recuperation of the daughter of my people has not come up?

Jeremiah

9 O that my head were waters, and that my eyes were a source of tears! Then I could weep day and night for the slain ones of the daughter of my people.

2 O that I had in the wilderness a lodging place of travelers! Then I would leave my people and go away from them, for all of them are adulterers, a solemn assembly of treacherous dealers; 3 and they bend their tongue as their bow in falsehood; but not for faithfulness have they proved mighty in the land.

“For from badness to badness they went forth, and they ignored even me,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

4 “Guard yourselves each one against his own companion, and put YOUR trust in no brother at all. For even every brother would positively supplant, and every companion himself would walk around as a mere slanderer, 5 and they keep trifling each one with his companion; and they speak no truth at all. They have taught their tongue to speak falsehood. They have tired themselves out merely in doing wrong.

6 “Your sitting is in the midst of deception. Through deception they have refused to know me,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

7 Therefore this is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Here I am smelting them, and I have to examine them, because how otherwise shall I act on account of the daughter of my people? 8 Their tongue is a slaughtering arrow. Deception is what it has spoken. With his mouth, peace is what a person keeps speaking with his own companion; but within himself he sets his ambush.”

9 “Because of these things should I not hold an accounting with them?” is the utterance of Jehovah. “Or upon a nation that is like this should not my soul avenge itself? 10 Over the mountains I shall raise a weeping and lamentation, and over the pasture grounds of the wilderness a dirge; for they will have been burned so that there is no man passing through and people actually will not hear the sound of livestock. Both the flying creature of the heavens and the beast will have fled; they will have gone. 11 And I will make Jerusalem piles of stones, the lair of jackals; and the cities of Judah I shall make a desolate waste, without an inhabitant.

12 “Who is the man that is wise, that he may understand this, even the one to whom the mouth of Jehovah has spoken, that he may tell it? On what account should the land actually perish, be actually burned like the wilderness without anyone passing through?”

13 And Jehovah proceeded to say: “On account of their leaving my law that I gave to be before them, and because they have not obeyed my voice and have not walked in it, 14 but they kept on walking after the stubbornness of their heart and after the Ba′al images, about which their fathers had taught them; 15 therefore this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Here I am making them, that is, this people, eat wormwood, and I will make them drink poisoned water; 16 and I will scatter them among the nations that neither they nor their fathers have known, and I will send after them the sword until I shall have exterminated them.’

17 “This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘Behave with understanding, YOU people, and call the dirge-chanting women, that they may come; and send even to the skilled women, that they may come, 18 and that they may hurry and raise up over us a lamentation. And may our eyes run down with tears and our own beaming eyes trickle with waters. 19 For the voice of lamentation is what has been heard from Zion: “How we have been despoiled! How much we have felt shame! For we have left the land; for they have thrown away our residences.” 20 But hear, O YOU women, the word of Jehovah, and may YOUR ear take the word of his mouth. Then teach YOUR daughters a lamentation, and each woman her companion a dirge. 21 For death has come up through our windows; it has come into our dwelling towers, in order to cut off the child from the street, the young men from the public squares.’

22 “Speak, ‘This is what the utterance of Jehovah is: “The dead bodies of mankind must also fall like manure upon the face of the field and like a row of newly cut grain after the reaper, with no one to do the gathering up.”’”

23 This is what Jehovah has said: “Let not the wise man brag about himself because of his wisdom, and let not the mighty man brag about himself because of his mightiness. Let not the rich man brag about himself because of his riches.”

24 “But let the one bragging about himself brag about himself because of this very thing, the having of insight and the having of knowledge of me, that I am Jehovah, the One exercising loving-kindness, justice and righteousness in the earth; for in these things I do take delight,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

25 “Look! Days are coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I will hold an accounting with everyone circumcised but still in uncircumcision, 26 upon Egypt and upon Judah and upon E′dom and upon the sons of Am′mon and upon Mo′ab and upon all those with hair clipped at the temples who are dwelling in the wilderness; for all the nations are uncircumcised, and all the house of Israel are uncircumcised in heart.”

Jeremiah

15 And Jehovah proceeded to say to me: “If Moses and Samuel were standing before me, my soul would not be toward this people. There would be a sending of them away from before my face, that they might go out. 2 And it must occur that should they say to you, ‘Where shall we go out to?’ you must also say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Whoever is for deadly plague, to deadly plague! And whoever is for the sword, to the sword! And whoever is for the famine, to the famine! And whoever is for the captivity, to the captivity!”’

3 “‘And I will commission over them four families,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘the sword to kill, and the dogs to drag away, and the flying creatures of the heavens and the beasts of the earth to eat and to bring to ruin. 4 And I will give them for a quaking to all the kingdoms of the earth on account of Ma·nas′seh the son of Hez·e·ki′ah, the king of Judah, for what he did in Jerusalem. 5 For who will show compassion upon you, O Jerusalem, and who will sympathize with you, and who will turn aside to ask about your welfare?’

6 “‘You yourself have deserted me,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘Backwards is the way you keep walking. And I shall stretch out my hand against you and bring you to ruin. I have got tired of feeling regret. 7 And I shall winnow them with a fork in the gates of the land. I shall certainly bereave them of children. I will destroy my people, since they have not turned back from their own ways. 8 To me their widows have become more numerous than the sand grains of the seas. I will bring for them, upon mother, young man, the despoiler at midday. I will cause to fall upon them suddenly excitement and disturbances. 9 The woman giving birth to seven has faded away; her soul has struggled for breath. Her sun has set while it is yet day; it has become ashamed and felt abashed.’ ‘And to the sword I shall give the mere remnant of them before their enemies,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

10 Woe to me, O my mother, because you have given birth to me, a man subject to quarrel and a man subject to strife with all the earth. I have given no loan, and they have given me no loan. All of them are calling down evil upon me.

11 Jehovah has said: “Surely I will minister to you for good. Surely I will intercede for you in the time of calamity and in the time of distress, against the enemy. 12 Can one break iron in pieces, iron out of the north, and copper? 13 Your resources and your treasures I shall give for mere plunder, not for a price, but for all your sins, even in all your territories. 14 And I will cause them to pass over with your enemies into a land that you have not known. For a fire itself has been ignited in my anger. Against YOU people it is kindled.”

15 You yourself have known. O Jehovah, remember me and turn your attention to me and avenge me upon my persecutors. In your slowness to anger do not take me away. Take note of my bearing reproach on account of your own self. 16 Your words were found, and I proceeded to eat them; and your word becomes to me the exultation and the rejoicing of my heart; for your name has been called upon me, O Jehovah God of armies. 17 I have not sat down in the intimate group of those playing jokes and begun exulting. Because of your hand I have sat down all by myself, for it is with denunciation that you have filled me. 18 Why has my pain become chronic and my stroke incurable? It has refused to be healed. You positively become to me like something deceitful, like waters that have proved untrustworthy.

19 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “If you will come back, then I shall bring you back. Before me you will stand. And if you will bring forth what is precious from valueless things, you will become like my own mouth. They themselves will come back to you, but you yourself will not come back to them.”

20 “And I have made you to this people a fortified copper wall; and they will certainly fight against you, but they will not prevail over you. For I am with you, to save you and to deliver you,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 21 “And I will deliver you out of the hand of the bad ones, and I will redeem you out of the palm of the tyrannical ones.”

Jeremiah

19 This is what Jehovah said: “Go, and you must get an earthenware flask of a potter and some of the older men of the people and some of the older men of the priests. 2 And you must go out to the valley of the son of Hin′nom, which is at the entrance of the Gate of the Potsherds. And there you must proclaim the words that I shall speak to you. 3 And you must say, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah, O YOU kings of Judah and YOU inhabitants of Jerusalem. This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said:

“‘“Here I am bringing a calamity upon this place, of which when anyone hears, his ears will tingle; 4 for the reason that they have left me and have proceeded to make this place unrecognizable and to make sacrificial smoke in it to other gods whom they had not known, they and their forefathers and the kings of Judah; and they have filled this place with the blood of the innocent ones. 5 And they built the high places of the Ba′al in order to burn their sons in the fire as whole burnt offerings to the Ba′al, something that I had not commanded or spoken of, and that had not come up into my heart.”’

6 “‘“Therefore, look! there are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “when this place will be called no more To′pheth and the valley of the son of Hin′nom, but the valley of the killing. 7 And I will make void the counsel of Judah and of Jerusalem in this place, and I will cause them to fall by the sword before their enemies and by the hand of those seeking for their soul. And I will give their dead bodies as food to the flying creatures of the heavens and to the beasts of the earth. 8 And I will make this city an object of astonishment and something to be whistled at. Every last one passing along by it will stare in astonishment and whistle over all its plagues. 9 And I will make them eat the flesh of their sons and the flesh of their daughters; and they will eat each one the flesh of his fellowman, because of the tightness and because of the stress with which their enemies and those seeking for their soul will hem them in.”’

10 “And you must break the flask before the eyes of the men who are going with you. 11 And you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “In the same way I shall break this people and this city as someone breaks the vessel of the potter so that it is no more able to be repaired; and in To′pheth they will bury until there is no more place to bury.”’

12 “‘That is how I shall do to this place,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and to the inhabitants of it, even to make this city like To′pheth. 13 And the houses of Jerusalem and the houses of the kings of Judah must become like the place of To′pheth, unclean ones, that is, all the houses upon the roofs of which they made sacrificial smoke to all the army of the heavens and there was a pouring out of drink offerings to other gods.’”

14 And Jeremiah proceeded to come from To′pheth, to which Jehovah had sent him to prophesy, and to stand in the courtyard of the house of Jehovah and say to all the people: 15 “This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Here I am bringing upon this city and upon all its cities all the calamity that I have spoken against it, because they have hardened their neck in order not to obey my words.’”

Jeremiah

21 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah, when King Zed·e·ki′ah sent to him Pash′hur the son of Mal·chi′jah and Zeph·a·ni′ah the son of Ma·a·sei′ah, the priest, saying: 2 “Please inquire in our behalf of Jehovah, because Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon is making war against us. Perhaps Jehovah will do with us according to all his wonderful works, so that he will withdraw from us.”

3 And Jeremiah proceeded to say to them: “This is what YOU will say to Zed·e·ki′ah, 4 ‘This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said: “Here I am turning in reverse the weapons of war that are in the hand of YOU people, with which YOU are fighting the king of Babylon, and the Chal·de′ans who are laying siege against YOU outside the wall, and I will gather them into the middle of this city. 5 And I myself will fight against YOU with a stretched-out hand and with a strong arm and with anger and with rage and with great indignation. 6 And I will strike the inhabitants of this city, both man and beast. With a great pestilence they will die.”’

7 “‘“And after that,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “I shall give Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah and his servants and the people and those who are remaining over in this city from the pestilence, from the sword and from the famine, into the hand of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon, even into the hand of their enemies and into the hand of those who are seeking for their soul, and he will certainly strike them with the edge of the sword. He will not feel sorry for them, nor will he show compassion or have any mercy.”’

8 “And to this people you will say, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am putting before YOU people the way of life and the way of death. 9 The one sitting still in this city will die by the sword and by the famine and by the pestilence; but the one who is going out and who actually falls away to the Chal·de′ans who are laying siege against YOU will keep living, and his soul will certainly come to be his as a spoil.”’

10 “‘“For I have set my face against this city for calamity and not for good,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “Into the hand of the king of Babylon it will be given, and he will certainly burn it with fire.”

11 “‘And as regards the household of the king of Judah, hear, O men, the word of Jehovah. 12 O house of David, this is what Jehovah has said: “Every morning render sentence in justice, and deliver the one being robbed out of the hand of the defrauder, that my rage may not go forth just like a fire and actually burn and there be no one to extinguish it because of the badness of YOUR dealings.”’

13 “‘Here I am against you, O inhabitress of the low plain, O rock of the level land,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘As for YOU who are saying: “Who will descend against us? And who will come into our dwellings?” 14 I will also hold an accounting against YOU according to the fruitage of YOUR dealings,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. ‘And I will set a fire ablaze in her forest, and it will certainly devour all the things round about her.’”

Jeremiah

22 This is what Jehovah has said: “Go down to the house of the king of Judah, and you must speak there this word. 2 And you must say, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah, O king of Judah who are sitting on the throne of David, you with your servants and your people, those who are coming in through these gates. 3 This is what Jehovah has said: “RENDER justice and righteousness, and deliver the one that is being robbed out of the hand of the defrauder; and do not maltreat any alien resident, fatherless boy or widow. Do them no violence. And do not shed any innocent blood in this place. 4 For if YOU will by all means perform this word, there will also certainly come in through the gates of this house the kings sitting for David upon his throne, riding in chariots and on horses, he with his servants and his people.”’

5 “‘But if YOU will not obey these words, by myself I do swear,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘that this house will become a mere devastated place.’

6 “For this is what Jehovah has said concerning the house of the king of Judah, ‘You are as Gil′e·ad to me, the head of Leb′a·non. Assuredly I shall make you a wilderness; as for the cities, not one will be inhabited. 7 And I will sanctify against you those bringing ruin, each one and his weapons; and they must cut down the choicest of your cedars and cause them to fall into the fire. 8 And many nations will actually pass along by this city and say one to the other: “On what account did Jehovah do like this to this great city?” 9 And they will have to say: “On account of the fact that they left the covenant of Jehovah their God and proceeded to bow down to other gods and to serve them.”’

10 “Do not weep for the dead one, and do not sympathize with him, YOU people. Weep profusely for the one going away, for he will return no more and he will actually not see the land of his relatives. 11 For this is what Jehovah has said concerning Shal′lum the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah who is reigning instead of Jo·si′ah his father, who has gone forth from this place, ‘He will return there no more. 12 For in the place where they have taken him into exile he will die, and this land he will see no more.’

13 “Woe to the one building his house, but not with righteousness, and his upper chambers, but not with justice, by use of his fellowman who serves for nothing, and whose wages he does not give him; 14 the one saying, ‘I am going to build for myself a roomy house and commodious upper chambers; and my windows must be widened out for it, and the paneling will be with cedar and smeared with vermilion.’ 15 Will you continue reigning because you are competing by use of cedar? As for your father, did he not eat and drink and execute justice and righteousness? In that case it went well with him. 16 He pleaded the legal claim of the afflicted one and the poor one. In that case it went well. ‘Was not that a case of knowing me?’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 17 ‘Assuredly your eyes and your heart are upon nothing but upon your unjust gain, and upon the blood of the innocent one in order to shed it, and upon defrauding and upon extortion in order to carry them on.’

18 “Therefore this is what Jehovah has said concerning Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah, ‘They will not wail for him: “Alas, my brother! And alas, my sister!” They will not wail for him: “Alas, O master! And alas, his dignity!” 19 With the burial of a he-ass he will be buried, with a dragging about and a throwing away, out beyond the gates of Jerusalem.’

20 “Go up onto Leb′a·non and cry out, and on Ba′shan let your voice out. And cry out from Ab′a·rim, because all those intensely loving you have been broken. 21 I spoke to you during your freedom from care. You said, ‘I shall not obey.’ This has been your way since your youth, for you did not obey my voice. 22 A wind will shepherd all your own shepherds; and as for those intensely loving you, they will go into captivity itself. For at that time you will be ashamed and certainly feel humiliated because of all your calamity. 23 O you who are dwelling in Leb′a·non, being nested in the cedars, how you will certainly sigh when there come to you birth pangs, the labor pains like those of a woman giving birth!”

24 “‘As I am alive,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘even if Co·ni′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·kim, the king of Judah, happened to be the seal ring on my right hand, from there I would pull you off! 25 And I will give you into the hand of those who are seeking for your soul and into the hand of those of whom you are scared and into the hand of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon and into the hand of the Chal·de′ans. 26 And I will hurl you and your mother who gave you birth out into another land in which YOU people were not born, and there is where YOU will die. 27 And into the land to which they will be lifting up their soul to return, there they will not return. 28 Is this man Co·ni′ah a mere form despised, dashed to pieces, or a vessel in which there is no delight? Why is it that he himself and his offspring must be hurled down and thrown into the land that they have not known?’

29 “O earth, earth, earth, hear the word of Jehovah. 30 This is what Jehovah has said, ‘WRITE down this man as childless, as an able-bodied man who will not have any success in his days; for from his offspring not a single one will have any success, sitting upon the throne of David and ruling anymore in Judah.’”

Jeremiah

30 The word that occurred to Jeremiah from Jehovah, saying: 2 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘Write for yourself in a book all the words that I will speak to you. 3 For, “look! there are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I will gather the captive ones of my people, Israel and Judah,” Jehovah has said, “and I will bring them back to the land that I gave to their forefathers, and they will certainly repossess it.”’”

4 And these are the words that Jehovah has spoken to Israel and to Judah. 5 For this is what Jehovah has said: “The sound of trembling we have heard, dread, and there is no peace. 6 Ask, please, O men, and see whether a male is giving birth. Why is it that I have seen every able-bodied man with his hands upon his loins like a female that is giving birth, and all faces have turned pale? 7 Alas! For that day is a great one, so that there is no other like it, and it is the time of distress for Jacob. But he will be saved even out of it.”

8 “And it must occur in that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, “that I shall break one’s yoke from off your neck, and your bands I shall tear in two, and no more will strangers exploit him as a servant. 9 And they will certainly serve Jehovah their God and David their king, whom I shall raise up for them.”

10 “And as for you, do not be afraid, O my servant Jacob,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and do not be struck with terror, O Israel. For here I am saving you from far off and your offspring from the land of their captivity. And Jacob will certainly return and be free of disturbance and be at ease, and there will be no one causing trembling.”

11 “For I am with you,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “to save you; but I shall make an extermination among all the nations to which I have scattered you. However, in your case I shall make no extermination. And I shall have to correct you to the proper degree, as I shall by no means leave you unpunished.”

12 For this is what Jehovah has said: “There is no cure for your breakdown. Your stroke is chronic. 13 There is no one pleading your cause, for your ulcer. There are no means of healing, no mending, for you. 14 All those intensely loving you are the ones that have forgotten you. You are not the one for whom they keep searching. For with the stroke of an enemy I have struck you, with the chastisement of someone cruel, on account of the abundance of your error; your sins have become numerous. 15 Why do you cry out on account of your breakdown? Your pain is incurable on account of the abundance of your error; your sins have become numerous. I have done these things to you. 16 Therefore all those devouring you will themselves be devoured; and as for all your adversaries, into captivity they will all of them go. And those pillaging you will certainly come to be for pillaging, and all those plundering you I shall give over to plundering.”

17 “For I shall bring up a recuperation for you, and from your strokes I shall heal you,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “For a woman chased away is what they called you: ‘That is Zion, for whom no one is searching.’”

18 This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am gathering the captive ones of the tents of Jacob, and for his tabernacles I shall have pity. And the city will actually be rebuilt upon her mound; and upon its rightful site the dwelling tower itself will sit. 19 And from them there will certainly go forth thanksgiving, and the sound of those who are laughing. And I will multiply them, and they will not become few; and I will make them heavy in number, and they will not become insignificant. 20 And his sons must become as in former times, and before me his own assembly will be firmly established. And I will turn my attention upon all his oppressors. 21 And his majestic one will certainly come to be from him, and from the midst of him his own ruler will go forth; and I will cause him to come near, and he must approach to me.”

“For who, now, is this one that has given his heart in pledge in order to approach to me?” is the utterance of Jehovah. 22 “And YOU will certainly become my people, and I myself shall become YOUR God.”

23 Look! A windstorm of Jehovah, rage itself, has gone forth, an onward-sweeping tempest. Upon the head of the wicked ones it will whirl. 24 The burning anger of Jehovah will not turn back until he will have executed and until he will have carried out the ideas of his heart. In the final part of the days YOU people will give YOUR consideration to it.

Jeremiah

37 And King Zed·e·ki′ah the son of Jo·si′ah began to reign in place of Co·ni′ah the son of Je·hoi′a·kim, whom Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon made king in the land of Judah. 2 And he himself and his servants and the people of the land did not listen to the words of Jehovah that he spoke by means of Jeremiah the prophet.

3 And King Zed·e·ki′ah proceeded to send Je·hu′cal the son of Shel·e·mi′ah and Zeph·a·ni′ah the son of Ma·a·sei′ah the priest to Jeremiah the prophet, saying: “Pray, please, in our behalf to Jehovah our God.” 4 And Jeremiah was coming in and going out into the midst of the people, as they had not put him in the house of detention. 5 And there was a military force of Phar′aoh that came out of Egypt; and the Chal·de′ans that were laying siege to Jerusalem got to hear the report about them. So they withdrew from against Jerusalem. 6 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to Jeremiah the prophet, saying: 7 “This is what Jehovah the God of Israel has said, ‘This is what YOU men should say to the king of Judah, the one sending YOU to me to inquire of me: “Look! The military force of Phar′aoh that is coming forth to YOU people for the purpose of assistance will have to go back to their land, Egypt. 8 And the Chal·de′ans will certainly come back and fight against this city and capture it and burn it with fire.” 9 This is what Jehovah has said: “Do not deceive YOUR souls, saying, ‘The Chal·de′ans will without fail go away from against us,’ because they will not go away. 10 For if YOU men had struck down all the military force of the Chal·de′ans who are fighting YOU and there remained over among them men pierced through, they would each one in his tent rise up and actually burn this city with fire.”’”

11 And it occurred when the military force of the Chal·de′ans had withdrawn themselves from against Jerusalem because of the military force of Phar′aoh, 12 that Jeremiah began to go forth from Jerusalem to go to the land of Benjamin and to get his portion from there in the midst of the people. 13 So it came about when he was in the Gate of Benjamin that the officer holding the oversight, whose name was I·ri′jah the son of Shel·e·mi′ah the son of Han·a·ni′ah, was there. At once he took hold of Jeremiah the prophet, saying: “It is to the Chal·de′ans that you are falling away!” 14 But Jeremiah said: “It is false! I am not falling away to the Chal·de′ans.” But he did not listen to him. So I·ri′jah kept hold of Jeremiah and brought him in to the princes. 15 And the princes began to get indignant at Jeremiah, and they struck him and put him into the house of fetters, in the house of Je·hon′a·than the secretary, for this was what they had made the house of detention. 16 When Jeremiah came into the house of the cistern and into the vaulted rooms, then Jeremiah continued dwelling there many days.

17 And King Zed·e·ki′ah proceeded to send and take him, and the king began asking him questions in his house in a place of concealment. And he went on to say: “Does there exist a word from Jehovah?” To this Jeremiah said: “There does exist!” And he said further: “Into the hand of the king of Babylon you will be given!”

18 Then Jeremiah said to King Zed·e·ki′ah: “In what way have I sinned against you and against your servants and against this people, so that YOU men have put me into the house of detention? 19 Where, now, are YOUR prophets who prophesied to YOU, saying, ‘The king of Babylon will not come against YOU men and against this land’? 20 And now listen, please, O my lord the king. May my request for favor, please, fall before you, and do not send me back to the house of Je·hon′a·than the secretary, that I may not die there.” 21 Accordingly King Zed·e·ki′ah commanded, and they then put Jeremiah in custody in the Courtyard of the Guard; and there was a giving of a round loaf of bread to him daily from the street of the bakers, until all the bread was exhausted from the city. And Jeremiah continued dwelling in the Courtyard of the Guard.

Jeremiah

41 So it came about in the seventh month that Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah the son of E·lish′a·ma of the royal offspring and of the principal men of the king and ten other men with him came to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam at Miz′pah. And there they began to eat bread together in Miz′pah. 2 Then Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and the ten men that happened to be with him rose up and struck down Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan with the sword. So he put to death the one whom the king of Babylon had commissioned over the land. 3 And all the Jews who happened to be with him, that is, with Ged·a·li′ah, in Miz′pah, and the Chal·de′ans who were found there, that is, the men of war, Ish′ma·el struck down.

4 And it came about on the second day of the putting of Ged·a·li′ah to death, when there was no one at all that knew it, 5 then there came men from She′chem, from Shi′loh and from Sa·mar′i·a, eighty men with their beards shaved off and with their garments ripped apart and with cuts made upon themselves, and there were grain offering and frankincense in their hand to bring to the house of Jehovah. 6 So Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah went out from Miz′pah to meet them, weeping while he was walking along. And it came about that as soon as he encountered them he proceeded to say to them: “Come to Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam.” 7 But it occurred that as soon as they came into the midst of the city, Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah went slaughtering them and throwing them into the midst of the cistern, he and the men that were with him.

8 But there were ten men that were found among them who immediately said to Ish′ma·el: “Do not put us to death, for there exist in our possession hidden treasures in the field, wheat and barley and oil and honey.” So he refrained, and he did not put them to death in the midst of their brothers. 9 Now the cistern into which Ish′ma·el threw all the carcasses of the men that he had struck down was a great cistern, the one that King A′sa had made because of Ba′a·sha the king of Israel. It was the one that Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah filled with those slain.

10 Then Ish′ma·el took captive all the remnant of the people who were in Miz′pah, the daughters of the king and all the people who were remaining over in Miz′pah, whom Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard had put in the custody of Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam. So Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah took them captive and went off to cross over to the sons of Am′mon.

11 In time Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the chiefs of the military forces who were with him got to hear all the bad that Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah had done. 12 Consequently they took all the men and went off to fight against Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah and found him by the abundant waters that were in Gib′e·on.

13 Then it came about that as soon as all the people that were with Ish′ma·el saw Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the chiefs of the military forces who were with him, they began to rejoice. 14 And all the people whom Ish′ma·el had led captive from Miz′pah proceeded to turn around and return and go to Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah. 15 And as for Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah, he escaped with eight men from before Jo·ha′nan, that he might go to the sons of Am′mon.

16 Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the chiefs of the military forces who were with him now took all the remnant of the people whom they brought back from Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah, from Miz′pah, after he had struck down Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam, able-bodied men, men of war, and the wives and the little children and the court officials, whom he brought back from Gib′e·on. 17 So they went and took up dwelling in the lodging place of Chim′ham that was beside Beth′le·hem, in order to go on and enter into Egypt, 18 because of the Chal·de′ans; for they had become afraid because of them, since Ish′ma·el the son of Neth·a·ni′ah had struck down Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam, whom the king of Babylon had commissioned over the land.

Jeremiah

43 Now it came about that as soon as Jeremiah finished speaking to all the people all the words of Jehovah their God with which Jehovah their God had sent him to them, even all these words, 2 Az·a·ri′ah the son of Ho·shai′ah and Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the presumptuous men proceeded to say to Jeremiah: “It is a falsehood that you are speaking. Jehovah our God has not sent you, saying, ‘Do not enter into Egypt to reside there as aliens.’ 3 But Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah is instigating you against us for the purpose of giving us into the hand of the Chal·de′ans, to put us to death or to take us into exile in Babylon.”

4 And Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the chiefs of the military forces and all the people did not obey the voice of Jehovah, to keep on dwelling in the land of Judah. 5 So Jo·ha′nan the son of Ka·re′ah and all the chiefs of the military forces took all the remnant of Judah that had returned from all the nations to which they had been dispersed, in order to reside for a while in the land of Judah, 6 even the able-bodied men and the wives and the little children and the daughters of the king and every soul that Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard had let stay with Ged·a·li′ah the son of A·hi′kam the son of Sha′phan, and Jeremiah the prophet and Bar′uch the son of Ne·ri′ah. 7 And they finally came into the land of Egypt, for they did not obey the voice of Jehovah; and they came gradually as far as Tah′pan·hes.

8 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to Jeremiah in Tah′pan·hes, saying: 9 “Take in your hand great stones, and you must hide them in the mortar in the terrace of bricks that is at the entrance of the house of Phar′aoh in Tah′pan·hes before the eyes of the Jewish men. 10 And you must say to them, ‘This is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “Here I am sending and I will take Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will place his throne right above these stones that I have hidden, and he will certainly extend his state tent over them. 11 And he must come in and strike the land of Egypt. Whoever is due for deadly plague will be for deadly plague, and whoever is due for captivity will be for captivity, and whoever is due for the sword will be for the sword. 12 And I will set a fire ablaze in the houses of the gods of Egypt; and he will certainly burn them and lead them captive and wrap himself up in the land of Egypt, just as a shepherd wraps himself up in his garment, and he will actually go out from there in peace. 13 And he will certainly break to pieces the pillars of Beth-she′mesh, which is in the land of Egypt; and the houses of the gods of Egypt he will burn with fire.”’”

Jeremiah

46 This is what occurred as the word of Jehovah to Jeremiah the prophet concerning the nations: 2 For Egypt, concerning the military force of Phar′aoh Ne′cho the king of Egypt, who happened to be by the river Eu·phra′tes at Car′che·mish, whom Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon defeated in the fourth year of Je·hoi′a·kim the son of Jo·si′ah, the king of Judah: 3 “Set in array, O men, buckler and large shield, and approach to battle. 4 Harness the horses, and mount, O YOU horsemen, and station yourselves with the helmet. Polish the lances. Clothe yourselves with coats of mail.

5 “‘Why is it that I have seen them terror-stricken? They are turning back, and their mighty men themselves are crushed to pieces; and they have positively fled, and they have not turned around. There is fright all around,’ is the utterance of Jehovah. 6 ‘Let not the swift one try to flee, and let not the mighty man try to escape. Up north by the bank of the river Eu·phra′tes they have stumbled and fallen.’

7 “Who is this one that comes up just like the Nile River, like the rivers the waters of which toss themselves? 8 Egypt itself comes up just like the Nile River, and like rivers the waters toss themselves. And it says, ‘I shall go up. I shall cover the earth. I shall readily destroy the city and those inhabiting it.’ 9 Go up, O YOU horses; and drive madly, O YOU chariots! And let the mighty men go forth, Cush and Put, who are handling the shield, and the Lu′dim, who are handling and treading the bow.

10 “And that day belongs to the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, the day of vengeance for avenging himself upon his adversaries. And the sword will certainly devour and satisfy itself and take its fill of their blood, for the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, has a sacrifice in the land of the north by the river Eu·phra′tes.

11 “Go up to Gil′e·ad and get some balsam, O virgin daughter of Egypt. In vain you have multiplied the means of healing. There is no mending for you. 12 The nations have heard your dishonor and your own outcry has filled the land. For they have stumbled, mighty man against mighty man. Together they have fallen down, both of them.”

13 The word that Jehovah spoke to Jeremiah the prophet as regards the coming of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon to strike down the land of Egypt: 14 “Tell it in Egypt, O men, and publish it in Mig′dol, and publish it in Noph and in Tah′pan·hes. Say, ‘Station yourself, making preparation also for yourself, for a sword will certainly devour all around you. 15 Why is it that your powerful ones have been washed away? They have made no stand, for Jehovah himself has pushed them away. 16 In great numbers they are stumbling. They also actually fall. And they keep saying one to the other: “Do rise up, and do let us return to our people and to the land of our relatives because of the maltreating sword.”’ 17 There they have proclaimed, ‘Phar′aoh the king of Egypt is a mere noise. He has let the festal time pass by.’

18 “‘As I am alive,’ is the utterance of the King, whose name is Jehovah of armies, ‘like Ta′bor among the mountains and like Car′mel by the sea he will come in. 19 Make for yourself mere baggage for exile, O inhabitress, the daughter of Egypt. For Noph itself will become a mere object of astonishment and will actually be set afire, so as to be without an inhabitant. 20 Egypt is as a very pretty heifer. From the north a mosquito itself will certainly come against her. 21 Furthermore, her hired soldiers in the midst of her are like fattened calves. But they themselves also have given way; they have fled together. They have not made a stand. For the very day of their disaster has come in upon them, the time of their being given attention.’

22 “‘Her voice is like that of a serpent that goes along; for with vital energy men will go, and with axes they will actually come in to her, like those who are gathering pieces of wood. 23 They will certainly cut down her forest,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘for it could not be penetrated. For they have become more numerous than the locust, and they are without number. 24 The daughter of Egypt will certainly feel shame. She will actually be given into the hand of the people of the north.’

25 “Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said, ‘Here I am turning my attention upon A′mon from No and upon Phar′aoh and upon Egypt and upon her gods and upon her kings, even upon Phar′aoh and upon all those trusting in him.’

26 “‘And I will give them into the hand of those seeking for their soul and into the hand of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon and into the hand of his servants; and afterward she will be resided in as in the days of old,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.

27 “‘And as for you, do not be afraid, O my servant Jacob, and do not be terror-stricken, O Israel. For here I am saving you from far away and your offspring from the land of their captivity. And Jacob will certainly return and have no disturbance and be at ease and without anyone causing trembling. 28 As for you, do not be afraid, O my servant Jacob,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘for I am with you. For I shall make an extermination among all the nations to which I have dispersed you, but with you I shall make no extermination. Yet I shall have to chastise you to the proper degree, and I shall absolutely not leave you unpunished.’”

Jeremiah

49 For the sons of Am′mon this is what Jehovah has said: “Are there no sons that Israel has, or is there no inheritor that he has? Why is it that Mal′cam has taken possession of Gad, and his own people have taken up dwelling in Israel’s very cities?”

2 “‘Therefore, look! there are days coming,’ is the utterance of Jehovah, ‘and I will cause the alarm signal of war to be heard even against Rab′bah of the sons of Am′mon; and she will certainly become a mound of a desolate waste, and her dependent towns themselves will be set aflame in the very fire.’

“‘And Israel will actually take possession of those in possession of him,’ Jehovah has said.

3 “‘Howl, O Hesh′bon, for A′i has been despoiled! Cry out, O dependent towns of Rab′bah. Gird sackcloth on yourselves. Wail, and rove about among the stone pens, for Mal′cam himself will go even into exile, his priests and his princes, all together. 4 Why do you brag about the low plains, your flowing low plain, O daughter unfaithful, you the one trusting in her treasures, saying: “Who will come to me?”’”

5 “‘Here I am bringing in upon you a dreadful thing,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord, Jehovah of armies, ‘from all those round about you. And YOU people will certainly be dispersed, each one in his own direction, and there will be no one collecting together those running away.’”

6 “‘But afterward I shall gather the captive ones of the sons of Am′mon,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

7 For E′dom this is what Jehovah of armies has said: “Is there no longer any wisdom in Te′man? Has counsel perished from those having understanding? Has their wisdom gone to putrefying? 8 Flee! Let yourselves give way! Go down deep in order to dwell, O inhabitants of De′dan! For the disaster of E′sau I will bring in upon him, the time that I must turn my attention to him. 9 If grape gatherers themselves actually came in to you, would they not let some gleanings remain? If thieves came in by night, they would certainly cause only as much ruin as they wanted. 10 But as for me, I will strip E′sau bare. I will uncover his places of concealment, and one will not be able to hide oneself. His offspring and his brothers and his neighbors will certainly be despoiled, and he will not be. 11 Do leave your fatherless boys. I myself shall preserve them alive, and your own widows will trust even in me.”

12 For this is what Jehovah has said: “Look! Although it is not their custom to drink the cup, they will drink without fail. And you yourself, will you be absolutely left unpunished? You will not be left unpunished, for you will drink without fail.”

13 “For by my own self I have sworn,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “that nothing but an object of astonishment, a reproach, a devastation and a malediction will Boz′rah become; and all her own cities will become devastated places to time indefinite.”

14 There is a report that I have heard from Jehovah, and there is an envoy that is sent among the nations, saying: “Collect yourselves together, and come against her, and rise up to battle.”

15 “For, look! I have made you small indeed among the nations, despised among mankind. 16 The shuddering you caused has deceived you, the presumptuousness of your heart, O you who are residing in the retreats of the crag, holding the height of the hill. Although you build your nest high up just like an eagle, down from there I shall bring you,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 17 “And E′dom must become an object of astonishment. Everyone passing along by her will stare in astonishment and whistle on account of all her plagues. 18 Just as in the overthrow of Sod′om and Go·mor′rah and her neighbor towns,” Jehovah has said, “no man will dwell there, and no son of mankind will reside in her as an alien.

19 “Look! Someone will come up just like a lion from the proud thickets along the Jordan to the durable abiding place, but in a moment I will make him run away from her. And the one who is chosen I shall appoint over her. For who is like me, and who will challenge me, and who, now, is the shepherd that can stand before me? 20 Therefore hear, O men, the counsel of Jehovah that he has formulated against E′dom, and his thoughts that he has thought out against the inhabitants of Te′man: Surely the little ones of the flock will be dragged about. Surely on account of them he will make their dwelling place become desolate. 21 At the sound of their falling the earth has begun to rock. There is an outcry! The sound of it has been heard even at the Red Sea. 22 Look! Just like an eagle someone will ascend and pounce down, and he will spread out his wings over Boz′rah; and the heart of the mighty men of E′dom will actually become in that day like the heart of the wife having distress in childbirth.”

23 For Damascus: “Ha′math and Ar′pad have become ashamed, for it is a bad report that they have heard. They have disintegrated. In the sea there is anxious care; it is not able to keep undisturbed. 24 Damascus has lost courage. She has turned to flee, and sheer panic has seized her. Distress and birth pangs themselves have taken hold of her, as with a woman that is giving birth. 25 How is it that the city of praise has not been abandoned, the town of exultation?

26 “Therefore her young men will fall in her public squares, and all the men of war themselves will be brought to silence in that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies. 27 “And I will set a fire ablaze on the wall of Damascus, and it will certainly devour the dwelling towers of Ben-ha′dad.”

28 For Ke′dar and the kingdoms of Ha′zor, which Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon struck down, this is what Jehovah has said: “Rise up, go up to Ke′dar, O men, and despoil the sons of the East. 29 Their own tents and their own flocks will be taken, their tent cloths and all their articles. And their own camels will be carried off from them. And they will certainly cry out to them, ‘Fright is all around!’”

30 “Flee, take flight far away; go down deep in order to dwell, O inhabitants of Ha′zor,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “For Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon has formulated a counsel even against YOU and has thought out against YOU a thought.”

31 “Rise up, O men, go up against the nation that is at ease, dwelling in security!” is the utterance of Jehovah.

“No doors and no bar does it have. Solitary they reside. 32 And their camels must become a plunder, and the multitude of their livestock a spoil. And I will scatter them to every wind, those who have their hair clipped at the temples; and from all regions near it I shall bring in their disaster,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 33 “And Ha′zor must become the lair of jackals, a desolate waste to time indefinite. No man will dwell there, and in her no son of mankind will reside as an alien.”

34 This is what occurred as the word of Jehovah to Jeremiah the prophet concerning E′lam in the beginning of the kingship of Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah, saying: 35 “This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘Here I am breaking the bow of E′lam, the beginning of their mightiness. 36 And I will bring in upon E′lam the four winds from the four extremities of the heavens. And I will scatter them to all these winds, and there will prove to be no nation to which the dispersed ones of E′lam will not come.’”

37 “And I will shatter the E′lam·ites before their enemies and before those seeking for their soul; and I will bring upon them a calamity, my burning anger,” is the utterance of Jehovah. “And I will send after them the sword until I shall have exterminated them.”

38 “And I will set my throne in E′lam, and I will destroy out of there the king and the princes,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

39 “And it will certainly occur in the final part of the days that I shall gather the captive ones of E′lam,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

Jeremiah

51 This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am rousing up against Babylon and against the inhabitants of Leb-ka′mai a ruinous wind; 2 and I will send to Babylon winnowers who will certainly winnow her and who will make her land empty; for they will actually prove to be against her on all sides in the day of calamity.

3 “Let the one treading his bow do no treading. And let no one raise himself up in his coat of mail.

“And do not YOU men show any compassion for her young men. Devote to destruction all her army. 4 And they must fall slain in the land of the Chal·de′ans and pierced through in her streets.

5 “For Israel and Judah are not widowed from their God, from Jehovah of armies. For the land of those has been full of guilt from the standpoint of the Holy One of Israel.

6 “FLEE out of the midst of Babylon, and provide escape each one for his own soul. Do not be rendered inanimate through her error. For it is the time of vengeance belonging to Jehovah. There is treatment that he is paying back to her. 7 Babylon has been a golden cup in the hand of Jehovah, she making all the earth drunk. From her wine the nations have drunk. That is why the nations keep acting crazed. 8 Suddenly Babylon has fallen, so that she is broken. Howl over her, YOU people. Take balsam for her pain. Perhaps she may be healed.”

9 “We would have healed Babylon, but she has not been healed. Leave her, YOU people, and let us go each one to his own land. For clear to the heavens her judgment has reached, and it has been lifted up to the cloudy skies. 10 Jehovah has brought forth deeds of righteousness for us. Come and do let us recount in Zion the work of Jehovah our God.”

11 “Polish the arrows. Fill the circular shields, O men. Jehovah has aroused the spirit of the kings of the Medes, because it is against Babylon that his idea is, in order to bring her to ruin. For it is the vengeance of Jehovah, the vengeance for his temple. 12 Against the walls of Babylon lift up a signal. Make strong the watch. Post the watchmen. Make ready those lying in ambush. For Jehovah both has formed the idea and will certainly do what he has spoken against the inhabitants of Babylon.”

13 “O woman residing on abounding waters, abundant in treasures, your end has come, the measure of your profit making. 14 Jehovah of armies has sworn by his own soul, ‘I will fill you with men, like the locusts, and they will certainly sing forth over you a shout.’ 15 He is the Maker of the earth by his power, the One firmly establishing the productive land by his wisdom, and the One who by his understanding stretched out the heavens. 16 At his voice there is a giving by him of a turmoil of waters in the heavens, and he causes vapors to ascend from the extremity of the earth. He has made even sluices for the rain, and he brings forth the wind from his storehouses. 17 Every man has behaved so unreasoningly as not to know. Every metalworker will feel ashamed because of the carved image; for his molten image is a falsehood, and there is no spirit in them. 18 They are vanity, a work of mockery. In the time of their being given attention they will perish.

19 “The Share of Jacob is not like these things, for he is the Former of everything, even the staff of his inheritance. Jehovah of armies is his name.”

20 “You are a club for me, as weapons of war, and by you I shall certainly dash nations to pieces, and by you I will bring kingdoms to ruin. 21 And by you I will dash the horse and his rider to pieces, and by you I will dash the war chariot and its rider to pieces. 22 And by you I will dash man and woman to pieces, and by you I will dash old man and boy to pieces, and by you I will dash young man and virgin to pieces. 23 And by you I will dash shepherd and his drove to pieces, and by you I will dash farmer and his span of animals to pieces, and by you I will dash governors and deputy rulers to pieces. 24 And I will pay back to Babylon and to all the inhabitants of Chal·de′a all their badness that they have committed in Zion before the eyes of YOU people,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

25 “Here I am against you, O ruinous mountain,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “you ruiner of the whole earth; and I will stretch out my hand against you and roll you away from the crags and make you a burnt-out mountain.”

26 “And people will not take from you a stone for a corner or a stone for foundations, because desolate wastes to time indefinite are what you will become,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

27 “Lift up a signal in the land, O men. Blow a horn among the nations. Sanctify against her the nations. Summon against her the kingdoms of Ar′a·rat, Min′ni and Ash′ke·naz. Commission against her a recruiting officer. Make the horses come up like bristly locusts. 28 Sanctify against her the nations, the kings of Me′di·a, its governors and all its deputy rulers and all the land of each one’s dominion. 29 And let the earth rock and be in severe pain, for against Babylon the thoughts of Jehovah have risen up to make the land of Babylon an object of astonishment, without an inhabitant.

30 “The mighty men of Babylon have ceased to fight. They have kept sitting in the strong places. Their mightiness has run dry. They have become women. Her residences have been set on fire. Her bars have been broken.

31 “One runner runs to meet another runner, and one reporter to meet another reporter, to report to the king of Babylon that his city has been captured at every end, 32 and that the fords themselves have been seized, and the papyrus boats they have burned with fire, and the men of war themselves have become disturbed.”

33 For this is what Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, has said: “The daughter of Babylon is like a threshing floor. It is the time to tread her down solid. Yet a little while and the time of the harvest must come for her.”

34 “Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon has eaten me up; he has thrown me into confusion. He has set me as an empty vessel. He has swallowed me down like a big snake; he has filled his abdomen with my pleasant things. He has rinsed me away. 35 ‘The violence done to me and to my organism be upon Babylon!’ the inhabitress of Zion will say. ‘And my blood be upon the inhabitants of Chal·de′a!’ Jerusalem will say.”

36 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am conducting your legal case, and I shall certainly execute vengeance for you. And I will dry up her sea, and I will make her wells dry. 37 And Babylon must become piles of stones, the lair of jackals, an object of astonishment and something to whistle at, without an inhabitant. 38 All together they will roar just like maned young lions. They will certainly growl like the whelps of lions.”

39 “When they are heated I shall set their banquets and I will make them drunk, in order that they may exult; and they must sleep an indefinitely lasting sleep, from which they will not wake up,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 40 “I shall bring them down like male sheep to the slaughtering, like rams along with the he-goats.”

41 “O how She′shach has been captured, and how the Praise of the whole earth gets to be seized! How Babylon has become a mere object of astonishment among the nations! 42 The sea has come up even over Babylon. By the multitude of its waves she has been covered. 43 Her cities have become an object of astonishment, a waterless land and a desert plain. As a land, in them no man will dwell, and through them no son of mankind will pass. 44 And I will turn my attention upon Bel in Babylon, and I will bring forth out of his mouth what he has swallowed. And to him nations will stream no more. Also, the wall itself of Babylon must fall.

45 “Get out of the midst of her, O my people, and provide each one his soul with escape from the burning anger of Jehovah. 46 Or otherwise YOUR heart will be timid, and YOU will become afraid because of the report that is to be heard in the land. And in one year the report will actually come, and after it in another year there will be the report and violence in the earth and ruler against ruler. 47 Therefore, look! there are days coming, and I will turn my attention upon the graven images of Babylon; and all her own land will become ashamed, and all her own slain ones will fall in the midst of her.

48 “And over Babylon the heavens and the earth and all that is in them will certainly cry out joyfully, for out of the north there will come to her the despoilers,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 49 “Not only was Babylon the cause for the slain ones of Israel to fall but also at Babylon the slain ones of all the earth have fallen.

50 “YOU escapees from the sword, keep going. Do not stand still. From far away remember Jehovah, and may Jerusalem herself come up into YOUR heart.”

51 “We have been put to shame, for we have heard reproach. Humiliation has covered our faces, for strangers have come against the holy places of the house of Jehovah.”

52 “Therefore, look! there are days coming,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “and I will turn my attention upon her graven images, and throughout all her land the pierced one will groan.”

53 “Even if Babylon should ascend to the heavens and even if she should make the height of her strength unapproachable, from me the despoilers will come to her,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

54 “Listen! There is an outcry from Babylon, and a great crash from the land of the Chal·de′ans, 55 for Jehovah is despoiling Babylon, and he will certainly destroy out of her the great voice, and their waves will actually be boisterous like many waters. The noise of their voice will certainly be given out. 56 For there must come upon her, upon Babylon, the despoiler, and her mighty men will certainly be captured. Their bows must be shattered, for Jehovah is a God of recompenses. Without fail he will repay. 57 And I will make her princes and her wise ones, her governors and her deputy rulers and her mighty men drunk, and they must sleep an indefinitely lasting sleep, from which they will not wake up,” is the utterance of the King, whose name is Jehovah of armies.

58 This is what Jehovah of armies has said: “The wall of Babylon, although broad, will without fail be demolished; and her gates, although high, will be set aflame with fire. And the peoples will have to toil for simply nothing, and national groups simply for the fire; and they will just tire themselves out.”

59 The word that Jeremiah the prophet commanded Se·rai′ah the son of Ne·ri′ah the son of Mah·sei′ah when he went with Zed·e·ki′ah the king of Judah to Babylon in the fourth year of his being king; and Se·rai′ah was the quartermaster. 60 And Jeremiah proceeded to write in one book all the calamity that would come upon Babylon, even all these words written against Babylon. 61 Furthermore, Jeremiah said to Se·rai′ah: “As soon as you come to Babylon and actually see her, you must also read aloud all these words. 62 And you must say, ‘O Jehovah, you yourself have spoken against this place, in order to cut it off so that there may come to be in it no inhabitant, either man or even domestic animal, but that she may become mere desolate wastes to time indefinite.’ 63 And it must occur that when you will have completed reading this book, you will tie to it a stone, and you must pitch it into the midst of the Eu·phra′tes. 64 And you must say, ‘This is how Babylon will sink down and never rise up because of the calamity that I am bringing in upon her; and they will certainly tire themselves out.’”

Down to this point are the words of Jeremiah.

Jeremiah

52 Zed·e·ki′ah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign, and for eleven years he reigned in Jerusalem. And the name of his mother was Ha·mu′tal the daughter of Jeremiah of Lib′nah. 2 And he continued to do what was bad in the eyes of Jehovah, according to all that Je·hoi′a·kim had done. 3 For on account of the anger of Jehovah it occurred in Jerusalem and Judah, until he had cast them out from before his face. And Zed·e·ki′ah proceeded to rebel against the king of Babylon. 4 Finally it came about in the ninth year of his being king, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, that Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon came, he and all his military force, against Jerusalem, and they began to camp against her and to build against her a siege wall all around. 5 So the city came under siege until the eleventh year of King Zed·e·ki′ah.

6 In the fourth month, on the ninth day of the month, the famine also got to be severe in the city and there proved to be no bread for the people of the land. 7 Finally the city was broken through; and as regards all the men of war, they began to run away and go forth from the city by night by the way of the gate between the double wall that is by the king’s garden, while the Chal·de′ans were all around against the city; and they kept going by the way of the Ar′a·bah. 8 And a military force of the Chal·de′ans went chasing after the king, and they got to overtake Zed·e·ki′ah in the desert plains of Jer′i·cho; and all his own military force was scattered from his side. 9 Then they seized the king and brought him up to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math, that he might pronounce upon him judicial decisions. 10 And the king of Babylon proceeded to slaughter the sons of Zed·e·ki′ah before his eyes, and also all the princes of Judah he slaughtered in Rib′lah. 11 And the eyes of Zed·e·ki′ah he blinded, after which the king of Babylon bound him with copper fetters and brought him to Babylon and put him in the house of custody until the day of his death.

12 And in the fifth month, on the tenth day of the month, that is, in the nineteenth year of King Neb·u·chad·rez′zar, the king of Babylon, Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard, who was standing before the king of Babylon, came into Jerusalem. 13 And he proceeded to burn the house of Jehovah and the house of the king and all the houses of Jerusalem; and every great house he burned with fire. 14 And all the walls of Jerusalem, round about, all the military forces of the Chal·de′ans that were with the chief of the bodyguard pulled down.

15 And some of the lowly ones of the people and the rest of the people that were left remaining in the city and the deserters that had fallen away to the king of Babylon and the rest of the master workmen Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard took into exile. 16 And some of the lowly ones of the land Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard let remain as vinedressers and as compulsory laborers.

17 And the copper pillars that belonged to the house of Jehovah and the carriages and the copper sea that was in the house of Jehovah the Chal·de′ans broke to pieces and went carrying all the copper of them to Babylon. 18 And the cans and the shovels and the extinguishers and the bowls and the cups and all the copper utensils with which they used to minister they took. 19 And the basins and the fire holders and the bowls and the cans and the lampstands and the cups and the bowls that were of genuine gold, and those that were of genuine silver, the chief of the bodyguard took. 20 And the two pillars, the one sea, and the twelve copper bulls that were under the sea, the carriages, that King Sol′o·mon had made for the house of Jehovah. There happened to be no weight taken of the copper of them—all these articles.

21 And as regards the pillars, eighteen cubits in height was each pillar, and a thread of twelve cubits itself would go around it; and its thickness was four fingerbreadths, it being hollow. 22 And the capital upon it was of copper, and the height of the one capital was five cubits; and as regards the network and the pomegranates upon the capital, all around, the whole was of copper; and the second pillar had just the same as these, also the pomegranates. 23 And the pomegranates came to be ninety-six, on the sides, all the pomegranates being one hundred upon the network round about.

24 Furthermore, the chief of the bodyguard took Se·rai′ah the chief priest and Zeph·a·ni′ah the second priest and the three doorkeepers, 25 and from the city he took one court official that happened to be commissioner over the men of war, and seven men of those having access to the king, who were found in the city, and the secretary of the chief of the army, the one mustering the people of the land, and sixty men of the people of the land, who were found in the midst of the city. 26 So these Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard took and conducted them to the king of Babylon at Rib′lah. 27 And these the king of Babylon proceeded to strike down and to put them to death in Rib′lah in the land of Ha′math. Thus Judah went into exile from off its soil.

28 These are the people whom Neb·u·chad·rez′zar took into exile: in the seventh year, three thousand and twenty-three Jews.

29 In the eighteenth year of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar, from Jerusalem there were eight hundred and thirty-two souls.

30 In the twenty-third year of Neb·u·chad·rez′zar, Neb·u′zar·ad′an the chief of the bodyguard took Jews into exile, seven hundred and forty-five souls.

All the souls were four thousand and six hundred.

31 At length it came about in the thirty-seventh year of the exile of Je·hoi′a·chin the king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-fifth day of the month, that E′vil-mer′o·dach the king of Babylon, in the year of his becoming king, raised up the head of Je·hoi′a·chin the king of Judah and proceeded to bring him forth from the prison house. 32 And he began to speak with him good things and to put his throne higher than the thrones of the other kings that were with him in Babylon. 33 And he took off his prison garments, and he ate bread before him constantly all the days of his life. 34 And as for his allowance, there was a constant allowance given him from the king of Babylon, daily as due, until the day of his death, all the days of his life.

Lamentations

א [ʼA′leph]

4 O how the gold that shines becomes dim, the good gold!

O how the holy stones are poured out at the head of all the streets!

ב [Behth]

2 As for the precious sons of Zion, those who were weighed against refined gold,

O how they have been reckoned as large jars of earthenware, the work of the hands of a potter!

ג [Gi′mel]

3 Even jackals themselves have presented the udder. They have suckled their cubs.

The daughter of my people becomes cruel, like ostriches in the wilderness.

ד [Da′leth]

4 The tongue of the suckling has cleaved to its palate because of thirst.

Children themselves have asked for bread. There is no one dealing it out to them.

ה [Heʼ]

5 The very ones that were eating pleasant things have been struck with astonishment in the streets.

The very ones that were being reared in scarlet have had to embrace ash heaps.

ו [Waw]

6 The punishment for the error of the daughter of my people also becomes greater than the punishment for the sin of Sod′om,

Which was overthrown as in a moment, and to which no hands turned helpfully.

ז [Za′yin]

7 Her Naz′i·rites were purer than snow; they were whiter than milk.

They were in fact more ruddy than corals; their polish was as the sapphire.

ח [Chehth]

8 Their aspect has become darker than blackness itself. They have not been recognized in the streets.

Their skin has shriveled upon their bones. It has become just as dry as a tree.

ט [Tehth]

9 Better have those slain with the sword proved to be than those slain by famine,

Because these pine away, pierced through for lack of the produce of the open field.

י [Yohdh]

10 The very hands of compassionate women have boiled their own children.

They have become as bread of consolation to one during the breakdown of the daughter of my people.

כ [Kaph]

11 Jehovah has accomplished his rage. He has poured out his burning anger.

And he sets a fire ablaze in Zion, which eats up her foundations.

ל [La′medh]

12 The kings of the earth and all the inhabitants of the productive land had not believed

That the adversary and the enemy would come into the gates of Jerusalem.

מ [Mem]

13 Because of the sins of her prophets, the errors of her priests,

There were in the midst of her those pouring out the blood of righteous ones.

נ [Nun]

14 They have wandered about as blind in the streets. They have become polluted with blood,

So that none are able to touch their garments.

ס [Sa′mekh]

15 “Get out of the way! Unclean!” they have called out to them. “Get out of the way! Get out of the way! Do not touch!”

For they have gone homeless. They have also wandered about. People have said among the nations: “They will not reside again as aliens.

פ [Peʼ]

16 The face of Jehovah has divided them up. He will not look upon them again.

Men will certainly show no consideration even for the priests. They will certainly show no favor even to the old men.”

ע [ʽA′yin]

17 While we yet are, our eyes keep pining away in vain for assistance to us.

During our looking about we have looked out to a nation that can bring no salvation.

צ [Tsa·dheh′]

18 They have hunted our steps so that there is no walking in our public squares.

Our end has drawn near. Our days have come to their full, for our end has come.

ק [Qohph]

19 Swifter than the eagles of the heavens our pursuers have proved to be.

Upon the mountains they have hotly pursued us. In the wilderness they have lain in wait for us.

ר [Rehsh]

20 The very breath of our nostrils, the anointed one of Jehovah, has been captured in their large pit,

The one of whom we have said: “In his shade we shall live among the nations.”

ש [Sin]

21 Exult and rejoice, O daughter of E′dom, dwelling as you do in the land of Uz.

To you also the cup will pass along. You will become drunk and show yourself in nakedness.

ת [Taw]

22 Your error, O daughter of Zion, has come to its finish. He will not carry you off into exile again.

He has turned his attention to your error, O daughter of E′dom. He has uncovered your sins.

Ezekiel

2 And he proceeded to say to me: “Son of man, stand up upon your feet that I may speak with you.” 2 And spirit began to come into me as soon as he spoke to me, and it finally made me stand up upon my feet that I might hear the One speaking to me.

3 And he went on to say to me: “Son of man, I am sending you to the sons of Israel, to rebellious nations that have rebelled against me. They themselves and their forefathers have transgressed against me down to this selfsame day. 4 And the sons insolent of face and hard of heart—I am sending you to them, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said.’ 5 And as for them, whether they will hear or will refrain—for they are a rebellious house—they will certainly know also that a prophet himself happened to be in the midst of them.

6 “And you, O son of man, do not be afraid of them; and of their words do not be afraid, because there are obstinate ones and things pricking you and it is among scorpions that you are dwelling. Of their words do not you be afraid, and at their faces do not you be struck with terror, for they are a rebellious house. 7 And you must speak my words to them, regardless of whether they hear or they refrain, for they are a case of rebellion.

8 “And you, O son of man, hear what I am speaking to you. Do not become rebellious like the rebellious house. Open your mouth and eat what I am giving you.”

9 And I began to see, and, look! there was a hand thrust out to me, and, look! in it there was the roll of a book. 10 And he gradually spread it out before me, and it was written upon in front and on the back; and there were written in it dirges and moaning and wailing.

Ezekiel

5 “And as for you, O son of man, take for yourself a sharp sword. As a barbers’ razor you will take it for yourself, and you must make it pass along upon your head and upon your beard, and you must take for yourself weighing scales and divide the hair in portions. 2 A third you will burn in the very fire in the midst of the city as soon as the days of the siege have come to the full. And you must take another third. You will strike it with the sword all around her, and the last third you will scatter to the wind, and I shall draw out a sword itself after them.

3 “And you must take therefrom a few in number and wrap them up in your skirts. 4 And others of them you will take and you must pitch them into the midst of the fire and incinerate them in the fire. From one a fire will go forth to all the house of Israel.

5 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘This is Jerusalem. In the midst of the nations I have set her, with lands all around her. 6 And she proceeded to behave rebelliously against my judicial decisions in wickedness more than the nations, and against my statutes more than the lands that are all around her, for my judicial decisions they rejected and, as for my statutes, they did not walk in them.’

7 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that YOU people were more turbulent than the nations that are all around YOU, in my statutes YOU did not walk and my judicial decisions YOU did not perform; but according to the judicial decisions of the nations that are all around YOU, YOU performed, did YOU not? 8 therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, O city, even I, and I will execute in the midst of you judicial decisions in the eyes of the nations. 9 And I will do in you that which I have not done and the like of which I shall not do anymore by reason of all your detestable things.

10 “‘“Therefore fathers themselves will eat sons in the midst of you, and sons themselves will eat their fathers, and I will execute in you acts of judgment and scatter all the remainder of you to every wind.”’

11 “‘Therefore as I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘surely for the reason that it was my sanctuary that you defiled with all your disgusting things and with all your detestable things, I myself also am the One that will diminish you and my eye will not feel sorry and I myself also will not show compassion. 12 A third of you—by the pestilence they will die, and by famine they will come to their end in the midst of you. And another third—by the sword they will fall all around you. And the last third I shall scatter even to every wind, and a sword is what I shall draw out after them. 13 And my anger will certainly come to its finish and I will appease my rage on them and comfort myself; and they will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have spoken in my insistence on exclusive devotion, when I bring my rage to its finish upon them.

14 “‘And I shall make you a devastated place and a reproach among the nations that are all around you before the eyes of every passerby. 15 And you must become a reproach and an object of reviling words, a warning example and a horror to the nations that are all around you, when I do in you acts of judgment in anger and in rage and in raging reproofs. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken.

16 “‘When I send the injurious arrows of the famine upon them, which must prove to be for ruination, which arrows I shall send to bring YOU people to ruin, even famine I shall increase upon YOU people and I will break YOUR rods around which ring-shaped loaves are suspended. 17 And I will send upon YOU people famine and injurious wild beasts, and they must bereave you of children, and pestilence and blood themselves will pass along through you, and a sword I shall bring in upon you. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken.’”

Ezekiel

9 And he proceeded to call out in my ears with a loud voice, saying: “HAVE those giving their attention to the city come near, each one with his weapon in his hand for bringing ruin!”

2 And, look! there were six men coming from the direction of the upper gate that faces to the north, each one with his weapon for smashing in his hand; and there was one man in among them clothed with linen, with a secretary’s inkhorn at his hips, and they proceeded to come in and stand beside the copper altar.

3 And as regards the glory of the God of Israel, it was taken up from over the cherubs over which it happened to be to the threshold of the house, and he began calling out to the man that was clothed with the linen, at whose hips there was the secretary’s inkhorn. 4 And Jehovah went on to say to him: “Pass through the midst of the city, through the midst of Jerusalem, and you must put a mark on the foreheads of the men that are sighing and groaning over all the detestable things that are being done in the midst of it.”

5 And to these others he said in my ears: “Pass through the city after him and strike. Let not YOUR eye feel sorry, and do not feel any compassion. 6 Old man, young man and virgin and little child and women YOU should kill off—to a ruination. But to any man upon whom there is the mark do not go near, and from my sanctuary YOU should start.” So they started with the old men that were before the house. 7 And he said further to them: “Defile the house and fill the courtyards with the slain ones. Go forth!” And they went forth and struck in the city.

8 And it came about that, while they were striking and I was left remaining, I proceeded to fall upon my face and cry out and say: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Are you bringing to ruin all the remaining ones of Israel while you are pouring out your rage upon Jerusalem?”

9 So he said to me: “The error of the house of Israel and Judah is very, very great, and the land is filled with bloodshed and the city is full of crookedness; for they have said, ‘Jehovah has left the land, and Jehovah is not seeing.’ 10 And as for me also, my eye will not feel sorry, neither shall I show compassion. Their way I shall certainly bring upon their own head.”

11 And, look! the man clothed with the linen, at whose hips there was the inkhorn, was bringing back word, saying: “I have done just as you have commanded me.”

Ezekiel

11 And a spirit proceeded to lift me up and bring me to the eastern gate of the house of Jehovah that is facing eastward, and, look! in the entrance of the gate there were twenty-five men, and I got to see in the midst of them Ja·az·a·ni′ah the son of Az′zur and Pel·a·ti′ah the son of Be·nai′ah, princes of the people. 2 Then he said to me: “Son of man, these are the men that are scheming hurtfulness and advising bad counsel against this city; 3 that are saying, ‘Is not the building of houses close at hand? She is the widemouthed cooking pot, and we are the flesh.’

4 “Therefore prophesy against them. Prophesy, O son of man.”

5 Then the spirit of Jehovah fell upon me, and he went on to say to me: “Say, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “YOU people said the right thing, O house of Israel; and as regards the things that come up in YOUR spirit, I myself have known it. 6 YOU have caused YOUR slain ones in this city to be many, and YOU have filled her streets with the slain ones.”’” 7 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘As regards YOUR slain ones whom YOU people have put in the midst of her, they are the flesh, and she is the widemouthed cooking pot; and there will be a bringing forth of YOU yourselves out of the midst of her.’”

8 “‘A sword YOU have feared, and a sword I shall bring upon YOU,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 9 ‘And I shall certainly bring YOU forth out of the midst of her and give YOU into the hand of strangers and execute upon YOU acts of judgment. 10 By the sword YOU will fall. On the border of Israel I shall judge YOU people; and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah. 11 She herself will not prove to be for YOU a widemouthed cooking pot, and YOU yourselves will not prove to be flesh in the midst of her. On the border of Israel I shall judge YOU, 12 and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah, because in my regulations YOU did not walk and my judgments YOU did not do, but according to the judgments of the nations that are round about YOU, YOU have done.’”

13 And it came about that as soon as I prophesied Pel·a·ti′ah the son of Be·nai′ah himself died, and I proceeded to fall upon my face and cry with a loud voice and say: “Alas, O Sovereign Lord Jehovah! Is it an extermination that you are executing with the remaining ones of Israel?”

14 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 15 “Son of man, as regards your brothers, your brothers, the men concerned with your right to repurchase, and all the house of Israel, all of it, are the ones to whom the inhabitants of Jerusalem have said, ‘Get far away from Jehovah. To us it belongs; the land has been given us as a thing to possess’; 16 therefore say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Although I have put them far away among the nations, and although I have scattered them among the lands, yet I shall become to them a sanctuary for a little while among the lands to which they have come.”’

17 “Therefore say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “I will also collect YOU from the peoples and gather YOU from the lands among which YOU have been scattered, and I will give YOU the soil of Israel. 18 And they will certainly come there and remove all its disgusting things and all its detestable things out of it. 19 And I will give them one heart, and a new spirit I shall put inside them; and I shall certainly remove the heart of stone from their flesh and give them a heart of flesh, 20 in order that they may walk in my own statutes and keep my own judicial decisions and actually carry them out; and they may really become my people and I myself may become their God.”’

21 “‘“But as for those whose heart is walking in their disgusting things and their detestable things, upon their head I shall certainly bring their own way,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.’”

22 And the cherubs now lifted up their wings, and the wheels were close by them, and the glory of the God of Israel was over them, from above. 23 And the glory of Jehovah went ascending from over the midst of the city and began to stand over the mountain that is to the east of the city. 24 And a spirit itself lifted me up and finally brought me to Chal·de′a to the exiled people, in the vision by the spirit of God; and the vision that I had seen went ascending from upon me. 25 And I began to speak to the exiled people all the things of Jehovah that he had caused me to see.

Ezekiel

13 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, prophesy concerning the prophets of Israel who are prophesying, and you must say to those prophesying out of their own heart, ‘Hear the word of Jehovah. 3 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Woe to the stupid prophets, who are walking after their own spirit, when there is nothing that they have seen! 4 Like foxes in the devastated places are what your own prophets have become, O Israel. 5 YOU men will certainly not go up into the gaps, neither will YOU build up a stone wall in behalf of the house of Israel, in order to stand in the battle in the day of Jehovah.” 6 “They have visioned what is untrue and a lying divination, those who are saying, ‘The utterance of Jehovah is,’ when Jehovah himself has not sent them, and they have waited to have a word come true. 7 Is it not an untrue vision that YOU men have visioned, and a lying divination that YOU have said, when saying, ‘The utterance of Jehovah is,’ when I myself have spoken nothing?”’

8 “‘Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “‘For the reason that YOU men have spoken untruth and YOU have visioned a lie, therefore here I am against YOU,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.” 9 And my hand has come to be against the prophets that are visioning untruth and that are divining a lie. In the intimate group of my people they will not continue on, and in the register of the house of Israel they will not be written, and to the soil of Israel they will not come; and YOU people will have to know that I am the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, 10 for the reason, yes, for the reason that they have led my people astray, saying, “There is peace!” when there is no peace, and there is one that is building a partition wall, but in vain there are those plastering it with whitewash.’

11 “Say to those plastering with whitewash that it will fall. A flooding downpour will certainly occur, and YOU, O hailstones, will fall, and a blast of windstorms itself will cause a splitting. 12 And, look! the wall must fall. Will it not be said to YOU men, ‘Where is the coating with which YOU did the plastering?’

13 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘I will also cause a blast of windstorms to burst forth in my rage, and in my anger there will occur a flooding downpour, and in rage there will be hailstones for an extermination. 14 And I will tear down the wall that YOU men have plastered with whitewash and bring it into contact with the earth, and its foundation must be exposed. And she will certainly fall, and YOU must come to an end in the midst of her; and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

15 “‘And I will bring my rage to its finish upon the wall and upon those plastering it with whitewash, and I shall say to YOU men: “The wall is no more, and those plastering it are no more, 16 the prophets of Israel that are prophesying to Jerusalem and that are visioning for her a vision of peace, when there is no peace,”’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

17 “And as for you, O son of man, set your face against the daughters of your people who are acting as prophetesses out of their own heart, and prophesy against them. 18 And you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Woe to the women sewing bands together upon all elbows and making veils upon the head of every size in order to hunt souls! Are the souls that YOU women hunt down the ones belonging to my people, and the souls belonging to YOU the ones that YOU preserve alive? 19 And will YOU profane me toward my people for the handfuls of barley and for the morsels of bread, in order to put to death the souls that ought not to die and in order to preserve alive the souls that ought not to live by YOUR lie to my people, the hearers of a lie?”’

20 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am against the bands of YOU women, with which YOU are hunting down the souls as though they were flying things, and I will rip them from off YOUR arms and let go the souls that YOU are hunting down, souls as though they were flying things. 21 And I will rip away YOUR veils and deliver my people out of YOUR hand, and they will no more prove to be in YOUR hand something caught in the hunt; and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah. 22 By reason of dejecting the heart of a righteous one with falsehood, when I myself had not caused him pain, and for making the hands of a wicked one strong so that he would not turn back from his bad way in order to preserve him alive, 23 therefore untruth YOU women will not keep on visioning, and divination YOU will divine no longer; and I will deliver my people out of YOUR hand, and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah.’”

Ezekiel

17 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, propound a riddle and compose a proverbial saying toward the house of Israel. 3 And you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “The great eagle, having great wings, with long pinions, full of plumage, which had color variety, came to Leb′a·non and proceeded to take the treetop of the cedar. 4 He plucked off the very top of its young shoots and came bringing it to the land of Ca′naan; in a city of traders he placed it. 5 Furthermore, he took some of the seed of the land and put it in a field for seed. As a willow by vast waters, as a willow tree he placed it. 6 And it began to sprout and gradually became a luxuriantly growing vine low in height, inclined to turn its foliage inward; and as for its roots, they gradually came to be under it. And it finally became a vine and produced shoots and sent forth branches.

7 “‘“And there came to be another great eagle, having great wings, and having large pinions, and, look! this very vine stretched its roots hungrily toward him. And its foliage it thrust out to him in order for him to irrigate it, away from the garden beds where it was planted. 8 Into a good field, by vast waters, it was already transplanted, in order to produce boughs and to bear fruit, to become a majestic vine.”’

9 “Say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Will it have success? Will not someone tear out its very roots and make its very fruit scaly? And must not all its freshly plucked sprouts become dry? It will become dry. Neither by a great arm nor by a multitudinous people will it have to be lifted up from its roots. 10 And, look! although transplanted, will it have success? Will it not dry up completely, even as when the east wind touches it? In the garden beds of its sprout it will dry up.”’”

11 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 12 “Say, please, to the rebellious house, ‘Do YOU people actually not know what these things mean?’ Say, ‘Look! The king of Babylon came to Jerusalem and proceeded to take its king and its princes and bring them to himself at Babylon. 13 Furthermore, he took one of the royal seed and concluded a covenant with him and brought him into an oath; and the foremost men of the land he took away, 14 in order that the kingdom might become low, unable to lift itself up, that by keeping his covenant it might stand. 15 But he finally rebelled against him in sending his messengers to Egypt, for it to give him horses and a multitudinous people. Will he have success? Will he escape, he who is doing these things, and who has broken a covenant? And will he actually escape?’

16 “‘“As I am alive,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, “in the place of the king who put in as king the one that despised his oath and that broke his covenant, with him in the midst of Babylon he will die. 17 And by a great military force and by a multitudinous congregation Phar′aoh will not make him effective in the war, by throwing up a siege rampart and by building a siege wall, in order to cut off many souls. 18 And he has despised an oath in breaking a covenant, and, look! he had given his hand and has done even all these things. He will not make his escape.”’

19 “‘Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “As I am alive, surely my oath that he has despised and my covenant that he has broken—I will even bring it upon his head. 20 And I will spread over him my net, and he will certainly be caught in my hunting net; and I will bring him to Babylon and put myself on judgment with him there respecting his unfaithfulness with which he acted against me. 21 And as regards all the fugitives of his in all his bands, by the sword they will fall, and the ones left remaining will be spread abroad even to every wind. And YOU people will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have spoken it.”’

22 “‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “I myself will also take and put some of the lofty treetop of the cedar; from the top of its twigs I shall pluck off a tender one and I will myself transplant it upon a high and lofty mountain. 23 On the mountain of the height of Israel I shall transplant it, and it will certainly bear boughs and produce fruit and become a majestic cedar. And under it there will actually reside all the birds of every wing; in the shadow of its foliage they will reside. 24 And all the trees of the field will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have abased the high tree, have put on high the low tree, have dried up the still-moist tree and have made the dry tree blossom. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken and have done it.”’”

Ezekiel

18 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “What does it mean to YOU people that YOU are expressing this proverbial saying on the soil of Israel, saying, ‘Fathers are the ones that eat unripe grapes, but it is the teeth of the sons that get set on edge’?

3 “‘As I am alive,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘it will no more continue to be YOURS to express this proverbial saying in Israel. 4 Look! All the souls—to me they belong. As the soul of the father so likewise the soul of the son—to me they belong. The soul that is sinning—it itself will die.

5 “‘And as regards a man, in case he happens to be righteous and he has executed justice and righteousness; 6 on the mountains he did not eat and his eyes he did not raise to the dungy idols of the house of Israel, and his companion’s wife he did not defile and to a woman in her impurity he would not go near; 7 and no man would he maltreat; the pledge that he took for indebtedness, he would return; nothing would he wrest away in robbery; to the hungry one he would give his own bread and the naked one he would cover with a garment; 8 nothing would he give on interest and no usury would he take; from injustice he would draw back his hand; true justice he would execute between man and man; 9 in my statutes he kept walking and my judicial decisions he kept in order to execute truth, he is righteous. He will positively keep living,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

10 “‘And if one has become father to a son who is a robber, a shedder of blood, who has done the like of one of these things 11 (but he himself has done none of these very things); in case he has eaten also upon the mountains, and his companion’s wife he has defiled; 12 the afflicted and poor one he has maltreated; things he has wrested away in robbery, a pledged thing he would not return; and to the dungy idols he lifted up his eyes, a detestable thing is what he has done. 13 On usury he has given, and interest he has taken, and he positively will not keep living. All these detestable things he has done. He will positively be put to death. On him his own blood will come to be.

14 “‘And, look! one has become father to a son, who keeps seeing all the sins of his father that he has done, and he sees and does not do things like them. 15 On the mountains he has not eaten, and his eyes he has not lifted up to the dungy idols of the house of Israel; his companion’s wife he has not defiled; 16 and no man has he maltreated, no pledge has he seized, and nothing has he taken in robbery; to the hungry one he has given his own bread, and the naked one he has covered with a garment; 17 from the afflicted one he has drawn back his hand; no usury and interest has he taken; my judicial decisions he has carried out; in my statutes he has walked; he himself will not die because of the error of his father. He will positively keep living. 18 As for his father, because he committed outright defrauding, wrested something away in robbery of a brother, and whatever is not good he has done in the midst of his peoples, look! then he must die for his error.

19 “‘And YOU people will certainly say: “Why is it that the son does not have to bear anything because of the error of the father?” Now as regards the son, justice and righteousness he has executed, all the statutes of mine he has kept and he keeps doing them. He will positively keep living. 20 The soul that is sinning—it itself will die. A son himself will bear nothing because of the error of the father, and a father himself will bear nothing because of the error of the son. Upon his own self the very righteousness of the righteous one will come to be, and upon his own self the very wickedness of a wicked one will come to be.

21 “‘Now as regards someone wicked, in case he should turn back from all his sins that he has committed and he should actually keep all my statutes and execute justice and righteousness, he will positively keep living. He will not die. 22 All his transgressions that he has committed—they will not be remembered against him. For his righteousness that he has done he will keep living.’

23 “‘Do I take any delight at all in the death of someone wicked,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘and not in that he should turn back from his ways and actually keep living?’

24 “‘Now when someone righteous turns back from his righteousness and actually does injustice; according to all the detestable things that the wicked one has done he keeps doing and he is living, none of all his righteous acts that he has done will be remembered. For his unfaithfulness that he has committed and for his sin with which he has sinned, for them he will die.

25 “‘And YOU people will certainly say: “The way of Jehovah is not adjusted right.” Hear, please, O house of Israel. Is not my own way adjusted right? Are not the ways of YOU people not adjusted right?

26 “‘When someone righteous turns back from his righteousness and he actually does injustice and dies on account of them, for his injustice that he has done he will die.

27 “‘And when someone wicked turns back from his wickedness that he has committed and proceeds to execute justice and righteousness, he is the one that will preserve his own soul alive. 28 When he sees and he turns back from all his transgressions that he has done, he will positively keep living. He will not die.

29 “‘And the house of Israel will certainly say: “The way of Jehovah is not adjusted right.” As for my ways, are they not adjusted right, O house of Israel? Are not the ways of YOU people the ones that are not adjusted right?’

30 “‘Therefore each one according to his ways is how I shall judge YOU, O house of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘Turn back, yes, cause a turning back from all YOUR transgressions, and let nothing prove to be for YOU people a stumbling block causing error. 31 Throw off from yourselves all YOUR transgressions in which YOU have transgressed and make for yourselves a new heart and a new spirit, for why should YOU die, O house of Israel?’

32 “‘For I do not take any delight in the death of someone dying,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘So cause a turning back and keep living, O YOU people.’”

Ezekiel

21 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, set your face toward Jerusalem and drip words toward the holy places, and prophesy against the soil of Israel. 3 And you must say to the soil of Israel, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, and I will bring forth my sword out of its sheath and cut off from you righteous one and wicked one. 4 In order that I may actually cut off from you righteous one and wicked one, therefore my sword will go forth from its sheath against all flesh from south to north. 5 And all those of flesh will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have brought forth my sword from its sheath. No more will it go back.”’

6 “And as for you, O son of man, sigh with shaking hips. Even with bitterness you should sigh before their eyes. 7 And it must occur that, in case they say to you, ‘On account of what are you sighing?’ you must say, ‘At a report.’ For it will certainly come, and every heart must melt and all hands must drop down and every spirit must become dejected and all knees themselves will drip with water. ‘Look! It will certainly come and be brought to occur,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

8 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 9 “Son of man, prophesy, and you must say, ‘This is what Jehovah has said: “Say, ‘A sword, a sword! It has been sharpened, and it is also polished. 10 For the purpose of organizing a slaughter it has been sharpened; for the purpose of its getting a glitter it has been polished.’”’”

“Or shall we exult?”

“‘Is it rejecting the scepter of my own son, as it does every tree?

11 “‘And one gives it to be polished, in order to wield it with the hand. It—a sword has been sharpened, and it—it has been polished, in order to give it into the hand of a killer.

12 “‘Cry out and howl, O son of man, for it itself has come to be against my people; it is against all the chieftains of Israel. The very ones hurled to the sword have come to be with my people. Therefore make a slap on the thigh. 13 For an examination has been made, and what of it if it is rejecting also the scepter? This will not continue existing,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

14 “And you, O son of man—prophesy, and strike palm against palm, and ‘A sword!’ should be repeated for three times. The sword of the slain ones it is. It is the sword of someone slain who is great, which is making an encirclement of them. 15 In order for the heart to melt and in order to multiply those who are overthrown at all their gates, I will make a slaughter by the sword. Alas, it is made for a glittering, polished for a slaughter! 16 Show yourself sharp; go to the right! Set your position; go to the left! To wherever your face is directed! 17 And I myself also shall strike my one palm against my other palm, and I will bring my rage to its rest. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken.”

18 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 19 “And as for you, O son of man, set for yourself two ways for the sword of the king of Babylon to enter. From the one land both of them should go forth, and an index hand should be cut out; at the head of the way to the city it should be cut out. 20 A way you should set for the sword to enter against Rab′bah of the sons of Am′mon, and one against Judah, against Jerusalem fortified. 21 For the king of Babylon stood still at the crossways, at the head of the two ways, in order to resort to divination. He has shaken the arrows. He has asked by means of the teraphim; he has looked into the liver. 22 In his right hand the divination proved to be for Jerusalem, to set battering rams, to open one’s mouth for a slaying, to raise the sound in an alarm signal, to set battering rams against gates, to throw up a siege rampart, to build a siege wall. 23 And it has become to them like an untrue divination in their eyes—those who are sworn with oaths to them; and he is calling error to remembrance, in order for them to be caught.

24 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘By reason of YOUR causing YOUR error to be remembered by YOUR transgressions being uncovered, in order that YOUR sins may be seen according to all YOUR dealings, by reason of YOUR being called to remembrance YOU people will be seized even by the hand.’

25 “And as for you, O deadly wounded, wicked chieftain of Israel, whose day has come in the time of the error of the end, 26 this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Remove the turban, and lift off the crown. This will not be the same. Put on high even what is low, and bring low even the high one. 27 A ruin, a ruin, a ruin I shall make it. As for this also, it will certainly become no one’s until he comes who has the legal right, and I must give it to him.’

28 “And you, O son of man, prophesy, and you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said concerning the sons of Am′mon and concerning the reproach from them.’ And you must say, ‘A sword, a sword drawn for a slaughter, polished to cause it to devour, in order to glitter, 29 because of their beholding for you an unreality, because of their divining for you a lie, in order to put you on the necks of the slain ones, the wicked men whose day has come in the time of the error of the end. 30 Return it to its sheath. In the place that you were created, in the land of your origin, I shall judge you. 31 And I will pour out upon you my denunciation. With the fire of my fury I shall blow upon you, and I will give you into the hand of men who are unreasoning, the craftsmen of ruination. 32 For the fire you will become fuel. Your own blood will prove to be in the midst of the land. You will not be remembered, for I myself, Jehovah, have spoken.’”

Ezekiel

22 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “And as for you, O son of man, will you judge, will you judge the bloodguilty city and certainly cause her to know all her detestable things? 3 And you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “O city that is shedding blood in her midst till her time comes, and that has made dungy idols within herself in order to become unclean, 4 by your blood that you have shed you have become guilty, and by your dungy idols that you have made you have become unclean. And you bring your days near, and you will come to your years. That is why I must make you an object of reproach to the nations and of jeering to all the lands. 5 The lands nearby and those far away from you will jeer you, O you unclean in name, abounding in confusion. 6 Look! The chieftains of Israel have proved to be in you, each one given over to his arm for the purpose of shedding blood. 7 Father and mother they have treated with contempt in you. Toward the alien resident they have acted with defrauding in the midst of you. Fatherless boy and widow they have maltreated in you.”’”

8 “‘My holy places you have despised, and my sabbaths you have profaned. 9 Outright slanderers have proved to be in you, for the purpose of shedding blood; and on the mountains they have eaten in you. Loose conduct they have carried on in the midst of you. 10 The nakedness of a father they have uncovered in you; a woman unclean in her menstruation they have humiliated in you. 11 And with the wife of his companion a man has done a detestable thing, and his own daughter-in-law a man has defiled with loose conduct; and his sister, the daughter of his own father, a man has humiliated in you. 12 A bribe they have taken in you for the purpose of shedding blood. Interest and usury you have taken, and you violently keep making gain of your companions with defrauding, and me you have forgotten,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

13 “‘And, look! I have struck my hand at your unjust gain that you have made, and over your acts of bloodshed that have proved to be in the midst of you. 14 Will your heart keep enduring or your hands furnish strength in the days when I am taking action toward you? I myself, Jehovah, have spoken and I will take action. 15 And I will scatter you among the nations and disperse you among the lands, and I will destroy your uncleanness out of you. 16 And you will certainly be profaned within yourself before the eyes of the nations, and you will have to know that I am Jehovah.’”

17 And the word of Jehovah continued to come to me, saying: 18 “Son of man, to me those of the house of Israel have become as scummy dross. All of them are copper and tin and iron and lead in the midst of a furnace. Much scummy dross, that of silver, they have become.

19 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that all of YOU have become as much scummy dross, therefore here I am collecting YOU together into the midst of Jerusalem. 20 As in collecting silver and copper and iron and lead and tin into the midst of a furnace, in order to blow upon it with fire to cause a liquefying, so I shall collect them together in my anger and in my rage, and I will blow and cause YOU people to liquefy. 21 And I will bring YOU together and blow upon YOU with the fire of my fury, and YOU must be liquefied in the midst of her. 22 As in the liquefying of silver in the midst of a furnace, so YOU people will be liquefied in the midst of her; and YOU will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have poured out my rage upon YOU.’”

23 And the word of Jehovah continued to come to me, saying: 24 “Son of man, say to her, ‘You are a land not being cleansed, one not rained down upon in the day of denunciation. 25 There is a conspiracy of her prophets in the midst of her, like the roaring lion, tearing prey. A soul they actually devour. Treasure and precious things they keep taking. Her widows they have multiplied in the midst of her. 26 Her priests themselves have done violence to my law, and they keep profaning my holy places. Between the holy thing and the common they have made no distinction, and between the unclean thing and the clean they have made nothing known, and from my sabbaths they have hidden their eyes, and I am profaned in the midst of them. 27 Her princes in the midst of her are like wolves tearing prey in shedding blood, in destroying souls for the purpose of making unjust gain. 28 And her prophets have plastered for them with whitewash, visioning an unreality and divining for them a lie, saying: “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said,” when Jehovah himself has not spoken. 29 The people of the land themselves have carried on a scheme of defrauding and have done a tearing away in robbery, and the afflicted one and the poor one they have maltreated, and the alien resident they have defrauded without justice.’

30 “‘And I kept looking for a man from among them who would be repairing the stone wall and standing in the gap before me in behalf of the land, in order for me not to bring it to ruin; and I found no one. 31 So I shall pour out my denunciation upon them. With the fire of my fury I will exterminate them. Their way I will bring upon their own head,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

23 And the word of Jehovah proceeded to come to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, two women, the daughters of one mother, there happened to be. 3 And they began to prostitute themselves in Egypt. In their youth they committed prostitution. There their breasts were squeezed, and there they pressed the bosoms of their virginity. 4 And their names were O·ho′lah the older one and O·hol′i·bah her sister, and they came to be mine and began to give birth to sons and daughters. And as for their names, O·ho′lah is Sa·mar′i·a, and O·hol′i·bah is Jerusalem.

5 “And O·ho′lah began to prostitute herself, while subject to me, and kept lusting after those passionately loving her, after the As·syr′i·ans, who were near, 6 governors clothed with blue material, and deputy rulers—desirable young men all of them, cavalrymen riding horses. 7 And she continued giving forth her prostitutions upon them, the choicest sons of As·syr′i·a all of them; and with all those after whom she lusted—with their dungy idols—she defiled herself. 8 And her prostitutions carried from Egypt she did not leave, for with her they had lain down in her youth, and they were the ones that pressed the bosoms of her virginity and they kept pouring out their immoral intercourse upon her. 9 Therefore I gave her into the hand of those passionately loving her, into the hand of the sons of As·syr′i·a, toward whom she had lusted. 10 They were the ones that uncovered her nakedness. Her sons and her daughters they took, and her they killed even with sword. And she came to be infamy to women, and acts of judgment were what they executed upon her.

11 “When her sister O·hol′i·bah got to see it, then she exercised her sensual desire more ruinously than she, and her prostitution more than the fornication of her sister. 12 For the sons of As·syr′i·a she lusted, governors and deputy rulers who were near, clothed with perfect taste, cavalrymen riding horses—desirable young men all of them. 13 And I got to see that, because she had defiled herself, both of them had one way. 14 And she kept adding to her acts of prostitution when she got to see the men in carvings upon the wall, images of Chal·de′ans carved in vermilion, 15 girded with belts on their hips, with pendant turbans on their heads, having the appearance of warriors, all of them, the likeness of the sons of Babylon, Chal·de′ans as respects the land of their birth. 16 And she began to lust after them at the sight of her eyes and proceeded to send messengers to them in Chal·de′a. 17 And the sons of Babylon kept coming in to her, to the bed of expressions of love, and defiling her with their immoral intercourse; and she continued getting defiled by them, and her soul began to turn away disgusted from them.

18 “And she went on uncovering her acts of prostitution and uncovering her nakedness, so that my soul turned away disgusted from company with her, just as my soul had turned away disgusted from company with her sister. 19 And she kept multiplying her acts of prostitution to the point of calling to mind the days of her youth, when she prostituted herself in the land of Egypt. 20 And she kept lusting in the style of concubines belonging to those whose fleshly member is as the fleshly member of male asses and whose genital organ is as the genital organ of male horses. 21 And you continued calling attention to the loose conduct of your youth by the pressing of your bosoms from Egypt onward, for the sake of the breasts of your youth.

22 “Therefore, O O·hol′i·bah, this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am rousing up your passionate lovers against you, those from whom your soul has turned away in disgust, and I will bring them in against you on all sides, 23 the sons of Babylon and all the Chal·de′ans, Pe′kod and Sho′a and Ko′a, all the sons of As·syr′i·a with them, desirable young men, governors and deputy rulers all of them, warriors and summoned ones, riding on horses, all of them. 24 And they must come in against you with rattling of war chariots and wheels, and with a congregation of peoples, with large shield and buckler and helmet. They will set themselves against you all around, and I will give judgment over to them, and they must judge you with their judgments. 25 And I will express my ardor against you, and they must take action against you in rage. Your nose and your ears they will remove, and the remainder of you will fall even by the sword. Your sons and your daughters they themselves will take, and the remainder of you will be devoured by the fire. 26 And they will certainly strip off you your garments and take away your beautiful articles. 27 And I shall actually cause your loose conduct to cease from you, and your prostitution carried from the land of Egypt; and you will not raise your eyes to them, and Egypt you will remember no more.’

28 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am giving you into the hand of those whom you have hated, into the hand of those from whom your soul has turned away disgusted. 29 And they must take action against you in hatred and take away all your product of toil and leave you naked and nude; and the nudeness of your acts of fornication and your loose conduct and your acts of prostitution must be uncovered. 30 There will be a doing of these things to you because of your going like a prostitute after the nations, on account of the fact that you defiled yourself with their dungy idols. 31 In the way of your sister you have walked; and I shall have to give her cup into your hand.’

32 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘The cup of your sister you will drink, the deep and wide one. You will become an object of laughter and derision, the cup containing much. 33 With drunkenness and grief you will be filled, with the cup of astonishment and of desolation, the cup of your sister Sa·mar′i·a. 34 And you will have to drink it and drain it out, and its earthenware fragments you will gnaw, and your breasts you will tear out. “For I myself have spoken,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.’

35 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that you have forgotten me and you proceeded to cast me behind your back, then you yourself also bear your loose conduct and your acts of prostitution.’”

36 And Jehovah went on to say to me: “Son of man, will you judge O·ho′lah and O·hol′i·bah and tell them their detestable things? 37 For they have committed adultery and there is blood on their hands, and with their dungy idols they have committed adultery. And, besides that, their sons whom they had borne to me they made pass through the fire to them as food. 38 What is more, this is what they have done to me: They have defiled my sanctuary in that day, and my sabbaths they have profaned. 39 And when they had slaughtered their sons to their dungy idols they even proceeded to come into my sanctuary on that day to profane it, and, look! that is what they have done in the midst of my house. 40 And in addition to that, when they began to send to the men coming from far away, to whom there was sent a messenger, then, look! they came, for whom you had washed yourself, painted your eyes and decked yourself with ornaments. 41 And you sat down upon a glorious couch, with a table set in order before it, and my incense and my oil you put upon it. 42 And the sound of a crowd at ease was in her, and to the men out of the mass of mankind there were drunkards being brought in from the wilderness, and they proceeded to put bracelets on the hands of the women and beautiful crowns upon their heads.

43 “Then I said respecting her who was worn out with adultery, ‘Now she will keep on committing her prostitution, even she herself.’ 44 And they kept on coming in to her, just as one comes in to a woman that is a prostitute; in that manner they came in to O·ho′lah and to O·hol′i·bah as women of loose conduct. 45 But as regards righteous men, they are the ones that will judge her with the judgment for adulteresses and with the judgment for female shedders of blood; for adulteresses are what they are, and there is blood on their hands.

46 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘There will be the bringing up of a congregation against them and a making of them a frightful object and something to plunder. 47 And the congregation must pelt them with stones, and there will be a cutting of them down with their swords. Their sons and their daughters they will kill, and with fire their houses they will burn. 48 And I shall certainly cause loose conduct to cease out of the land, and all the women will have to let themselves be corrected, so that they will not do according to YOUR loose conduct. 49 And they must bring YOUR loose conduct upon YOU, and the sins of YOUR dungy idols YOU will bear; and YOU people will have to know that I am the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.’”

Ezekiel

26 And it came about in the eleventh year, on the first day of the month, that the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, for the reason that Tyre has said against Jerusalem, ‘Aha! She has been broken, the doors of the peoples! The trend will certainly be to me. I shall be filled—she has been devastated,’ 3 therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am against you, O Tyre, and I will bring up against you many nations, just as the sea brings up its waves. 4 And they will certainly bring the walls of Tyre to ruin and tear down her towers, and I will scrape her dust away from her and make her a shining, bare surface of a crag. 5 A drying yard for dragnets is what she will become in the midst of the sea.’

“‘For I myself have spoken,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘and she must become an object of plunder for the nations. 6 And her dependent towns that are in the field—by the sword they will be killed, and people will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

7 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am bringing against Tyre Neb·u·chad·rez′zar the king of Babylon from the north, a king of kings, with horses and war chariots and cavalrymen and a congregation, even a multitudinous people. 8 Your dependent towns in the field he will kill even with the sword, and he must make against you a siege wall and throw up against you a siege rampart and raise up against you a large shield; 9 and the strike of his attack engine he will direct against your walls, and your towers he will pull down, with his swords. 10 Owing to the heaving mass of his horses their dust will cover you. Owing to the sound of cavalryman and wheel and war chariot your walls will rock, when he comes in through your gates, as in the cases of entering into a city opened by breaches. 11 With the hoofs of his horses he will trample down all your streets. Your people he will kill even with the sword, and to the earth your own pillars of strength will go down. 12 And they will certainly spoil your resources and plunder your sales goods, and tear down your walls, and your desirable houses they will pull down. And your stones and your woodwork and your dust they will place in the very midst of the water.’

13 “‘And I will cause the turmoil of your singing to cease, and the very sound of your harps will be heard no more. 14 And I will make you a shining, bare surface of a crag. A drying yard for dragnets is what you will become. Never will you be rebuilt; for I myself, Jehovah, have spoken,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

15 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said to Tyre, ‘At the sound of your downfall, when the fatally wounded one groans, when there is a killing with slaughter in the midst of you, will not the islands rock? 16 And down from their thrones all the chieftains of the sea will certainly come and remove their sleeveless coats, and they will strip off their own embroidered garments. They will put on trembling spells. Upon the earth they will sit down, and they will certainly tremble every moment and stare in amazement at you. 17 And they must raise up over you a dirge and say to you:

“‘“How you have perished, that used to be inhabited from the seas, O praised city, who became a strong one in the sea, she and those inhabiting her, those who gave their terror to all the inhabitants of the earth! 18 Now the islands will tremble in the day of your downfall. And the islands that are in the sea must be disturbed owing to your going out.”’

19 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘When I make you a devastated city, like the cities that are actually not inhabited, when I bring up over you the watery deep, and the vast waters will have covered you, 20 I will also bring you down with those going down into the pit to the people of long ago, and I will cause you to dwell in the lowest land, like places devastated for a long time, with those going down into the pit, in order that you may not be inhabited; and I will put decoration in the land of those alive.

21 “‘Sudden terrors are what I shall make you, and you will not be; and you will be sought for, but you will no more be found to time indefinite,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

27 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “And as for you, O son of man, raise up concerning Tyre a dirge, 3 and you must say to Tyre,

“‘O you who are dwelling at the entrances of the sea, the tradeswoman of the peoples for many islands, this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “O Tyre, you yourself have said, ‘I am perfect in prettiness.’ 4 In the heart of the seas are your territories. Your own builders have perfected your prettiness. 5 Out of juniper timbers from Se′nir they built for you all the planks. A cedar from Leb′a·non they took to make a mast upon you. 6 Out of massive trees from Ba′shan they made your oars. Your prow they made with ivory in cypress wood, from the islands of Kit′tim. 7 Linen in various colors from Egypt your cloth expanse happened to be, in order for it to serve as your sail. Blue thread and wool dyed reddish purple from the islands of E·li′shah are what your deck covering proved to be.

8 “‘“The inhabitants of Si′don and of Ar′vad themselves became rowers for you. Your skilled ones, O Tyre, happened to be in you; they were your sailors. 9 Even old men of Ge′bal and her skilled ones happened to be in you as caulkers for your seams. All the ships of the sea and their mariners themselves proved to be in you, in order to exchange articles of merchandise. 10 Persians and Lu′dim and men of Put—they happened to be in your military force, your men of war. Shield and helmet they hung up in you. They were the ones that caused your splendor. 11 The sons of Ar′vad, even your military force, were upon your walls all around, and valorous men were the ones that happened to be in your own towers. Their circular shields they hung up on your walls all around. They themselves perfected your prettiness.

12 “‘“Tar′shish was your merchant because of the abundance of all sorts of valuable things. For its silver, iron, tin and lead, your stores were given. 13 Ja′van, Tu′bal and Me′shech themselves were your traders. For the souls of mankind and articles of copper your articles of exchange were given. 14 From the house of To·gar′mah there were horses and steeds and mules, for which your stores were given. 15 The sons of De′dan were your traders; many islands were merchants in your employ; horns of ivory and ebony they have paid back as gift to you. 16 E′dom was your merchant because of the abundance of your works. For turquoise, wool dyed reddish purple and material of various colors and fine fabric and corals and rubies, your stores were given in exchange.

17 “‘“Judah and the land of Israel themselves were your traders. For the wheat of Min′nith and special foodstuff and honey and oil and balsam, your articles of exchange were given.

18 “‘“Damascus was your merchant in the abundance of your works, because of the abundance of all your valuable things, with the wine of Hel′bon and the wool of reddish gray. 19 Ve′dan and Ja′van from U′zal—for your stores they gave. Iron in wrought works, cassia and cane—for your articles of exchange they proved to be. 20 De′dan was your trader in garments of woven material for riding. 21 The Arabs and all the chieftains of Ke′dar themselves were merchants in your employ. In male lambs and rams and he-goats—in them they were your merchants. 22 The traders of She′ba and Ra′a·mah themselves were your traders; for the finest of all sorts of perfumes and for all sorts of precious stones and gold, your stores were given. 23 Ha′ran and Can′neh and E′den, the traders of She′ba, As′shur and Chil′mad were your traders. 24 They were your traders in gorgeous garments, in wraps of blue material and material of various colors and in carpets of two-colored stuff, in ropes twined and solidly made, in your trading center.

25 “‘“The ships of Tar′shish were your caravans for your articles of exchange, so that you get filled and become very glorious in the heart of the open sea.

26 “‘“Into vast waters those rowing you have brought you. The east wind itself has broken you in the heart of the open sea. 27 Your valuable things and your stores, your articles of exchange, your mariners and your sailors, the caulkers of your seams and those exchanging your articles of merchandise and all your men of war, who are in you and in all your congregation, who are in the midst of you,—they will fall in the heart of the open sea in the day of your downfall.

28 “‘“At the sound of the outcry of your sailors the open country will rock. 29 And all those handling an oar, mariners, all the sailors of the sea, will certainly go down from their ships; upon the land they will stand. 30 And over you they will certainly let themselves be heard with their voice and will cry out bitterly. And they will bring up dust upon their heads. In the ashes they will wallow. 31 And they will have to make themselves bald with a baldness for you, and gird on sackcloth and weep over you in bitterness of soul, with bitter wailing. 32 And for you in their lamentation they will certainly lift up a dirge and chant over you,

“‘“‘Who is like Tyre, like her that has been brought to silence in the midst of the sea? 33 When your stores went forth from the open sea, you satisfied many peoples. With the abundance of your valuable things and your articles of exchange you made earth’s kings rich. 34 Now you have been broken by the open sea, in the depths of the waters. As for your articles of exchange and all your congregation, in the midst of you they have fallen. 35 All the inhabitants of the islands—in amazement they will certainly stare at you, and their kings themselves will have to shudder in horror. Faces must become perturbed. 36 As for merchants among the peoples, they will certainly whistle over you. Sudden terrors are what you must become, and you will be no more to time indefinite.’”’”

Ezekiel

31 And it occurred further that in the eleventh year, in the third month, on the first day of the month, the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, say to Phar′aoh the king of Egypt and to his crowd,

“‘Whom have you come to resemble in your greatness? 3 Look! An As·syr′i·an, a cedar in Leb′a·non, pretty in bough, with a woody thicket offering shadow, and high in stature, so that among the clouds its treetop proved to be. 4 Waters were what made it get big; the watery deep caused it to grow high. With its streams it was going all around its planting place; and its channels it sent forth to all the trees of the field. 5 That is why it grew higher in its stature than all the other trees of the field.

“‘And its boughs kept multiplying, and its branches continued getting longer because of much water in its watercourses. 6 On its boughs all the flying creatures of the heavens made their nests, and under its branches all the wild beasts of the field gave birth, and in its shade all the populous nations would dwell. 7 And it came to be pretty in its greatness, in the length of its foliage, for its root system proved to be over many waters. 8 Other cedars were no match for it in the garden of God. As for juniper trees, they bore no resemblance as respects its boughs. And plane trees themselves did not prove to be like it in branches. No other tree in the garden of God resembled it in its prettiness. 9 Pretty is the way that I made it in the abundance of its foliage, and all the other trees of E′den that were in the garden of the true God kept envying it.’

10 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that you became high in stature, so that it put its treetop even among the clouds and its heart became exalted because of its height, 11 I shall also give it into the hand of the despot of the nations. Without fail he will act against it. According to its wickedness I will drive it out. 12 And strangers, the tyrants of the nations, will cut it down, and people will abandon it upon the mountains; and in all the valleys its foliage will certainly fall, and its branches will be broken among all the streambeds of the earth. And out from its shade all the peoples of the earth will come down and abandon it. 13 Upon its fallen trunk all the flying creatures of the heavens will reside, and upon its branches there will certainly come to be all the wild beasts of the field; 14 to the end that none of the watered trees may become high in their stature, or put their treetops even among the clouds, and that none drinking water may stand up against them in their height, for they will certainly all of them be given to death, to the land down below, in the midst of the sons of mankind, to those going down into the pit.’

15 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘On the day of its going down to She′ol I shall certainly cause a mourning. On its account I will cover the watery deep, that I may hold back its streams and that the many waters may be restrained; and on its account I shall darken Leb′a·non, and on its account the trees of the field will all swoon away. 16 At the sound of its downfall I shall certainly cause nations to rock when I bring it down to She′ol with those going down into the pit, and in the land down below all the trees of E′den, the choicest and the best of Leb′a·non, all those drinking water, will be comforted. 17 With him they themselves also have gone down to She′ol, to those slain by the sword, and those who as his seed have dwelt in his shadow in the midst of nations.’

18 “‘Whom have you come to resemble thus in glory and greatness among the trees of E′den? But you will certainly be brought down with the trees of E′den to the land down below. In the midst of the uncircumcised ones you will lie down with those slain by the sword. This is Phar′aoh and all his crowd,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

32 And it occurred further that in the twelfth year, in the twelfth month, on the first day of the month, the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, lift up a dirge concerning Phar′aoh the king of Egypt, and you must say to him, ‘As a maned young lion of nations you have been silenced.

“‘And you have been like the marine monster in the seas, and you kept gushing in your rivers and kept muddying the waters with your feet and fouling their rivers.’

3 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘I will also spread over you my net by means of a congregation of many peoples, and they will certainly bring you in my dragnet. 4 And I must abandon you on the land. Upon the surface of the field I shall hurl you. And on you I will cause all the flying creatures of the heavens to reside, and off you I will satisfy the wild beasts of the whole earth. 5 And I will put your flesh upon the mountains and fill the valleys with the refuse of you. 6 And I will cause the land to drink up your discharged matter, from your blood, upon the mountains; and streambeds themselves will be filled up from you.’

7 “‘And when you get extinguished I will cover the heavens and darken their stars. As for the sun, with clouds I shall cover it, and the moon itself will not let its light shine. 8 All the luminaries of light in the heavens—I shall darken them on your account, and I will put darkness upon your land,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

9 “‘And I will offend the heart of many peoples when I bring the captives from you among the nations to lands that you have not known. 10 And at you I shall certainly cause many peoples to be awestruck, and their kings themselves will shudder in horror at you when I brandish my sword in their faces, and they will have to tremble every moment, each one for his own soul, on the day of your downfall.’

11 “For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘The very sword of the king of Babylon will come upon you. 12 I shall cause your crowd to fall by the very swords of mighty ones, the tyrants of the nations, all of them; and they will actually despoil the pride of Egypt, and all her crowd must be annihilated. 13 And I will destroy all her domestic animals from beside many waters, and the foot of earthling man will no more muddy them, nor will even the hoofs of a domestic animal muddy them.’

14 “‘At that time I shall make their waters clear up, and their rivers I shall make go just like oil,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

15 “‘When I make the land of Egypt a desolate waste and the land is desolated of its fullness, when I strike down all the inhabitants in it, they will also have to know that I am Jehovah.

16 “‘This is a dirge, and people will certainly chant it. Even the daughters of the nations will chant it; over Egypt and over all its crowd they will chant it,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

17 And it occurred further that in the twelfth year, on the fifteenth day of the month, the word of Jehovah occurred to me, saying: 18 “Son of man, lament over the crowd of Egypt and bring it down, her and the daughters of majestic nations, to the land down below, with those going down into the pit.

19 “‘Compared with whom are you more pleasant? Do go down, and you must be laid with the uncircumcised ones!’

20 “‘In the midst of those slain by the sword they will fall. To a sword she has been given. Drag her away and all her crowds, YOU men.

21 “‘The foremost men of the mighty ones will speak out of the midst of She′ol even to him, with his helpers. They will certainly go down; they must lie down as the uncircumcised, slain by the sword. 22 There is where As·syr′i·a and all her congregation are. His burial places are round about him. All of them are slain, those falling by the sword. 23 For her burial places have been put in the innermost parts of a pit, and her congregation proves to be round about her grave, all of them slain, falling by the sword, because they had caused terror in the land of those alive.

24 “‘There are E′lam and all her crowd round about her grave, all of them slain ones, those falling by the sword, who have gone down uncircumcised to the land down below, those who have caused their terror in the land of those alive; and they will bear their humiliation with those going down into the pit. 25 In the midst of slain ones they have set a bed for her among all her crowd. Her burial places are round about it. All of them are uncircumcised, slain by the sword, because their terror was caused in the land of those alive; and they will bear their humiliation with those going down into the pit. In the midst of slain ones he has been put.

26 “‘There is where Me′shech and Tu′bal and all her crowd are. Her burial places are round about him. All of them are uncircumcised, pierced through by the sword, because they have caused their terror in the land of those alive. 27 And will they not lie down with mighty ones, falling from among the uncircumcised, who have gone down to She′ol with their weapons of war? And they will put their swords under their heads, and their errors will come to be upon their bones, because mighty ones were a terror in the land of those alive. 28 And as for you, in the midst of uncircumcised ones you will be broken, and you will lie down with those slain by the sword.

29 “‘There is where E′dom, her kings and all her chieftains are, who, in their mightiness, were put with those slain by the sword; they themselves will lie down even with the uncircumcised ones and with those going down into the pit.

30 “‘There is where the dukes of the north are, all of them, and all the Si·do′ni·ans, who have gone down with the slain ones, in their terribleness because of their mightiness, ashamed. And they will lie down uncircumcised with those slain by the sword and will bear their humiliation with those going down into the pit.

31 “‘These are the ones that Phar′aoh will see, and he will certainly be comforted over all his crowd. Phar′aoh and all his military force will be people slain by the sword,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

32 “‘For he has caused his terror in the land of those alive, and he must be laid in the midst of the uncircumcised ones, with those slain by the sword, even Phar′aoh and all his crowd,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

34 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, prophesy against the shepherds of Israel. Prophesy, and you must say to them, to the shepherds, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Woe to the shepherds of Israel, who have become feeders of themselves! Is it not the flock that the shepherds ought to feed? 3 The fat is what YOU eat, and with the wool YOU clothe YOUR own selves. The plump animal is what YOU slaughter. The flock itself YOU do not feed. 4 The sickened ones YOU have not strengthened, and the ailing one YOU have not healed, and the broken one YOU have not bandaged, and the dispersed one YOU have not brought back, and the lost one YOU have not sought to find, but with harshness YOU have had them in subjection, even with tyranny. 5 And they were gradually scattered because of there being no shepherd, so that they became food for every wild beast of the field, and they continued to be scattered. 6 My sheep kept straying on all the mountains and on every high hill; and on all the surface of the earth my sheep were scattered, with no one making a search and with no one seeking to find.

7 “‘“Therefore, YOU shepherds, hear the word of Jehovah, 8 ‘“As I am alive,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, “surely for the reason that my sheep became something for plunder and my sheep continued to be food for every wild beast of the field, because there was no shepherd, and my shepherds did not search for my sheep, but the shepherds kept feeding themselves, and my own sheep they did not feed,”’ 9 therefore, YOU shepherds, hear the word of Jehovah. 10 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am against the shepherds, and I shall certainly ask back my sheep from their hand and make them cease from feeding my sheep, and the shepherds will no longer feed themselves; and I will deliver my sheep out of their mouth, and they will not become food for them.’”

11 “‘For this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am, I myself, and I will search for my sheep and care for them. 12 According to the care of one feeding his drove in the day of his coming to be in the midst of his sheep that have been spread abroad, that is the way that I shall care for my sheep; and I will deliver them out of all the places to which they have been scattered in the day of clouds and thick gloom. 13 And I will bring them out from the peoples and collect them together from the lands and bring them in onto their soil and feed them on the mountains of Israel, by the streambeds and by all the dwelling places of the land. 14 In a good pasturage I shall feed them, and on Israel’s high mountains their abiding place will come to be. There they will lie down in a good abiding place, and on a fat pasturage they will feed upon the mountains of Israel.”

15 “‘“I myself shall feed my sheep, and I myself shall make them lie down,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 16 “The lost one I shall search for, and the dispersed one I shall bring back, and the broken one I shall bandage and the ailing one I shall strengthen, but the fat one and the strong one I shall annihilate. I shall feed that one with judgment.”

17 “‘And as for YOU my sheep, this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am judging between a sheep and a sheep, between the rams and the he-goats. 18 Is it such a little thing for YOU men that on the very best pasturage YOU feed but the rest of YOUR pasturages YOU should trample down with YOUR feet, and that the clear waters YOU drink but the ones left over YOU should foul by stamping with YOUR very feet? 19 And as for my sheep, on the pasture ground trampled by YOUR feet should they feed and the water befouled by the stamping of YOUR feet should they drink?”

20 “‘Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said to them: “Here I am, I myself, and I shall certainly judge between a plump sheep and a lean sheep, 21 for the reason that with flank and with shoulder YOU kept pushing and with YOUR horns YOU kept shoving all the sickened ones until YOU had scattered them to the outside. 22 And I will save my sheep, and they will no longer become something for plunder; and I will judge between a sheep and a sheep. 23 And I will raise up over them one shepherd, and he must feed them, even my servant David. He himself will feed them, and he himself will become their shepherd. 24 And I myself, Jehovah, will become their God, and my servant David a chieftain in the midst of them. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken.

25 “‘“And I will conclude with them a covenant of peace, and I shall certainly cause the injurious wild beast to cease out of the land, and they will actually dwell in the wilderness in security and sleep in the forests. 26 And I will make them and the surroundings of my hill a blessing, and I will cause the pouring rain to descend in its time. Pouring rains of blessing there will prove to be. 27 And the tree of the field must give its fruitage, and the land itself will give its yield, and they will actually prove to be on their soil in security. And they will have to know that I am Jehovah when I break the bars of their yoke and I have delivered them out of the hand of those who had been using them as slaves. 28 And they will no longer become something to plunder for the nations; and as regards the wild beast of the earth, it will not devour them, and they will actually dwell in security, with no one to make them tremble.

29 “‘“And I will raise up for them a planting for a name, and they will no more become those taken away by famine in the land, and they will no longer bear the humiliation by the nations. 30 ‘And they will have to know that I, Jehovah their God, am with them and that they are my people, the house of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”’

31 “‘And as regards YOU my sheep, the sheep of my pasturing, YOU are earthling men. I am YOUR God,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

36 “And as for you, O son of man, prophesy concerning the mountains of Israel, and you must say, ‘O mountains of Israel, hear the word of Jehovah. 2 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “For the reason that the enemy has said against YOU, ‘Aha! Even the high places of old time—as a possession it has become ours!’”’

3 “Therefore prophesy, and you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “For the reason, even for the reason that there has been a lying desolate and a snapping at YOU from all sides, in order for YOU to become a possession to the remaining ones of the nations and YOU continue being talked about with the tongue and there is a bad report among people, 4 therefore, O mountains of Israel, hear the word of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah! This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said to the mountains and to the hills, to the streambeds and to the valleys and to the devastated places that were laid desolate and to the abandoned cities that have come to be for plunder and for ridicule to the remaining ones of the nations that are round about; 5 therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Certainly in the fire of my zeal I will speak against the remaining ones of the nations and against E′dom, all of it, those who have given my land to themselves as a possession with the rejoicing of all the heart, with scorn in the soul, for the sake of its pasture ground and for the plunder.’”’

6 “Therefore prophesy concerning the soil of Israel, and you must say to the mountains and to the hills, to the streambeds and to the valleys, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Look! I myself in my zeal and in my rage must speak, for the reason that humiliation by nations is what YOU have borne.”’

7 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘I myself have raised my hand in an oath that the nations that YOU have round about—they themselves will bear their own humiliation. 8 And YOU yourselves, O mountains of Israel, will give forth YOUR very own boughs and bear YOUR own fruitage for my people Israel, for they have drawn near to the point of coming in. 9 For here I am in favor of YOU, and I shall certainly turn toward YOU, and YOU will actually be cultivated and sown with seed. 10 And I will multiply upon YOU humankind, the whole house of Israel, all of it, and the cities must become inhabited, and the devastated places themselves will be rebuilt. 11 Yes, I will multiply upon YOU humankind and animalkind, and they will certainly multiply and become fruitful, and I shall actually cause YOU to be inhabited as in YOUR former condition and I will do more good than in YOUR initial state; and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah. 12 And upon YOU I will cause humankind to walk, even my people Israel, and they must take possession of YOU, and YOU must become a hereditary possession to them, and YOU will not bereave them again of any more children.’”

13 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘For the reason that there are those saying to YOU: “A devourer of humankind is what you yourself are, and a land bereaving your nations of children is what you have become,”’ 14 ‘therefore humankind you will no more devour, and your nations you will no more bereave of children,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 15 ‘And I shall cause no further humiliating talk by the nations to be heard concerning you, and reproach by peoples you will bear no more, and your nations you will no more cause to stumble,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

16 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 17 “Son of man, the house of Israel were dwelling upon their soil, and they kept making it unclean with their way and with their dealings. Like the uncleanness of menstruation their way has become before me. 18 And I proceeded to pour out my rage upon them on account of the blood that they had poured out upon the land, which land they had made unclean with their dungy idols. 19 And I proceeded to scatter them among the nations, so that they were dispersed among the lands. According to their way and according to their dealings I judged them. 20 So they came in to the nations where they came in, and people proceeded to profane my holy name in saying with reference to them, ‘These are the people of Jehovah, and from his land they have gone out.’ 21 And I shall have compassion on my holy name, which the house of Israel have profaned among the nations where they have come in.”

22 “Therefore say to the house of Israel, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Not for YOUR sakes am I doing it, O house of Israel, but for my holy name, which YOU have profaned among the nations where YOU have come in.”’ 23 ‘And I shall certainly sanctify my great name, which was being profaned among the nations, which YOU profaned in the midst of them; and the nations will have to know that I am Jehovah,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘when I am sanctified among YOU before their eyes. 24 And I will take YOU out of the nations and collect YOU together out of all the lands and bring YOU in upon YOUR soil. 25 And I will sprinkle upon YOU clean water, and YOU will become clean; from all YOUR impurities and from all YOUR dungy idols I shall cleanse YOU. 26 And I will give YOU a new heart, and a new spirit I shall put inside YOU, and I will take away the heart of stone from YOUR flesh and give YOU a heart of flesh. 27 And my spirit I shall put inside YOU, and I will act so that in my regulations YOU will walk, and my judicial decisions YOU will keep and actually carry out. 28 And YOU will certainly dwell in the land that I gave to YOUR forefathers, and YOU must become my people and I myself shall become YOUR God.’

29 “‘And I will save YOU from all YOUR impurities and call to the grain and make it abound, and I shall put upon YOU no famine. 30 And I shall certainly make the fruitage of the tree abound, and the produce of the field, in order that YOU may no more receive among the nations the reproach of famine. 31 And YOU will be bound to remember YOUR bad ways and YOUR dealings that were not good, and YOU will be bound to feel a loathing at YOUR own person on account of YOUR errors and on account of YOUR detestable things. 32 Not for YOUR sakes am I doing this,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘let it be known to YOU. Be ashamed and feel humiliation because of YOUR ways, O house of Israel.’

33 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘In the day of my cleansing YOU from all YOUR errors I will also cause the cities to be inhabited, and the devastated places must be rebuilt. 34 And the desolated land itself will be cultivated, whereas it had become a desolate waste before the eyes of every passerby. 35 And people will certainly say: “That land yonder which was laid desolate has become like the garden of E′den, and the cities that were a waste and that were laid desolate and that were torn down are fortified; they have become inhabited.” 36 And the nations that will be left remaining round about YOU will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have built the things torn down, I have planted what has been laid desolate. I myself, Jehovah, have spoken and I have done it.’

37 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘This is what I shall yet let myself be searched for by the house of Israel to do for them: I shall multiply them like a flock with men. 38 Like a flock of holy persons, like the flock of Jerusalem in her festal seasons, thus the cities that had been a waste will become full of a flock of men; and people will have to know that I am Jehovah.’”

Ezekiel

37 The hand of Jehovah proved to be upon me, so that he brought me forth in the spirit of Jehovah and set me down in the midst of the valley plain, and it was full of bones. 2 And he had me pass along by them all round about, and, look! there were very many on the surface of the valley plain and, look! they were very dry. 3 And he began to say to me: “Son of man, can these bones come to life?” To that I said: “Sovereign Lord Jehovah, you yourself well know.” 4 And he went on to say to me: “Prophesy over these bones, and you must say to them, ‘O YOU dry bones, hear the word of Jehovah:

5 “‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said to these bones: “Here I am bringing into YOU breath, and YOU must come to life. 6 And I will put upon YOU sinews and cause to come upon YOU flesh, and I will overlay upon YOU skin and put in YOU breath, and YOU must come to life; and YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah.”’”

7 And I prophesied just as I had been commanded. And a sound began to occur as soon as I prophesied, and here there was a rattling, and bones began to approach, bone to its bone. 8 And I saw, and, look! upon them sinews themselves and flesh itself came up and skin began to be overlaid upon them above. But as regards breath, there was none in them.

9 And he went on saying to me: “Prophesy to the wind. Prophesy, O son of man, and you must say to the wind, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “From the four winds come in, O wind, and blow upon these killed people, that they may come to life.”’”

10 And I prophesied just as he had commanded me, and the breath proceeded to come into them, and they began to live and stand upon their feet, a very, very great military force.

11 And he went on to say to me: “Son of man, as regards these bones, they are the whole house of Israel. Here they are saying, ‘Our bones have become dry, and our hope has perished. We have been severed off to ourselves.’ 12 Therefore prophesy, and you must say to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am opening YOUR burial places, and I will bring YOU up out of YOUR burial places, O my people, and bring YOU in upon the soil of Israel. 13 And YOU will have to know that I am Jehovah when I open YOUR burial places and when I bring YOU up out of YOUR burial places, O my people.”’ 14 ‘And I will put my spirit in YOU, and YOU must come to life, and I will settle YOU upon YOUR soil; and YOU will have to know that I myself, Jehovah, have spoken and I have done it,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

15 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 16 “And as for you, O son of man, take for yourself a stick and write upon it, ‘For Judah and for the sons of Israel his partners.’ And take another stick and write upon it, ‘For Joseph, the stick of E′phra·im, and all the house of Israel his partners.’ 17 And cause them to approach each other into one stick for yourself, and they will actually become just one in your hand. 18 And when the sons of your people begin to say to you, ‘Will you not tell us what these things mean to you?’ 19 speak to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am taking the stick of Joseph, which is in the hand of E′phra·im, and the tribes of Israel his partners, and I will put them upon it, that is, the stick of Judah, and I shall actually make them one stick, and they must become one in my hand.”’ 20 And the sticks upon which you write must prove to be in your hand before their eyes.

21 “And speak to them, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am taking the sons of Israel from among the nations to which they have gone, and I will collect them together from round about and bring them onto their soil. 22 And I shall actually make them one nation in the land, on the mountains of Israel, and one king is what all of them will come to have as king, and they will no longer continue to be two nations, nor will they be divided any longer into two kingdoms. 23 And they will no longer defile themselves with their dungy idols and with their disgusting things and with all their transgressions; and I shall certainly save them from all their dwelling places in which they have sinned, and I will cleanse them, and they must become my people, and I myself shall become their God.

24 “‘“And my servant David will be king over them, and one shepherd is what they will all come to have; and in my judicial decisions they will walk, and my statutes they will keep, and they will certainly carry them out. 25 And they will actually dwell upon the land that I gave to my servant, to Jacob, in which YOUR forefathers dwelt, and they will actually dwell upon it, they and their sons and their sons’ sons to time indefinite, and David my servant will be their chieftain to time indefinite.

26 “‘“And I will conclude with them a covenant of peace; an indefinitely lasting covenant is what there will come to be with them. And I will place them and multiply them and place my sanctuary in the midst of them to time indefinite. 27 And my tabernacle will actually prove to be over them, and I shall certainly become their God, and they themselves will become my people. 28 And the nations will have to know that I, Jehovah, am sanctifying Israel when my sanctuary comes to be in the midst of them to time indefinite.”’”

Ezekiel

38 And the word of Jehovah continued to occur to me, saying: 2 “Son of man, set your face against Gog of the land of Ma′gog, the head chieftain of Me′shech and Tu′bal, and prophesy against him. 3 And you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, O Gog, you head chieftain of Me′shech and Tu′bal. 4 And I shall certainly turn you around and put hooks in your jaws and bring you forth with all your military force, horses and horsemen, all of them clothed in perfect taste, a numerous congregation, with large shield and buckler, all of them handling swords; 5 Persia, E·thi·o′pi·a and Put with them, all of them with buckler and helmet; 6 Go′mer and all its bands, the house of To·gar′mah, of the remotest parts of the north, and all its bands, many peoples with you.

7 “‘“Be ready, and let there be preparation on your part, you with all your congregation, those congregated alongside you, and you must become their guard.

8 “‘“After many days you will be given attention. In the final part of the years you will come to the land of people brought back from the sword, collected together out of many peoples, onto the mountains of Israel, that have proved to be a constantly devastated place; even a land that has been brought forth from the peoples, where they have dwelt in security, all of them. 9 And you will be bound to come up. Like a storm you will come in. Like clouds to cover the land you will become, you and all your bands and many peoples with you.”’

10 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘And it must occur in that day that things will come up into your heart, and you will certainly think up an injurious scheme; 11 and you must say: “I shall go up against the land of open rural country. I shall come in upon those having no disturbance, dwelling in security, all of them dwelling without wall, and they do not have even bar and doors.” 12 It will be to get a big spoil and to do much plundering, in order to turn your hand back upon devastated places reinhabited and upon a people gathered together out of the nations, one that is accumulating wealth and property, those who are dwelling in the center of the earth.

13 “‘She′ba and De′dan and the merchants of Tar′shish and all its maned young lions—they will say to you: “Is it to get a big spoil that you are coming in? Is it to do much plundering that you have congregated your congregation, in order to carry off silver and gold, to take wealth and property, to get a very great spoil?”’

14 “Therefore prophesy, O son of man, and you must say to Gog, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Will it not be in that day when my people Israel are dwelling in security that you will know it? 15 And you will certainly come from your place, from the remotest parts of the north, you and many peoples with you, all of them riding on horses, a great congregation, even a numerous military force. 16 And you will be bound to come up against my people Israel, like clouds to cover the land. In the final part of the days it will occur, and I shall certainly bring you against my land, for the purpose that the nations may know me when I sanctify myself in you before their eyes, O Gog.”’

17 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Are you the same one of whom I spoke in the former days by the hand of my servants the prophets of Israel, who were prophesying in those days—years—as to bringing you in upon them?’

18 “‘And it must occur in that day, in the day when Gog comes in upon the soil of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘that my rage will come up into my nose. 19 And in my ardor, in the fire of my fury, I shall have to speak. Surely in that day a great quaking will occur in the soil of Israel. 20 And because of me the fish of the sea and the flying creatures of the heavens and the wild beasts of the field and all the creeping things that are creeping on the ground and all mankind that are upon the surface of the ground will be bound to shiver, and the mountains will actually be thrown down and the steep ways will have to fall, and to the earth even every wall will fall.’

21 “‘And I will call forth against him throughout all my mountainous region a sword,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘Against his own brother the sword of each one will come to be. 22 And I will bring myself into judgment with him, with pestilence and with blood; and a flooding downpour and hailstones, fire and sulphur I shall rain down upon him and upon his bands and upon the many peoples that will be with him. 23 And I shall certainly magnify myself and sanctify myself and make myself known before the eyes of many nations; and they will have to know that I am Jehovah.’

Ezekiel

39 “And as regards you, O son of man, prophesy against Gog, and you must say, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “Here I am against you, O Gog, you head chieftain of Me′shech and Tu′bal. 2 And I will turn you around and lead you on and cause you to come up from the remotest parts of the north and bring you in upon the mountains of Israel. 3 And I will strike your bow out of your left hand, and your arrows I shall cause to fall out of your own right hand. 4 On the mountains of Israel you will fall, you and all your bands and the peoples that will be with you. To birds of prey, birds of every sort of wing, and the wild beasts of the field I will give you for food.”’

5 “‘Upon the surface of the field you will fall, for I myself have spoken,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

6 “‘And I will send fire upon Ma′gog and upon those who are inhabiting the islands in security; and people will have to know that I am Jehovah. 7 And my holy name I shall make known in the midst of my people Israel, and I shall no more let my holy name be profaned; and the nations will have to know that I am Jehovah, the Holy One in Israel.’

8 “‘Look! It must come and it must be brought to be,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. ‘This is the day of which I have spoken. 9 And the inhabitants of the cities of Israel will certainly go forth and burn and build fires with the armor and bucklers and large shields,—with the bows and with the arrows and with the handstaves and with the lances; and with them they will have to light fires seven years. 10 And they will not carry sticks of wood from the field, nor will they gather firewood out of the forests, for with the armor they will light fires.’

“‘And they will certainly make spoil of those who had been making spoil of them, and plunder those who had been plundering them,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

11 “‘And it must occur in that day that I shall give to Gog a place there, a burial place in Israel, the valley of those passing through on the east of the sea, and it will be stopping up those passing through. And there they will have to bury Gog and all his crowd, and they will be certain to call it the Valley of Gog’s Crowd. 12 And those of the house of Israel will have to bury them for the purpose of cleansing the land, for seven months. 13 And all the people of the land will have to do the burying, and it will certainly become for them a matter of fame in the day that I glorify myself,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

14 “‘And there will be men for continual employment whom they will divide off, passing along through the land, burying, with those passing through, those left remaining on the surface of the earth, in order to cleanse it. To the end of seven months they will keep making search. 15 And those passing through must pass along through the land, and should one actually see the bone of a man he must also build beside it a marker, until those who do the burying will have buried it in the Valley of Gog’s Crowd. 16 And the name of the city will also be Ha·mo′nah. And they will have to cleanse the land.’

17 “And as regards you, O son of man, this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Say to the birds of every sort of wing and to all the wild beasts of the field: “Collect yourselves together and come. Gather yourselves together all around to my sacrifice, which I am sacrificing for YOU, a great sacrifice on the mountains of Israel. And YOU will certainly eat flesh and drink blood. 18 The flesh of mighty ones YOU will eat, and the blood of the chieftains of the earth YOU will drink, rams, young male sheep, and he-goats, young bulls, the fatlings of Ba′shan all of them. 19 And YOU will be certain to eat fat to satisfaction and to drink blood to drunkenness, from my sacrifice that I will sacrifice for YOU.”’

20 “‘And YOU must get satisfied at my table on horses and charioteers, mighty persons and all sorts of warriors,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

21 “‘And I will set my glory among the nations; and all the nations will have to see my judgment that I have executed and my hand that I have placed among them. 22 And those of the house of Israel will have to know that I am Jehovah their God from that day and forward. 23 And the nations will have to know that it was because of their error that they, the house of Israel, went into exile, on account of the fact that they behaved unfaithfully toward me, so that I concealed my face from them and gave them into the hand of their adversaries, and they kept falling, all of them, by the sword. 24 According to their uncleanness and according to their transgressions I did with them, and I kept concealing my face from them.’

25 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘Now is when I shall bring back the captive ones of Jacob and actually have mercy upon all the house of Israel; and I will show exclusive devotion for my holy name. 26 And they will have borne their humiliation and all their unfaithfulness with which they have acted toward me, when they dwell on their soil in security, with no one to make them tremble. 27 When I bring them back from the peoples and I actually collect them together out of the lands of their enemies, I will also sanctify myself among them before the eyes of many nations.’

28 “‘And they will have to know that I am Jehovah their God, when I send them in exile to the nations and actually bring them together upon their soil, so that I shall leave none of them remaining there any longer. 29 And I shall no longer conceal my face from them, because I will pour out my spirit upon the house of Israel,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.”

Ezekiel

42 And he gradually brought me forth to the outer courtyard by the way toward the north. And he proceeded to bring me to the dining-room block that was in front of the separated area and that was in front of the building to the north. 2 Before the length of a hundred cubits there was the north entrance, and the width was fifty cubits. 3 In front of the twenty cubits that belonged to the inner courtyard and in front of the pavement that belonged to the outer courtyard there was gallery opposite gallery in three stories. 4 And before the dining rooms there was a walkway ten cubits in width to the inside, a way of one cubit, and their entrances were to the north. 5 And as for the dining rooms, the uppermost ones were shorter, for the galleries took away from them, more than the lowest ones and than the middle ones, as regards the building. 6 For they were in three stories, and they had no pillars like the pillars of the courtyards. That is why more room was taken away than from the lowest ones and from the middle ones from the floor.

7 And the stone wall that was outside was close by the dining rooms toward the outer courtyard before the other dining rooms. Its length was fifty cubits. 8 For the length of the dining rooms that were toward the outer courtyard was fifty cubits, and, look! before the temple it was a hundred cubits. 9 And from below these dining rooms the entryway was to the east, when one comes in to them from the outer courtyard.

10 In the width of the stone wall of the courtyard toward the east, before the separated area and before the building, there were dining rooms. 11 And there was a way before them like the appearance of the dining rooms that were toward the north, so their length was and so their width was; and all their exits were alike, and their plans alike and their entrances alike. 12 And like the entrances of the dining rooms that were toward the south was the entrance at the head of the way, the way before the corresponding stone wall toward the east, when one comes in to them.

13 And he proceeded to say to me: “The dining rooms of the north and the dining rooms of the south that are before the separated area, they are the holy dining rooms, where the priests who are approaching Jehovah eat the most holy things. There they deposit the most holy things and the grain offering and the sin offering and the guilt offering, because the place is holy. 14 When they, the priests, have come in, they will not also go out from the holy place to the outer courtyard, but there they will deposit their garments in which they customarily minister, for they are something holy. They will clothe themselves with other garments, and must approach to what has to do with the people.”

15 And he finished the measurements of the inner house, and he brought me out by the way of the gate the front of which was toward the east, and he measured it all around.

16 He measured the eastern side with the measuring reed. It was five hundred reeds, by the measuring reed, round about.

17 He measured the northern side, five hundred reeds, by the measuring reed, round about.

18 The southern side he measured, five hundred reeds, by the measuring reed.

19 He went around to the western side. He measured five hundred reeds, by the measuring reed.

20 For the four sides he measured it. It had a wall all around, with a length of five hundred reeds and a width of five hundred reeds, to make a division between what is holy and what is profane.

Ezekiel

44 And he proceeded to bring me back by way of the gate of the sanctuary, the outer one facing east, and it was shut. 2 Then Jehovah said to me: “As regards this gate, shut is how it will continue. It will not be opened, and no mere man will come in by it; for Jehovah himself, the God of Israel, has come in by it, and it must continue shut. 3 However, the chieftain—as chieftain he himself will sit in it, in order to eat bread before Jehovah. By way of the porch of the gate he will come in, and by way of it he will go out.”

4 And he now brought me by way of the north gate to before the House, that I might see, and, look! the glory of Jehovah had filled the house of Jehovah. And I went falling on my face. 5 Then Jehovah said to me: “Son of man, set your heart and see with your eyes, and with your ears hear all that I am speaking with you regarding all the statutes of the house of Jehovah and regarding all its laws, and you must set your heart upon the entryway of the House with all the exits of the sanctuary. 6 And you must say to Rebelliousness, to the house of Israel, ‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “That is enough of YOU because of all YOUR detestable things, O house of Israel, 7 when YOU bring in the foreigners uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, in order to come to be in my sanctuary so as to profane it, even my house; when YOU present my bread, fat and blood, while they keep breaking my covenant on account of all YOUR detestable things. 8 Neither have YOU taken care of the obligation of my holy things, nor would YOU post others as caretakers of my obligation in my sanctuary for yourselves.”’

9 “‘This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said: “No foreigner, uncircumcised in heart and uncircumcised in flesh, may come into my sanctuary, that is, any foreigner who is in the midst of the sons of Israel.”’

10 “‘But as for the Levites who got far away from me when Israel, who wandered away from me, wandered after their dungy idols, they must also bear their error. 11 And in my sanctuary they must become ministers at posts of oversight over the gates of the House and ministers at the House. They themselves will slaughter the whole burnt offering and the sacrifice for the people, and they themselves will stand before them to minister to them. 12 For the reason that they kept ministering to them before their dungy idols and became to the house of Israel a stumbling block into error, that is why I have raised my hand against them,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, ‘and they must bear their error. 13 And they will not approach to me to act as priest to me or to approach to any holy things of mine, to the most holy things, and they must bear their humiliation and their detestable things that they did. 14 And I shall certainly make them caretakers of the obligation of the House, as regards all its service and as regards all that should be done in it.’

15 “‘And as for the Levitical priests, the sons of Za′dok, who took care of the obligation of my sanctuary when the sons of Israel wandered away from me, they themselves will come near to me to minister to me, and they must stand before me to present to me fat and the blood,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 16 ‘They are the ones that will come into my sanctuary, and they themselves will come near to my table to minister to me, and they must take care of the obligation to me.

17 “‘And it must occur that when they come into the gates of the inner courtyard, linen garments they should wear, and no wool should come up on them when they minister in the gates of the inner courtyard and inside. 18 Linen headdresses are what should prove to be on their head, and linen drawers are what should prove to be upon their hips. They should not gird themselves with what causes sweat. 19 And when they go forth to the outer courtyard, even to the outer courtyard to the people, they should strip off their garments in which they were ministering, and they must deposit them in the holy dining rooms and put on other garments, that they may not sanctify the people with their garments. 20 And their head they should not shave, and the hair of the head they should not wear loose. They should by all means clip the hair of their heads. 21 And no wine should any priests drink when they come into the inner courtyard. 22 And no widow or divorced woman should they take for themselves as wives, but virgins of the offspring of the house of Israel or the widow who happens to be the widow of a priest they may take.’

23 “‘And my people they should instruct in the difference between a holy thing and a profane thing; and the difference between what is unclean and what is clean they should cause them to know. 24 And in a legal case they themselves should stand in order to judge; with my judicial decisions they must also judge it. And my laws and my statutes in regard to all my festal seasons they should keep, and my sabbaths they should sanctify. 25 And to a dead person of mankind he should not come in so as to become unclean, but for father or for mother or for son or for daughter or for brother or for a sister that has not become a husband’s they may make themselves unclean. 26 And after his purification, seven days they should number off for him. 27 And on the day of his coming into the holy place, into the inner courtyard, to minister in the holy place, he should present his sin offering,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

28 “‘And it must become theirs as an inheritance: I am their inheritance. And no possession should YOU people give them in Israel: I am their possession. 29 The grain offering and the sin offering and the guilt offering—they are the ones who will eat them. And every devoted thing in Israel—theirs it will become. 30 And the first of all the first ripe fruits of everything and every contribution of everything out of all YOUR contributions—to the priests it will come to belong; and the firstfruits of YOUR coarse meals YOU should give to the priest, in order to cause a blessing to rest upon your house. 31 No body already dead and no creature torn to pieces of the flying creatures or of the beasts should the priests eat.’

Ezekiel

45 “‘And when YOU people allot the land as an inheritance, YOU should offer a contribution to Jehovah, a holy portion out of the land; as to length, twenty-five thousand cubits in length, and as to width, ten thousand. It will be a holy portion in all its boundaries round about. 2 From this there will prove to be for the holy place five hundred by five hundred, it being made square round about; and fifty cubits it will have as pasture ground on each side. 3 And out of this measurement you should measure the length of twenty-five thousand and the width of ten thousand, and in it the sanctuary will come to be, something most holy. 4 As a holy portion out of the land it will come to be for the priests themselves, the ministers of the sanctuary, those approaching to minister to Jehovah. And for them it must prove to be a place for houses, and a sacred place for the sanctuary.

5 “‘There will be twenty-five thousand in length and ten thousand in width. It will become the Levites’, the ministers of the House. As a possession they will have twenty dining rooms.

6 “‘And as the possession of the city, YOU people will give five thousand in width and a length of twenty-five thousand, exactly as the holy contribution. To all the house of Israel it will come to belong.

7 “‘And for the chieftain there will be on this side and on that side of the holy contribution and of the possession of the city, beside the holy contribution and beside the possession of the city, something on the west side westward and something on the east side eastward. And the length will be exactly as one of the shares, from the western boundary to the eastern boundary. 8 As regards the land, it will become his as a possession in Israel. And no more will my chieftains maltreat my people, and the land they will give to the house of Israel with respect to their tribes.’

9 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘That is enough of YOU, O chieftains of Israel!’

“‘Remove the violence and the despoiling, and do justice and righteousness themselves. Lift YOUR expropriations off my people,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah. 10 ‘Accurate scales and an accurate e′phah and an accurate bath measure YOU men should come to have. 11 As regards the e′phah and the bath measure, there should come to be but one fixed amount, for the bath to carry a tenth of a ho′mer and the tenth of the ho′mer an e′phah; with reference to the ho′mer, its required amount should prove to be. 12 And the shekel is twenty ge′rahs. Twenty shekels, twenty-five shekels, fifteen shekels should prove to be the ma′neh for YOU.’

13 “‘This is the contribution that YOU should offer, the sixth part of the e′phah from the ho′mer of wheat, and the sixth part of the e′phah from the ho′mer of barley; 14 and as for the allowance of the oil, there is the bath measure of the oil. The bath is a tenth of the cor. Ten baths are a ho′mer; because ten baths are a ho′mer. 15 And one sheep out of the flock, out of two hundred from the livestock of Israel, for the grain offering and for the whole burnt offering and for the communion sacrifices, in order to make atonement for them,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

16 “‘As for all the people of the land, they will be responsible for this contribution to the chieftain in Israel. 17 And upon the chieftain will devolve the whole burnt offerings and the grain offering and the drink offering during the festivals and during the new moons and during the sabbaths, during all the festal seasons of the house of Israel. He will be the one to provide the sin offering and the grain offering and the whole burnt offering and the communion sacrifices, in order to make atonement in behalf of the house of Israel.’

18 “This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘In the first month, on the first day of the month, you should take a young bull, a son of the herd, a sound one, and you must purify the sanctuary from sin. 19 And the priest must take some of the blood of the sin offering and put it upon the doorpost of the House and upon the four corners of the surrounding ledge belonging to the altar and upon the doorpost of the gate of the inner courtyard. 20 And that is how you will do on the seventh day in the month because of any man making a mistake and because of any inexperienced one; and YOU people must make atonement for the House.

21 “‘In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month, there should occur for YOU the passover. As a festival for seven days unfermented cakes are what should be eaten. 22 And on that day, in his own behalf and in behalf of all the people of the land, the chieftain must provide a young bull as a sin offering. 23 And for the seven days of the festival he should provide as a whole burnt offering to Jehovah seven young bulls and seven rams, sound ones, daily for the seven days, and as a sin offering a buck of the goats daily. 24 And as a grain offering an e′phah for the young bull and an e′phah for the ram he should provide, and, as regards oil, a hin to the e′phah.

25 “‘In the seventh month, on the fifteenth day of the month, during the festival, he should provide the same as these for the seven days, the same as the sin offering, as the whole burnt offering, and as the grain offering and as the oil.’”

Ezekiel

48 “And these are the names of the tribes. From the northern extremity, on the side by the way of Heth′lon to the entering in to Ha′math, Ha′zar-e′nan, the boundary of Damascus northward, on the side of Ha′math; and it must prove to have an eastern border and the western, Dan one portion. 2 And on the boundary of Dan, from the eastern border to the western border, Ash′er one. 3 And on the boundary of Ash′er, from the eastern border even to the western border, Naph′ta·li one. 4 And on the boundary of Naph′ta·li, from the eastern border to the western border, Ma·nas′seh one. 5 And on the boundary of Ma·nas′seh, from the eastern border to the western border, E′phra·im one. 6 And on the boundary of E′phra·im, from the eastern border even to the western border, Reu′ben one. 7 And on the boundary of Reu′ben, from the eastern border to the western border, Judah one. 8 And on the boundary of Judah, from the eastern border to the western border, the contribution that YOU people should contribute should prove to be twenty-five thousand cubits in width, and the length according to one of the portions from the eastern border to the western border. And the sanctuary must prove to be in the midst of it.

9 “As regards the contribution that YOU should contribute to Jehovah, the length will be twenty-five thousand cubits and the width ten thousand. 10 And as to these there should prove to be the holy contribution for the priests, to the north twenty-five thousand cubits, and to the west a width of ten thousand, and to the east a width of ten thousand, and to the south a length of twenty-five thousand. And the sanctuary of Jehovah must prove to be in the midst of it. 11 It will be for the priests, those who are sanctified from the sons of Za′dok, who took care of the obligation toward me, who did not wander away when the sons of Israel wandered away, just as the Levites wandered away. 12 And they must come to have a contribution from the contribution of the land as something most holy, on the boundary of the Levites.

13 “And the Levites should have, right next to the territory of the priests, twenty-five thousand cubits in length, and in width ten thousand; the whole length being twenty-five thousand and width being ten thousand. 14 And they should not sell any of it, nor should one make an exchange, nor should one cause the choicest of the land to pass away from them; for it is something holy to Jehovah.

15 “As regards the five thousand cubits that is left remaining in width alongside the twenty-five thousand, it is something profane for the city, for a dwelling place and for pasture ground. And the city must come to be in the midst of it. 16 And these are the city’s measurements: the northern border four thousand five hundred cubits, and the southern border four thousand five hundred, and the eastern border four thousand five hundred, and the western border four thousand five hundred. 17 And the city must come to have a pasture ground, to the north two hundred and fifty cubits, and to the south two hundred and fifty, and to the east two hundred and fifty, and to the west two hundred and fifty.

18 “And what is left remaining over in length will be exactly as the holy contribution, ten thousand cubits to the east, and ten thousand to the west; and it must prove to be exactly as the holy contribution, and its produce must come to be for bread for the ones serving the city. 19 And those who are serving the city out of all the tribes of Israel will cultivate it.

20 “The whole contribution is twenty-five thousand cubits by twenty-five thousand. A foursquare part YOU people should contribute as the holy contribution with the possession of the city.

21 “And what is left over will belong to the chieftain, on this side and on that side of the holy contribution and of the possession of the city, alongside the twenty-five thousand cubits of the contribution to the eastern boundary; and on the west alongside the twenty-five thousand cubits to the western boundary. Exactly like the portions, it will be for the chieftain. And the holy contribution and the sanctuary of the House must prove to be in the midst of it.

22 “And as regards the possession of the Levites and the possession of the city, in between what belongs to the chieftain it should prove to be. Between the boundary of Judah and the boundary of Benjamin it should come to belong to the chieftain.

23 “And as regards the rest of the tribes, from the eastern border to the western border, Benjamin one portion. 24 And by the boundary of Benjamin, from the eastern border to the western border, Sim′e·on one. 25 And by the boundary of Sim′e·on, from the eastern border to the western border, Is′sa·char one. 26 And by the boundary of Is′sa·char, from the eastern border to the western border, Zeb′u·lun one. 27 And by the boundary of Zeb′u·lun, from the eastern border to the western border, Gad one. 28 And by the boundary of Gad, to the southern border, it will be southward; and the boundary must prove to be from Ta′mar to the waters of Mer′i·bath-ka′desh, to the torrent valley, as far as the Great Sea.

29 “This will be the land that YOU people should cause to fall by lot for inheritance to the tribes of Israel, and these will be their shares,” is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah.

30 “And these will be the outlets of the city: On the northern border, four thousand five hundred cubits will be the measurement.

31 “And the gates of the city will be according to the names of the tribes of Israel, three gates being on the north, the gate of Reu′ben, one; the gate of Judah, one; the gate of Le′vi, one.

32 “And on the eastern border there will be four thousand five hundred cubits, and three gates, even the gate of Joseph, one; the gate of Benjamin, one; the gate of Dan, one.

33 “And the southern border will be four thousand five hundred cubits as to measurement, with three gates, the gate of Sim′e·on, one; the gate of Is′sa·char, one; the gate of Zeb′u·lun, one.

34 “The western border will be four thousand five hundred cubits, there being three gates, the gate of Gad, one; the gate of Ash′er, one; the gate of Naph′ta·li, one.

35 “Round about there will be eighteen thousand cubits; and the name of the city from that day on will be Jehovah Himself Is There.”

Daniel

3 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king made an image of gold, the height of which was sixty cubits and the breadth of which was six cubits. He set it up in the plain of Du′ra in the jurisdictional district of Babylon. 2 And Neb·u·chad·nez′zar himself as king sent to assemble the satraps, the prefects and the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the police magistrates and all the administrators of the jurisdictional districts to come to the inauguration of the image that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king had set up.

3 At that time the satraps, the prefects and the governors, the counselors, the treasurers, the judges, the police magistrates and all the administrators of the jurisdictional districts were assembling themselves for the inauguration of the image that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king had set up, and they were standing in front of the image that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar had set up. 4 And the herald was crying out loudly: “To YOU it is being said, O peoples, national groups and languages, 5 that at the time that YOU hear the sound of the horn, the pipe, the zither, the triangular harp, the stringed instrument, the bagpipe and all sorts of musical instruments, YOU fall down and worship the image of gold that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king has set up. 6 And whoever does not fall down and worship will at the same moment be thrown into the burning fiery furnace.” 7 Because of this, at the same time as all the peoples were hearing the sound of the horn, the pipe, the zither, the triangular harp, the stringed instrument and all sorts of musical instruments, all the peoples, national groups and languages were falling down and worshiping the image of gold that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king had set up.

8 Because of this, at that same time certain Chal·de′ans approached and accused the Jews. 9 They answered, and they were saying to Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king: “O king, live on even for times indefinite. 10 You yourself, O king, set forth the command that every man that hears the sound of the horn, the pipe, the zither, the triangular harp, the stringed instrument, and the bagpipe and all sorts of musical instruments, should fall down and worship the image of gold; 11 and that whoever would not fall down and worship should be thrown into the burning fiery furnace. 12 There exist certain Jews whom you appointed over the administration of the jurisdictional district of Babylon, Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go; these able-bodied men have paid no regard to you, O king, they are not serving your own gods, and the image of gold that you have set up they are not worshiping.”

13 At that time Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, in a rage and fury, said to bring in Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go. Consequently these able-bodied men were brought in before the king. 14 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar was answering and saying to them: “Is it really so, O Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go, that YOU are not serving my own gods, and the image of gold that I have set up YOU are not worshiping? 15 Now if YOU are ready so that when YOU hear the sound of the horn, the pipe, the zither, the triangular harp, the stringed instrument, and the bagpipe and all sorts of musical instruments, YOU fall down and worship the image that I have made, all right. But if YOU do not worship, at that same moment YOU will be thrown into the burning fiery furnace. And who is that god that can rescue YOU out of my hands?”

16 Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go answered, and they were saying to the king: “O Neb·u·chad·nez′zar, we are under no necessity in this regard to say back a word to you. 17 If it is to be, our God whom we are serving is able to rescue us. Out of the burning fiery furnace and out of your hand, O king, he will rescue us. 18 But if not, let it become known to you, O king, that your gods are not the ones we are serving, and the image of gold that you have set up we will not worship.”

19 Then it was that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar himself got filled with fury, and the very expression of his face was changed toward Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go. He was answering and saying to heat up the furnace seven times more than it was customary to heat it up. 20 And to certain able-bodied men of vital energy who were in his military force he said to bind Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go, in order to throw them into the burning fiery furnace.

21 Then it was that these able-bodied men were bound in their mantles, their garments and their caps and their other clothing and were thrown into the burning fiery furnace. 22 Just because the king’s word was harsh and the furnace was heated to excess, these able-bodied men that took up Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go were the ones that the fiery flame killed. 23 But these other able-bodied men, the three of them, Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go, fell down bound in the midst of the burning fiery furnace.

24 At that time Neb·u·chad·nez′zar the king himself became frightened and he rose up in a hurry. He was answering and saying to his high royal officials: “Was it not three able-bodied men that we threw bound into the midst of the fire?” They were answering and saying to the king: “Yes, O king.” 25 He was answering and saying: “Look! I am beholding four able-bodied men walking about free in the midst of the fire, and there is no hurt to them, and the appearance of the fourth one is resembling a son of the gods.”

26 Then it was that Neb·u·chad·nez′zar approached the door of the burning fiery furnace. He was answering and saying: “Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go, YOU servants of the Most High God, step out and come here!” At that time Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go were stepping out from the midst of the fire. 27 And the satraps, the prefects and the governors and the high officials of the king that were assembled were beholding these able-bodied men, that the fire had had no power over their bodies, and not a hair of their head had been singed, and even their mantles had not been changed and the smell of fire itself had not come onto them.

28 Neb·u·chad·nez′zar was answering and saying: “Blessed be the God of Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go, who sent his angel and rescued his servants that trusted in him and that changed the very word of the king and gave over their bodies, because they would not serve and would not worship any god at all except their own God. 29 And from me an order is being put through, that any people, national group or language that says anything wrong against the God of Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go should be dismembered, and its house should be turned into a public privy; forasmuch as there does not exist another god that is able to deliver like this one.”

30 At that time the king himself caused Sha′drach, Me′shach and A·bed′ne·go to prosper in the jurisdictional district of Babylon.

Daniel

9 In the first year of Da·ri′us the son of A·has·u·e′rus of the seed of the Medes, who had been made king over the kingdom of the Chal·de′ans; 2 in the first year of his reigning I myself, Daniel, discerned by the books the number of the years concerning which the word of Jehovah had occurred to Jeremiah the prophet, for fulfilling the devastations of Jerusalem, namely, seventy years. 3 And I proceeded to set my face to Jehovah the true God, in order to seek him with prayer and with entreaties, with fasting and sackcloth and ashes. 4 And I began to pray to Jehovah my God and to make confession and to say:

“Ah Jehovah the true God, the great One and the fear-inspiring One, keeping the covenant and the loving-kindness to those loving him and to those keeping his commandments, 5 we have sinned and done wrong and acted wickedly and rebelled; and there has been a turning aside from your commandments and from your judicial decisions. 6 And we have not listened to your servants the prophets, who have spoken in your name to our kings, our princes and our forefathers and to all the people of the land. 7 To you, O Jehovah, there belongs the righteousness, but to us the shame of face as at this day, to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and to all those of Israel, those nearby and those far away in all the lands to which you dispersed them because of their unfaithfulness with which they acted against you.

8 “O Jehovah, to us belongs the shame of face, to our kings, to our princes and to our forefathers, because we have sinned against you. 9 To Jehovah our God belong the mercies and the acts of forgiveness, for we have rebelled against him. 10 And we have not obeyed the voice of Jehovah our God by walking in his laws that he set before us by the hand of his servants the prophets. 11 And all those of Israel have overstepped your law, and there has been a turning aside by not obeying your voice, so that you poured out upon us the curse and the sworn oath that is written in the law of Moses the servant of the true God, for we have sinned against Him. 12 And he proceeded to carry out his words that he had spoken against us and against our judges who judged us, by bringing upon us great calamity, such as was not done under the whole heavens as what has been done in Jerusalem. 13 Just as it is written in the law of Moses, all this calamity—it has come upon us, and we have not softened the face of Jehovah our God by turning back from our error and by showing insight into your trueness.

14 “And Jehovah kept alert to the calamity and finally brought it upon us, for Jehovah our God is righteous in all his works that he has done; and we have not obeyed his voice.

15 “And now, O Jehovah our God, you who brought your people out from the land of Egypt by a strong hand and proceeded to make a name for yourself as at this day, we have sinned, we have acted wickedly. 16 O Jehovah, according to all your acts of righteousness, please, may your anger and your rage turn back from your city Jerusalem, your holy mountain; for, because of our sins and because of the errors of our forefathers, Jerusalem and your people are an object of reproach to all those round about us. 17 And now listen, O our God, to the prayer of your servant and to his entreaties, and cause your face to shine upon your sanctuary that is desolated, for the sake of Jehovah. 18 Incline your ear, O my God, and hear. Do open your eyes and see our desolated conditions and the city that has been called by your name; for not according to our righteous acts are we letting our entreaties fall before you, but according to your many mercies. 19 O Jehovah, do hear. O Jehovah, do forgive. O Jehovah, do pay attention and act. Do not delay, for your own sake, O my God, for your own name has been called upon your city and upon your people.”

20 While I was yet speaking and praying and confessing my sin and the sin of my people Israel and letting my request for favor fall before Jehovah my God concerning the holy mountain of my God, 21 and while I was yet speaking in the prayer, why, the man Ga′bri·el, whom I had seen in the vision at the start, having been made weary with tiredness, was arriving by me at the time of the evening gift offering. 22 And he proceeded to impart understanding and speak with me and say:

“O Daniel, now I have come forth to make you have insight with understanding. 23 At the start of your entreaties a word went forth, and I myself have come to make report, because you are someone very desirable. So give consideration to the matter, and have understanding in the thing seen.

24 “There are seventy weeks that have been determined upon your people and upon your holy city, in order to terminate the transgression, and to finish off sin, and to make atonement for error, and to bring in righteousness for times indefinite, and to imprint a seal upon vision and prophet, and to anoint the Holy of Holies. 25 And you should know and have the insight that from the going forth of the word to restore and to rebuild Jerusalem until Mes·si′ah the Leader, there will be seven weeks, also sixty-two weeks. She will return and be actually rebuilt, with a public square and moat, but in the straits of the times.

26 “And after the sixty-two weeks Mes·si′ah will be cut off, with nothing for himself.

“And the city and the holy place the people of a leader that is coming will bring to their ruin. And the end of it will be by the flood. And until the end there will be war; what is decided upon is desolations.

27 “And he must keep the covenant in force for the many for one week; and at the half of the week he will cause sacrifice and gift offering to cease.

“And upon the wing of disgusting things there will be the one causing desolation; and until an extermination, the very thing decided upon will go pouring out also upon the one lying desolate.”

Hosea

1 The word of Jehovah that occurred to Ho·se′a the son of Be·e′ri in the days of Uz·zi′ah, Jo′tham, A′haz and Hez·e·ki′ah, kings of Judah, and in the days of Jer·o·bo′am the son of Jo′ash, the king of Israel. 2 There was a start of the word of Jehovah by Ho·se′a, and Jehovah proceeded to say to Ho·se′a: “Go, take to yourself a wife of fornication and children of fornication, because by fornication the land positively turns from following Jehovah.”

3 And he proceeded to go and take Go′mer the daughter of Dib·la′im, so that she became pregnant and in time bore to him a son.

4 And Jehovah went on to say to him: “Call his name Jez′re·el, for yet a little while and I must hold an accounting for the acts of bloodshed of Jez′re·el against the house of Je′hu, and I must cause the royal rule of the house of Israel to cease. 5 And it must occur in that day that I must break the bow of Israel in the low plain of Jez′re·el.”

6 And she proceeded to become pregnant another time and to give birth to a daughter. And He went on to say to him: “Call her name Lo-ru·ha′mah, for I shall no more show mercy again to the house of Israel, because I shall positively take them away. 7 But to the house of Judah I shall show mercy, and I will save them by Jehovah their God; but I shall not save them by a bow or by a sword or by war, by horses or by horsemen.”

8 And she gradually weaned Lo-ru·ha′mah, and she proceeded to become pregnant and give birth to a son. 9 So He said: “Call his name Lo-am′mi, because YOU men are not my people and I myself shall prove to be not YOURS.

10 “And the number of the sons of Israel must become like the grains of the sand of the sea that cannot be measured or numbered. And it must occur that in the place in which it used to be said to them, ‘YOU men are not my people,’ it will be said to them, ‘The sons of the living God.’ 11 And the sons of Judah and the sons of Israel will certainly be collected together into a unity and will actually set up for themselves one head and go up out of the land, because great will be the day of Jez′re·el.

Hosea

4 Hear the word of Jehovah, O sons of Israel, for Jehovah has a legal case with the inhabitants of the land, for there is no truth nor loving-kindness nor knowledge of God in the land. 2 There are the pronouncing of curses and practicing of deception and murdering and stealing and committing of adultery that have broken forth, and acts of bloodshed have touched other acts of bloodshed. 3 That is why the land will mourn and every inhabitant in it will have to fade away with the wild beast of the field and with the flying creature of the heavens, and even the fishes of the sea themselves will be gathered in death.

4 “However, let no man contend, neither let a man reprove, as your people are like those who are contending against a priest. 5 And you will certainly stumble in the daytime, and even a prophet must stumble with you, as at night. And I will put your mother to silence. 6 My people will certainly be silenced, because there is no knowledge. Because the knowledge is what you yourself have rejected, I shall also reject you from serving as a priest to me; and because you keep forgetting the law of your God, I shall forget your sons, even I. 7 In proportion to the multitude of them, so they have sinned against me. My own glory they have exchanged for mere dishonor. 8 The sin of my people is what they keep devouring, and to their error they keep lifting up their soul.

9 “And it will have to become for the people the same as for the priest; and I shall certainly hold an accounting against them for their ways; and their dealings I shall bring back upon them. 10 And they will actually eat, but will not get satisfied. They will actually treat women as harlots; but they will not increase, because they have left off paying regard to Jehovah himself. 11 Fornication and wine and sweet wine are what take away good motive. 12 Of their wooden idol my own people keep inquiring, and their own hand staff keeps telling them; because the very spirit of fornication has caused them to wander off, and by fornication they go out from under their God. 13 On the tops of the mountains they sacrifice, and on the hills they make sacrificial smoke, under massive tree and storax tree and big tree, because its shade is good. That is why YOUR daughters commit fornication and YOUR own daughters-in-law commit adultery.

14 “I shall not hold an accounting against YOUR daughters because they commit fornication, and against YOUR daughters-in-law because they commit adultery. For, as to the men, it is with the harlots that they get off to themselves, and with the female temple prostitutes that they sacrifice; and a people that does not understand will be trodden down. 15 Although you are committing fornication, O Israel, let not Judah become guilty, and do not YOU people come to Gil′gal, neither go up to Beth-a′ven nor swear ‘As Jehovah is alive!’ 16 For, like a stubborn cow, Israel has become stubborn. Is it now that Jehovah will shepherd them like a young ram in a roomy place? 17 E′phra·im is joined with idols. Let him be to himself! 18 Their wheat beer being gone, they have positively treated woman as a harlot. Her shielders have positively loved dishonor. 19 A wind has wrapped her up in its wings. And they will be ashamed of their sacrifices.”

Hosea

7 “At the time that I would bring healing to Israel, the error of E′phra·im is also actually uncovered, and the bad things of Sa·mar′i·a; for they have practiced falsehood, and a thief himself comes in; a marauder band actually makes a dash on the outside. 2 And they do not say to their own heart that all their badness I will remember. Now their dealings have surrounded them. In front of my face they have come to be. 3 By their badness they make the king rejoice, and, by their deceptions, princes. 4 All of them are adulterers, like a furnace set burning by a baker, who ceases poking after kneading dough until it is leavened. 5 On the day of our king, princes have sickened themselves—there is a rage because of wine. He has drawn his hand along with deriders. 6 For they have brought their heart near as to a furnace; it is burning inside them. All night long their baker is sleeping; by morning the furnace is burning as with a flaming fire. 7 They get hot, all of them, like the furnace, and they actually devour their judges. Their own kings have all fallen; none among them is calling out to me.

8 “As for E′phra·im, it is among the peoples that he personally mingles himself. E′phra·im himself has become a round cake not turned on the other side. 9 Strangers have eaten up his power, and he himself has not come to know it. Also, gray hairs themselves have become white on him, but he himself has not come to know it. 10 And the pride of Israel has testified to his face, and they have not returned to Jehovah their God, nor have they looked for him because of all this. 11 And E′phra·im proves to be like a simpleminded dove without heart. To Egypt they have called; to As·syr′i·a they have gone.

12 “Whichever way they go, I shall spread out over them my net. Like flying creatures of the heavens I shall bring them down. I shall discipline them in agreement with the report to their assembly. 13 Woe to them, for they have fled from me! Despoiling to them, for they have transgressed against me! And I myself proceeded to redeem them, but they themselves have spoken lies even against me. 14 And they did not call to me for aid with their heart, although they kept howling on their beds. On account of their grain and sweet wine they kept loafing about; they kept turning against me. 15 And I, for my part, did disciplining; I strengthened their arms, but against me they kept scheming what was bad. 16 And they proceeded to return, not to anything higher; they had become like a loose bow. By the sword their princes will fall because of the denunciation of their tongue. This will be their derision in the land of Egypt.”

Hosea

8 “To your mouth—a horn! One comes like an eagle against the house of Jehovah, for the reason that they have overstepped my covenant, and against my law they have transgressed. 2 To me they keep crying, ‘O my God, we, Israel, have known you.’

3 “Israel has cast off good. Let one who is an enemy pursue him. 4 They themselves have set up kings, but not because of me. They have set up princes, but I did not know it. With their silver and their gold they have made for themselves idols, to the end that they may be cut off. 5 Your calf has been cast off, O Sa·mar′i·a. My anger has grown hot against them. How long will they be incapable of innocency? 6 For from Israel was even this. A mere craftsman made it, and it is not God; because the calf of Sa·mar′i·a will become mere splinters.

7 “For it is wind that they keep sowing, and a storm wind is what they will reap. Nothing has standing grain. No sprout produces flour. Should any perhaps produce it, strangers themselves will swallow it down.

8 “Israel must be swallowed down. Now they must come to be among the nations, like a vessel in which there is no delight. 9 For they themselves have gone up to As·syr′i·a, as a zebra isolated to itself. In E′phra·im’s case, they have hired lovers. 10 Also, although they keep hiring them among the nations, I shall now collect them together; and they will be a little while in severe pains because of the burden of king and princes.

11 “For E′phra·im has multiplied altars in order to sin. He has come to have altars in order to sin. 12 I proceeded to write for him many things of my law; just like something strange they have been accounted. 13 As my gift sacrifices they kept sacrificing flesh, and they kept eating what Jehovah himself took no pleasure in. Now he will remember their error and hold an accounting for their sins. To Egypt they themselves proceeded to return. 14 And Israel began forgetting his Maker and building temples; and Judah, for his part, multiplied fortified cities. And I shall certainly send fire into his cities and it must devour the dwelling towers of each one.”

Hosea

9 “Do not rejoice, O Israel. Do not act joyful like the peoples. For by fornication you have gone from alongside your God. You have loved gifts of hire on all the threshing floors of grain. 2 Threshing floor and winepress do not feed them, and sweet wine itself proves disappointing to her. 3 They will not continue dwelling in the land of Jehovah, and E′phra·im must return to Egypt, and in As·syr′i·a they will eat what is unclean. 4 They will not continue pouring out wine to Jehovah. And their sacrifices will not be gratifying to him; they are like the bread of times of mourning to them; all those eating it will defile themselves. For their bread is for their own soul; it will not come into the house of Jehovah. 5 What will YOU people do in the day of meeting and in the day of the festival of Jehovah? 6 For, look! they will have to go because of despoiling. Egypt itself will collect them together; Mem′phis, for its part, will bury them. As for their desirable things of silver, nettles themselves will take possession of them; thorny bushes will be in their tents.

7 “The days of being given attention must come; the days of the due payment must come. Those of Israel will know it. The prophet will be foolish, the man of inspired expression will be maddened on account of the abundance of your error, even animosity being abundant.”

8 The watchman of E′phra·im was with my God. As regards a prophet, there is the trap of a birdcatcher on all his ways; there is an animosity in the house of his God. 9 They have gone down deep in bringing ruin, as in the days of Gib′e·ah. He will remember their error; he will give attention to their sins.

10 “Like grapes in the wilderness I found Israel. Like the early fig on a fig tree in its beginning I saw the forefathers of YOU people. They themselves went in to Ba′al of Pe′or, and they proceeded to dedicate themselves to the shameful thing, and they came to be disgusting like the thing of their love. 11 As regards E′phra·im, like a flying creature their glory flies away, so that there is no giving birth, and no pregnant belly and no conception. 12 For although they bring up their sons, I will also bereave them of children so that there will be no man; because—woe also to them when I turn away from them! 13 E′phra·im, whom I have seen like Tyre planted in a pasture ground, even E′phra·im is destined to a bringing out of his sons even to a killer.”

14 Give to them, O Jehovah, what you should give. Give them a miscarrying womb and breasts shriveling up.

15 “All their badness was in Gil′gal, for there I had to hate them. On account of the evil of their dealings I shall drive them away from my own house. I will not continue on loving them. All their princes are acting stubborn. 16 E′phra·im must be struck down. Their very root must dry up. There will be no fruit that they produce. Also, in case they bring to birth, I will even put to death the desirable things of their belly.”

17 My God will reject them, for they have not listened to him, and they will become fugitives among the nations.

Hosea

10 “Israel is a degenerating vine. Fruit he keeps putting forth for himself. In proportion to the abundance of his fruit he has multiplied his altars. In proportion to the goodness of his land, they put up good pillars. 2 Their heart has become hypocritical; now they will be found guilty.

“There is one who will break their altars; he will despoil their pillars. 3 For now they will say, ‘We have no king, for we have not feared Jehovah. And as regards the king, what will he do for us?’

4 “They speak words, making false oaths, concluding a covenant; and judgment has sprouted like a poisonous plant in the furrows of the open field. 5 For the calf idol of Beth-a′ven the residents of Sa·mar′i·a will get frightened; for over it its people will certainly mourn, as well as its foreign-god priests who used to be joyful over it, on account of its glory, because it will have gone into exile away from it. 6 Even it someone will bring to As·syr′i·a itself as a gift to a great king. Shame is what E′phra·im himself will get, and Israel will be ashamed of its counsel. 7 Sa·mar′i·a and her king will certainly be silenced, like a snapped-off twig on the surface of waters. 8 And the high places of Beth-a′ven, the sin of Israel, will actually be annihilated. Thorns and thistles themselves will come up upon their altars. And people will in fact say to the mountains, ‘Cover us!’ and to the hills, ‘Fall over us!’

9 “From the days of Gib′e·ah you have sinned, O Israel. There they stood still. In Gib′e·ah war against the sons of unrighteousness did not get to overtake them. 10 When it is my craving I shall also discipline them. And against them peoples will certainly be gathered when there is a harnessing of them to their two errors.

11 “And E′phra·im was a trained heifer loving to thresh; and I, for my part, passed over her good-looking neck. I make someone ride E′phra·im. Judah plows; Jacob harrows for him. 12 Sow seed for yourselves in righteousness; reap in accord with loving-kindness. Till for yourselves arable land, when there is time for searching for Jehovah until he comes and gives instruction in righteousness to YOU.

13 “YOU people have plowed wickedness. Unrighteousness is what YOU have reaped. YOU have eaten the fruitage of deception, for you have trusted in your way, in the multitude of your mighty ones. 14 And an uproar has risen among your people, and your own fortified cities will all be despoiled, as with the despoiling by Shal′man of the house of Ar′bel, in the day of battle when a mother herself was dashed to pieces alongside her own sons. 15 In this way one will certainly do to YOU people, O Beth′el, because of YOUR extreme badness. In the dawn the king of Israel will positively have to be silenced.”

Amos

3 “Hear this word that Jehovah has spoken concerning YOU, O sons of Israel, concerning the whole family that I brought up out of the land of Egypt, saying, 2 ‘YOU people only have I known out of all the families of the ground. That is why I shall hold an accounting against YOU for all YOUR errors.

3 “‘Will two walk together unless they have met by appointment? 4 Will a lion roar in the forest when it has no prey? Will a young maned lion give forth its voice from its hiding place if it has caught nothing at all? 5 Will a bird fall into a trap on the earth when there is no snare for it? Does a trap go up from the ground when it has absolutely caught nothing? 6 If a horn is blown in a city, do not also the people themselves tremble? If a calamity occurs in the city, is it not also Jehovah who has acted? 7 For the Sovereign Lord Jehovah will not do a thing unless he has revealed his confidential matter to his servants the prophets. 8 There is a lion that has roared! Who will not be afraid? The Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself has spoken! Who will not prophesy?’

9 “‘PUBLISH it on the dwelling towers in Ash′dod and on the dwelling towers in the land of Egypt, and say: “Be gathered together against the mountains of Sa·mar′i·a, and see the many disorders in the midst of her and cases of defrauding inside her. 10 And they have not known how to do what is straightforward,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “those who are storing up violence and despoiling in their dwelling towers.”’

11 “Therefore this is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah has said, ‘There is an adversary even round about the land, and he will certainly bring your strength down from you, and your dwelling towers will actually be plundered.’

12 “This is what Jehovah has said, ‘Just as the shepherd snatches away from the mouth of the lion two shanks or a piece of an ear, so the sons of Israel will be snatched away, those sitting in Sa·mar′i·a on a splendid couch and on a Dam·a·scene′ divan.’

13 “‘HEAR and give witness in the house of Jacob,’ is the utterance of the Sovereign Lord Jehovah, the God of the armies. 14 ‘For, in the day of my holding an accounting for the revolts of Israel against him, I will also hold an accounting against the altars of Beth′el; and the horns of the altar will certainly be cut off and must fall to the earth. 15 And I will strike down the winter house in addition to the summer house.’

“‘And the houses of ivory will have to perish, and many houses will have to come to their finish,’ is the utterance of Jehovah.”

Amos

6 “Woe to those who are at ease in Zion and to those trusting in the mountain of Sa·mar′i·a! They are the distinguished ones of the chief part of the nations, and to them the house of Israel have come. 2 Make YOUR way over to Cal′neh, and see; and go from there to populous Ha′math, and go down to Gath of the Phi·lis′tines. Are they better than these kingdoms, or is their territory bigger than YOUR territory? 3 Are YOU putting out of YOUR mind the calamitous day, and do YOU bring near the dwelling of violence? 4 YOU men that are lying down on couches of ivory and are sprawling on their divans, and are eating the rams out of a flock and the young bulls from among fattened calves; 5 that are improvising according to the sound of the stringed instrument; that, like David, have devised for themselves instruments for song; 6 that are drinking out of bowls of wine, and that with the choicest oils do their anointing, and that have not been made sick at the catastrophe of Joseph.

7 “Therefore now they will go into exile at the head of those going into exile, and the revelry of sprawling ones must depart.

8 “‘The Sovereign Lord Jehovah has sworn by his own soul,’ is the utterance of Jehovah the God of armies, ‘“I am detesting the pride of Jacob, and his dwelling towers I have hated, and I will deliver up the city and what fills it. 9 And it must occur that if ten men should be left remaining in one house, they must also die. 10 And his father’s brother will have to carry them forth one by one, and will be burning them one by one, in order to bring out the bones from the house. And he will have to say to whoever is in the innermost parts of the house, ‘Are there any more with you?’ And he will certainly say, ‘Nobody!’ And he will have to say, ‘Keep silence! For it is not the occasion for making any mention of the name of Jehovah.’”

11 “‘For here is Jehovah commanding, and he will certainly strike down the great house into rubble and the small house into debris.

12 “‘On a crag will horses run, or will one plow there with cattle? For into a poisonous plant YOU people have turned justice, and the fruitage of righteousness into wormwood, 13 YOU who are rejoicing in a thing that is not; who are saying: “Have we not in our strength taken horns to ourselves?” 14 Look! I am raising up against YOU, O house of Israel,’ is the utterance of Jehovah the God of the armies, ‘a nation, and they must oppress YOU people from the entering in of Ha′math down to the torrent valley of the Ar′a·bah.’”

Amos

7 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah caused me to see, and, look! he was forming a locust swarm at the start of the coming up of the later sowing. And, look! it was the later sowing after the mown grass of the king. 2 And it occurred that when it had finished eating up the vegetation of the land, I proceeded to say: “O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, forgive, please. Who will rise up of Jacob? For he is small!”

3 Jehovah felt regret over this. “It shall not occur,” Jehovah said.

4 This is what the Sovereign Lord Jehovah caused me to see, and, look! the Sovereign Lord Jehovah was calling for a contention by means of fire; and it went eating up the vast watery deep and ate up the tract of land. 5 And I proceeded to say: “O Sovereign Lord Jehovah, hold off, please. Who will rise up of Jacob? For he is small!”

6 Jehovah felt regret over this. “That, too, will not occur,” the Sovereign Lord Jehovah said.

7 This is what he caused me to see, and, look! Jehovah was stationed on a wall made with a plummet, and there was a plummet in his hand. 8 Then Jehovah said to me: “What are you seeing, A′mos?” So I said: “A plummet.” And Jehovah went on to say: “Here I am setting a plummet in the midst of my people Israel. I shall no more do any further excusing of it. 9 And the high places of Isaac will certainly be laid desolate, and the sanctuaries themselves of Israel will be devastated; and I will rise up against the house of Jer·o·bo′am with a sword.”

10 And Am·a·zi′ah the priest of Beth′el proceeded to send to Jer·o·bo′am the king of Israel, saying: “A′mos has conspired against you right inside the house of Israel. The land is not able to put up with all his words. 11 For this is what A′mos has said, ‘By the sword Jer·o·bo′am will die; and as regards Israel, it will without fail go into exile from its own ground.’”

12 And Am·a·zi′ah proceeded to say to A′mos: “O visionary, go, run your way off to the land of Judah, and there eat bread, and there you may prophesy. 13 But at Beth′el you must no longer do any further prophesying, for it is the sanctuary of a king and it is the house of a kingdom.”

14 Then A′mos answered and said to Am·a·zi′ah: “I was not a prophet, neither was I the son of a prophet; but I was a herdsman and a nipper of figs of sycamore trees. 15 And Jehovah proceeded to take me from following the flock, and Jehovah went on to say to me, ‘Go, prophesy to my people Israel.’ 16 And now hear the word of Jehovah, ‘Are you saying: “You must not prophesy against Israel, and you must let no word drop against the house of Isaac”? 17 Therefore this is what Jehovah has said: “As regards your wife, in the city she will become a prostitute. And as regards your sons and your daughters, by the sword they will fall. And as regards your ground, by the measuring rope it will be apportioned out. And as regards you yourself, on unclean ground you will die; and as regards Israel, it will without fail go into exile from its own ground.”’”

Jonah

3 Then the word of Jehovah occurred to Jo′nah the second time, saying: 2 “Get up, go to Nin′e·veh the great city, and proclaim to her the proclamation that I am speaking to you.”

3 At that, Jo′nah got up and went to Nin′e·veh in accord with the word of Jehovah. Now Nin′e·veh herself proved to be a city great to God, with a walking distance of three days. 4 Finally Jo′nah started to enter into the city the walking distance of one day, and he kept proclaiming and saying: “Only forty days more, and Nin′e·veh will be overthrown.”

5 And the men of Nin′e·veh began to put faith in God, and they proceeded to proclaim a fast and to put on sackcloth, from the greatest one of them even to the least one of them. 6 When the word reached the king of Nin′e·veh, then he rose up from his throne and put off his official garment from himself and covered himself with sackcloth and sat down in the ashes. 7 Furthermore, he had the cry made, and he had it said in Nin′e·veh, by the decree of the king and his great ones, saying:

“No man and no domestic animal, no herd and no flock, should taste anything at all. None should take food. Even water they should not drink. 8 And let them cover themselves with sackcloth, man and domestic animal; and let them call out to God with strength and come back, each one from his bad way and from the violence that was in their hands. 9 Who is there knowing whether the true God may turn back and actually feel regret and turn back from his burning anger, so that we may not perish?”

10 And the true God got to see their works, that they had turned back from their bad way; and so the true God felt regret over the calamity that he had spoken of causing to them; and he did not cause it.

Micah

2 “Woe to those who are scheming what is harmful, and to those practicing what is bad, upon their beds! By the light of the morning they proceed to do it, because it is in the power of their hand. 2 And they have desired fields and have seized them; also houses, and have taken them; and they have defrauded an able-bodied man and his household, a man and his hereditary possession.

3 “Therefore this is what Jehovah has said, ‘Here I am thinking up against this family a calamity from which YOU people will not remove YOUR necks, so that YOU will not walk haughtily; because it is a time of calamity. 4 In that day one will raise up concerning YOU people a proverbial saying and will certainly lament a lamentation, even a lamentation. One will have to say: “We have positively been despoiled! The very portion of my people he alters. How he removes it from me! To the unfaithful one he apportions out our own fields.” 5 Therefore you will come to have no one casting out the cord, by lot, in the congregation of Jehovah. 6 Do not YOU people let words drop. They let words drop. They will not let words drop concerning these things. Humiliations will not move away.

7 “‘Is it being said, O house of Jacob: “Has the spirit of Jehovah become discontented, or are these his dealings?” Do not my own words do good in the case of the one walking uprightly?

8 “‘And yesterday my own people proceeded to rise up as an outright enemy. From the front of a garment YOU men strip off the majestic ornament, from the ones passing by confidently, like those returning from war. 9 The women of my people YOU drive out from the house in which a woman has exquisite delight. From off her children YOU take my splendor, to time indefinite. 10 Get up and go, because this is not a resting-place. Because of the fact that she has become unclean, there is a wrecking; and the wrecking work is painful. 11 If a man, walking by wind and falsehood, has told the lie: “I shall let words drop to you concerning wine and concerning intoxicating liquor,” he also will certainly become the one letting words drop for this people.

12 “‘I shall positively gather Jacob, all of you; I shall without fail collect the remaining ones of Israel together. In unity I shall set them, like a flock in the pen, like a drove in the midst of its pasture; they will be noisy with men.’

13 “The one making a breakthrough will certainly come up before them: they will actually break through. And they will pass through a gate, and they will go out by it. And their king will pass through before them, with Jehovah at the head of them.”

Habakkuk

2 At my guard post I will keep standing, and I will keep myself stationed upon the bulwark; and I shall keep watch, to see what he will speak by me and what I shall reply at the reproof of me.

2 And Jehovah proceeded to answer me and to say: “Write down the vision, and set it out plainly upon tablets, in order that the one reading aloud from it may do so fluently. 3 For the vision is yet for the appointed time, and it keeps panting on to the end, and it will not tell a lie. Even if it should delay, keep in expectation of it; for it will without fail come true. It will not be late.

4 “Look! His soul has been swelled up; it has not been upright within him. But as for the righteous one, by his faithfulness he will keep living. 5 And, indeed, because the wine is dealing treacherously, an able-bodied man is self-assuming; and he will not reach his goal, he who has made his soul spacious just like She′ol, and who is like death and cannot be satisfied. And he keeps gathering to himself all the nations and collecting together to himself all the peoples. 6 Will not these very ones, all of them, lift up against him a proverbial saying and an alluding remark, insinuations at him? And one will say,

“‘Woe to him who is multiplying what is not his own—O how long!—and who is making debt heavy against himself! 7 Will not those claiming interest of you rise up suddenly, and those wake up who are violently shaking you, and you certainly become to them something to pillage? 8 Because you yourself despoiled many nations, all the remaining ones of the peoples will despoil you, because of the shedding of blood of mankind and the violence to the earth, the town and all those dwelling in it.

9 “‘Woe to the one that is making evil gain for his house, in order to set his nest on the height, so as to be delivered from the grasp of what is calamitous! 10 You have counseled something shameful to your house, the cutting off of many peoples; and your soul is sinning. 11 For out of the wall a stone itself will cry out plaintively, and from the woodwork a rafter itself will answer it.

12 “‘Woe to the one that is building a city by bloodshed, and that has solidly established a town by unrighteousness! 13 Look! Is it not from Jehovah of armies that peoples will toil on only for the fire, and that national groups will tire themselves out merely for nothing? 14 For the earth will be filled with the knowing of the glory of Jehovah as the waters themselves cover over the sea.

15 “‘Woe to the one giving his companions something to drink, attaching to it your rage and anger, in order to make them drunk, for the purpose of looking upon their parts of shame. 16 You will certainly be satiated with dishonor instead of glory. Drink also, you yourself, and be considered uncircumcised. The cup of the right hand of Jehovah will come around to you, and there will be disgrace upon your glory; 17 because the violence done to Leb′a·non is what will cover you, and the rapacity upon the beasts that terrifies them, because of the shedding of blood of mankind and the violence done to the earth, the town and all those dwelling in it. 18 Of what benefit has a carved image been, when the former of it has carved it, a molten statue, and an instructor in falsehood? when the former of its form has trusted in it, to the extent of making valueless gods that are speechless?

19 “‘Woe to the one saying to the piece of wood: “O do awake!” to a dumb stone: “O wake up! It itself will give instruction”! Look! It is sheathed in gold and silver, and there is no breath at all in the midst of it. 20 But Jehovah is in his holy temple. Keep silence before him, all the earth!’”

Zephaniah

2 Gather yourselves together, yes, do the gathering, O nation not paling in shame. 2 Before the statute gives birth to anything, before the day has passed by just like chaff, before there comes upon YOU people the burning anger of Jehovah, before there comes upon YOU the day of Jehovah’s anger, 3 seek Jehovah, all YOU meek ones of the earth, who have practiced His own judicial decision. Seek righteousness, seek meekness. Probably YOU may be concealed in the day of Jehovah’s anger. 4 For, as regards Ga′za, an abandoned city is what she will become; and Ash′ke·lon is to be a desolate waste. As regards Ash′dod, at high noon they will drive her out; and as regards Ek′ron, she will be uprooted.

5 “Woe to those inhabiting the region of the sea, the nation of Cher′e·thites! The word of Jehovah is against YOU people. O Ca′naan, the land of the Phi·lis′tines, I will also destroy you, so that there will be no inhabitant. 6 And the region of the sea must become pasture grounds, with wells for shepherds and stone pens for sheep. 7 And it must become a region for the remaining ones of the house of Judah. Upon them they will feed. In the houses of Ash′ke·lon, in the evening, they will lie stretched out. For Jehovah their God will turn his attention to them and certainly gather back the captive ones of them.”

8 “I have heard the reproach by Mo′ab and the abusive words of the sons of Am′mon, with which they have reproached my people and kept putting on great airs against their territory. 9 Therefore, as I am alive,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, the God of Israel, “Mo′ab herself will become just like Sod′om, and the sons of Am′mon like Go·mor′rah, a place possessed by nettles, and a salt pit, and a desolate waste, even to time indefinite. The remaining ones of my people will plunder them, and the remnant of my own nation will take possession of them. 10 This is what they will have instead of their pride, because they reproached and kept putting on great airs against the people of Jehovah of armies. 11 Jehovah will be fear-inspiring against them; for he will certainly emaciate all the gods of the earth, and people will bow down to him, each one from his place, all the islands of the nations.

12 “YOU also, YOU E·thi·o′pi·ans, YOU yourselves will be people slain by my sword.

13 “And he will stretch out his hand toward the north, and he will destroy As·syr′i·a. And he will make Nin′e·veh a desolate waste, a waterless region like the wilderness. 14 And in the midst of her, droves will certainly lie stretched out, all the wild animals of a nation. Both pelican and porcupine will spend the night right among her pillar capitals. A voice will keep singing in the window. There will be devastation at the threshold; for he will certainly lay bare the very wainscoting. 15 This is the exultant city that was sitting in security, that was saying in her heart, ‘I am, and there is nobody else.’ O how she has become an object of astonishment, a place for the wild animals to lie stretched out! Everyone passing along by her will whistle; he will wag his hand.”

Zechariah

2 And I proceeded to raise my eyes and see; and, look! there was a man, and in his hand a measuring rope. 2 So I said: “Where are you going?”

In turn he said to me: “To measure Jerusalem, in order to see what her breadth amounts to and what her length amounts to.”

3 And, look! the angel who was speaking with me was going forth, and there was another angel going forth to meet him. 4 Then he said to him: “Run, speak to the young man over there, saying, ‘“As open rural country Jerusalem will be inhabited, because of the multitude of men and domestic animals in the midst of her. 5 And I myself shall become to her,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “a wall of fire all around, and a glory is what I shall become in the midst of her.”’”

6 “Hey there! Hey there! Flee, then, YOU people, from the land of the north,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

“For in the direction of the four winds of the heavens I have spread YOU people abroad,” is the utterance of Jehovah.

7 “Hey there, Zion! Make your escape, you who are dwelling with the daughter of Babylon. 8 For this is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘Following after the glory he has sent me to the nations that were despoiling YOU people; for he that is touching YOU is touching my eyeball. 9 For here I am waving my hand against them, and they will have to become spoil to their slaves.’ And YOU people will certainly know that Jehovah of armies himself has sent me.

10 “Cry out loudly and rejoice, O daughter of Zion; for here I am coming, and I will reside in the midst of you,” is the utterance of Jehovah. 11 “And many nations will certainly become joined to Jehovah in that day, and they will actually become my people; and I will reside in the midst of you.” And you will have to know that Jehovah of armies himself has sent me to you. 12 And Jehovah will certainly take possession of Judah as his portion upon the holy ground, and he must yet choose Jerusalem. 13 Keep silence, all flesh, before Jehovah, for he has aroused himself from his holy dwelling.

Zechariah

3 And he proceeded to show me Joshua the high priest standing before the angel of Jehovah, and Satan standing at his right hand in order to resist him. 2 Then the angel of Jehovah said to Satan: “Jehovah rebuke you, O Satan, yes, Jehovah rebuke you, he who is choosing Jerusalem! Is this one not a log snatched out of the fire?”

3 Now as for Joshua, he happened to be clothed in befouled garments and standing before the angel. 4 Then he answered and said to those standing before him: “Remove the befouled garments from upon him.” And he went on to say to him: “See, I have caused your error to pass away from upon you, and there is a clothing of you with robes of state.”

5 At that I said: “Let them put a clean turban upon his head.” And they proceeded to put the clean turban upon his head and to clothe him with garments; and the angel of Jehovah was standing by. 6 And the angel of Jehovah began to bear witness to Joshua, saying: 7 “This is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘If it is in my ways that you will walk, and if it is my obligation that you will keep, then also it will be you that will judge my house and also keep my courtyards; and I shall certainly give you free access among these who are standing by.’

8 “‘Hear, please, O Joshua the high priest, you and your companions who are sitting before you, for they are men serving as portents; for here I am bringing in my servant Sprout! 9 For, look! the stone that I have put before Joshua! Upon the one stone there are seven eyes. Here I am engraving its engraving,’ is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, ‘and I will take away the error of that land in one day.’

10 “‘In that day,’ is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, ‘YOU will call, each one to the other, while under the vine and while under the fig tree.’”

Zechariah

9 A pronouncement:

“The word of Jehovah is against the land of Ha′drach, and Damascus is where it rests; for Jehovah has an eye on earthling man and on all the tribes of Israel. 2 And Ha′math itself will also border upon her; Tyre and Si′don, for she is very wise. 3 And Tyre proceeded to build a rampart for herself, and to pile up silver like dust and gold like the mire of the streets. 4 Look! Jehovah himself will dispossess her, and into the sea he will certainly strike down her military force; and in the fire she herself will be devoured. 5 Ash′ke·lon will see and get afraid; and as for Ga′za, she will also feel very severe pains; Ek′ron also, because her looked-for hope will have to experience shame. And a king will certainly perish from Ga′za, and Ash′ke·lon herself will not be inhabited. 6 And an illegitimate son will actually seat himself in Ash′dod, and I shall certainly cut off the pride of the Phi·lis′tine. 7 And I will remove his bloodstained things from his mouth and his disgusting things from between his teeth, and he himself also will certainly be left remaining for our God; and he must become like a sheik in Judah, and Ek′ron like the Jeb′u·site. 8 And I will encamp as an outpost for my house, so that there will be no one passing through and no one returning; and there will no more pass through them a taskmaster, for now I have seen it with my eyes.

9 “Be very joyful, O daughter of Zion. Shout in triumph, O daughter of Jerusalem. Look! Your king himself comes to you. He is righteous, yes, saved; humble, and riding upon an ass, even upon a full-grown animal the son of a she-ass. 10 And I shall certainly cut off the war chariot from E′phra·im and the horse from Jerusalem. And the battle bow must be cut off. And he will actually speak peace to the nations; and his rulership will be from sea to sea and from the River to the ends of the earth.

11 “Also, you, O woman, by the blood of your covenant I will send your prisoners out of the pit in which there is no water.

12 “Return to the stronghold, YOU prisoners of the hope.

“Also, today I am telling you, ‘I shall repay to you, O woman, a double portion. 13 For I will tread as my bow Judah. The bow I will fill with E′phra·im, and I will awaken your sons, O Zion, against your sons, O Greece, and I will make you as the sword of a mighty man.’ 14 And over them Jehovah himself will be seen, and his arrow will certainly go forth just like lightning. And on the horn the Sovereign Lord Jehovah himself will blow, and he will certainly go with the windstorms of the south. 15 Jehovah of armies himself will defend them, and they will actually devour and subdue the slingstones. And they will certainly drink—be boisterous—as if there were wine; and they will actually become filled like the bowl, like the corners of the altar.

16 “And Jehovah their God will certainly save them in that day like the flock of his people; for they will be as the stones of a diadem glittering over his soil. 17 For O how great his goodness is, and how great his handsomeness is! Grain is what will make the young men thrive, and new wine the virgins.”

Zechariah

13 “In that day there will come to be a well opened to the house of David and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem for sin and for an abhorrent thing.

2 “And it must occur in that day,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies, “that I shall cut off the names of the idols out of the land, and they will no more be remembered; and also the prophets and the spirit of uncleanness I shall cause to pass out of the land. 3 And it must occur that in case a man should prophesy anymore, his father and his mother, the ones who caused his birth, must also say to him, ‘You will not live, because falsehood is what you have spoken in the name of Jehovah.’ And his father and his mother, the ones who caused his birth, must pierce him through because of his prophesying.

4 “And it must occur in that day that the prophets will become ashamed, each one of his vision when he prophesies; and they will not wear an official garment of hair for the purpose of deceiving. 5 And he will certainly say, ‘I am no prophet. I am a man cultivating the soil, because an earthling man himself acquired me from my youth on.’ 6 And one must say to him, ‘What are these wounds on your person between your hands?’ And he will have to say, ‘Those with which I was struck in the house of my intense lovers.’”

7 “O sword, awake against my shepherd, even against the able-bodied man who is my associate,” is the utterance of Jehovah of armies. “Strike the shepherd, and let those of the flock be scattered; and I shall certainly turn my hand back upon those who are insignificant.”

8 “And it must occur in all the land,” is the utterance of Jehovah, “that two parts in it are what will be cut off and expire; and as for the third part, it will be left remaining in it. 9 And I shall certainly bring the third part through the fire; and I shall actually refine them as in the refining of silver, and examine them as in the examining of gold. It, for its part, will call upon my name, and I, for my part, will answer it. I will say, ‘It is my people,’ and it, in its turn, will say, ‘Jehovah is my God.’”

Malachi

1 A pronouncement:

The word of Jehovah concerning Israel by means of Mal′a·chi:

2 “I have loved YOU people,” Jehovah has said.

And YOU have said: “In what way have you loved us?”

“Was not E′sau the brother of Jacob?” is the utterance of Jehovah. “But I loved Jacob, 3 and E′sau I have hated; and I finally made his mountains a desolated waste and his inheritance for the jackals of the wilderness.”

4 “Because E′dom keeps saying, ‘We have been shattered, but we shall return and build the devastated places,’ this is what Jehovah of armies has said, ‘They, for their part, will build; but I, for my part, shall tear down. And people will certainly call them “the territory of wickedness” and “the people whom Jehovah has denounced to time indefinite.” 5 And YOUR own eyes will see it, and YOU yourselves will say: “May Jehovah be magnified over the territory of Israel.”’”

6 “‘A son, for his part, honors a father; and a servant, his grand master. So if I am a father, where is the honor to me? And if I am a Grand Master, where is the fear of me?’ Jehovah of armies has said to YOU, O priests who are despising my name.

“‘And YOU have said: “In what way have we despised your name?”’

7 “‘By presenting upon my altar polluted bread.’

“‘And YOU have said: “In what way have we polluted you?”’

“‘By YOUR saying: “The table of Jehovah is something to be despised.” 8 And when YOU present a blind animal for sacrificing: “It is nothing bad.” And when YOU present a lame animal or a sick one: “It is nothing bad.”’”

“Bring it near, please, to your governor. Will he find pleasure in you, or will he receive you kindly?” Jehovah of armies has said.

9 “And now, please, soften the face of God, that he may show us favor. From YOUR hand this has occurred. Will he receive any of YOU men kindly?” Jehovah of armies has said.

10 “Who also is there among YOU that will shut the doors? And YOU men will not light my altar—for nothing. No delight do I have in YOU,” Jehovah of armies has said, “and in the gift offering from YOUR hand I take no pleasure.”

11 “For from the sun’s rising even to its setting my name will be great among the nations, and in every place sacrificial smoke will be made, a presentation will be made to my name, even a clean gift; because my name will be great among the nations,” Jehovah of armies has said.

12 “But YOU men are profaning me by YOUR saying, ‘The table of Jehovah is something polluted, and its fruit is something to be despised, its food.’ 13 And YOU have said, ‘Look! What a weariness!’ and YOU have caused a sniffing at it,” Jehovah of armies has said. “And YOU have brought something torn away, and the lame one, and the sick one; yes, YOU have brought it as a gift. Can I take pleasure in it at YOUR hand?” Jehovah has said.

14 “And cursed is the one acting cunningly when there exists in his drove a male animal, and he is making a vow and sacrificing a ruined one to Jehovah. For I am a great King,” Jehovah of armies has said, “and my name will be fear-inspiring among the nations.”

Malachi

3 “Look! I am sending my messenger, and he must clear up a way before me. And suddenly there will come to His temple the true Lord, whom YOU people are seeking, and the messenger of the covenant in whom YOU are delighting. Look! He will certainly come,” Jehovah of armies has said.

2 “But who will be putting up with the day of his coming, and who will be the one standing when he appears? For he will be like the fire of a refiner and like the lye of laundrymen. 3 And he must sit as a refiner and cleanser of silver and must cleanse the sons of Le′vi; and he must clarify them like gold and like silver, and they will certainly become to Jehovah people presenting a gift offering in righteousness. 4 And the gift offering of Judah and of Jerusalem will actually be gratifying to Jehovah, as in the days of long ago and as in the years of antiquity.

5 “And I will come near to YOU people for the judgment, and I will become a speedy witness against the sorcerers, and against the adulterers, and against those swearing falsely, and against those acting fraudulently with the wages of a wage worker, with the widow and with the fatherless boy, and those turning away the alien resident, while they have not feared me,” Jehovah of armies has said.

6 “For I am Jehovah; I have not changed. And YOU are sons of Jacob; YOU have not come to YOUR finish. 7 From the days of YOUR forefathers YOU have turned aside from my regulations and have not kept them. Return to me, and I will return to YOU,” Jehovah of armies has said.

And YOU have said: “In what way shall we return?”

8 “Will earthling man rob God? But YOU are robbing me.”

And YOU have said: “In what way have we robbed you?”

“In the tenth parts and in the contributions. 9 With the curse YOU are cursing me, and me YOU are robbing—the nation in its entirety. 10 Bring all the tenth parts into the storehouse, that there may come to be food in my house; and test me out, please, in this respect,” Jehovah of armies has said, “whether I shall not open to YOU people the floodgates of the heavens and actually empty out upon YOU a blessing until there is no more want.”

11 “And I will rebuke for YOU the devouring one, and it will not ruin for YOU the fruit of the ground, nor will the vine in the field prove fruitless for YOU,” Jehovah of armies has said.

12 “And all the nations will have to pronounce YOU happy, for YOU yourselves will become a land of delight,” Jehovah of armies has said.

13 “Strong have been YOUR words against me,” Jehovah has said.

And YOU have said: “What have we spoken with one another against you?”

14 “YOU have said, ‘It is of no value to serve God. And what profit is there in that we have kept the obligation to him, and that we have walked dejectedly on account of Jehovah of armies? 15 And at present we are pronouncing presumptuous people happy. Also, the doers of wickedness have been built up. Also, they have tested God out and keep getting away.’”

16 At that time those in fear of Jehovah spoke with one another, each one with his companion, and Jehovah kept paying attention and listening. And a book of remembrance began to be written up before him for those in fear of Jehovah and for those thinking upon his name.

17 “And they will certainly become mine,” Jehovah of armies has said, “at the day when I am producing a special property. And I will show compassion upon them, just as a man shows compassion upon his son who is serving him. 18 And YOU people will again certainly see the distinction between a righteous one and a wicked one, between one serving God and one who has not served him.”

Matthew

4 Then Jesus was led by the spirit up into the wilderness to be tempted by the Devil. 2 After he had fasted forty days and forty nights, then he felt hungry. 3 Also, the Tempter came and said to him: “If you are a son of God, tell these stones to become loaves of bread.” 4 But in reply he said: “It is written, ‘Man must live, not on bread alone, but on every utterance coming forth through Jehovah’s mouth.’”

5 Then the Devil took him along into the holy city, and he stationed him upon the battlement of the temple 6 and said to him: “If you are a son of God, hurl yourself down; for it is written, ‘He will give his angels a charge concerning you, and they will carry you on their hands, that you may at no time strike your foot against a stone.’” 7 Jesus said to him: “Again it is written, ‘You must not put Jehovah your God to the test.’”

8 Again the Devil took him along to an unusually high mountain, and showed him all the kingdoms of the world and their glory, 9 and he said to him: “All these things I will give you if you fall down and do an act of worship to me.” 10 Then Jesus said to him: “Go away, Satan! For it is written, ‘It is Jehovah your God you must worship, and it is to him alone you must render sacred service.’” 11 Then the Devil left him, and, look! angels came and began to minister to him.

12 Now when he heard that John had been arrested, he withdrew into Gal′i·lee. 13 Further, after leaving Naz′a·reth, he came and took up residence in Ca·per′na·um beside the sea in the districts of Zeb′u·lun and Naph′ta·li, 14 that there might be fulfilled what was spoken through Isaiah the prophet, saying: 15 “O land of Zeb′u·lun and land of Naph′ta·li, along the road of the sea, on the other side of the Jordan, Gal′i·lee of the nations! 16 the people sitting in darkness saw a great light, and as for those sitting in a region of deathly shadow, light rose upon them.” 17 From that time on Jesus commenced preaching and saying: “Repent, YOU people, for the kingdom of the heavens has drawn near.”

18 Walking alongside the sea of Gal′i·lee he saw two brothers, Simon who is called Peter and Andrew his brother, letting down a fishing net into the sea, for they were fishers. 19 And he said to them: “Come after me, and I will make YOU fishers of men.” 20 At once abandoning the nets, they followed him. 21 Going on also from there he saw two others who were brothers, James the son of Zeb′e·dee and John his brother, in the boat with Zeb′e·dee their father, mending their nets, and he called them. 22 At once leaving the boat and their father, they followed him.

23 Then he went around throughout the whole of Gal′i·lee, teaching in their synagogues and preaching the good news of the kingdom and curing every sort of disease and every sort of infirmity among the people. 24 And the report about him went out into all Syria; and they brought him all those faring badly, distressed with various diseases and torments, demon-possessed and epileptic and paralyzed persons, and he cured them. 25 Consequently great crowds followed him from Gal′i·lee and De·cap′o·lis and Jerusalem and Ju·de′a and from the other side of the Jordan.

Matthew

5 When he saw the crowds he went up into the mountain; and after he sat down his disciples came to him; 2 and he opened his mouth and began teaching them, saying:

3 “Happy are those conscious of their spiritual need, since the kingdom of the heavens belongs to them.

4 “Happy are those who mourn, since they will be comforted.

5 “Happy are the mild-tempered ones, since they will inherit the earth.

6 “Happy are those hungering and thirsting for righteousness, since they will be filled.

7 “Happy are the merciful, since they will be shown mercy.

8 “Happy are the pure in heart, since they will see God.

9 “Happy are the peaceable, since they will be called ‘sons of God.’

10 “Happy are those who have been persecuted for righteousness’ sake, since the kingdom of the heavens belongs to them.

11 “Happy are YOU when people reproach YOU and persecute YOU and lyingly say every sort of wicked thing against YOU for my sake. 12 Rejoice and leap for joy, since YOUR reward is great in the heavens; for in that way they persecuted the prophets prior to YOU.

13 “YOU are the salt of the earth; but if the salt loses its strength, how will its saltness be restored? It is no longer usable for anything but to be thrown outside to be trampled on by men.

14 “YOU are the light of the world. A city cannot be hid when situated upon a mountain. 15 People light a lamp and set it, not under the measuring basket, but upon the lampstand, and it shines upon all those in the house. 16 Likewise let YOUR light shine before men, that they may see YOUR fine works and give glory to YOUR Father who is in the heavens.

17 “Do not think I came to destroy the Law or the Prophets. I came, not to destroy, but to fulfill; 18 for truly I say to YOU that sooner would heaven and earth pass away than for one smallest letter or one particle of a letter to pass away from the Law by any means and not all things take place. 19 Whoever, therefore, breaks one of these least commandments and teaches mankind to that effect, he will be called ‘least’ in relation to the kingdom of the heavens. As for anyone who does them and teaches them, this one will be called ‘great’ in relation to the kingdom of the heavens. 20 For I say to YOU that if YOUR righteousness does not abound more than that of the scribes and Pharisees, YOU will by no means enter into the kingdom of the heavens.

21 “YOU heard that it was said to those of ancient times, ‘You must not murder; but whoever commits a murder will be accountable to the court of justice.’ 22 However, I say to YOU that everyone who continues wrathful with his brother will be accountable to the court of justice; but whoever addresses his brother with an unspeakable word of contempt will be accountable to the Supreme Court; whereas whoever says, ‘You despicable fool!’ will be liable to the fiery Ge·hen′na.

23 “If, then, you are bringing your gift to the altar and you there remember that your brother has something against you, 24 leave your gift there in front of the altar, and go away; first make your peace with your brother, and then, when you have come back, offer up your gift.

25 “Be about settling matters quickly with the one complaining against you at law, while you are with him on the way there, that somehow the complainant may not turn you over to the judge, and the judge to the court attendant, and you get thrown into prison. 26 I say to you for a fact, You will certainly not come out from there until you have paid over the last coin of very little value.

27 “YOU heard that it was said, ‘You must not commit adultery.’ 28 But I say to YOU that everyone that keeps on looking at a woman so as to have a passion for her has already committed adultery with her in his heart. 29 If, now, that right eye of yours is making you stumble, tear it out and throw it away from you. For it is more beneficial to you for one of your members to be lost to you than for your whole body to be pitched into Ge·hen′na. 30 Also, if your right hand is making you stumble, cut it off and throw it away from you. For it is more beneficial to you for one of your members to be lost than for your whole body to land in Ge·hen′na.

31 “Moreover it was said, ‘Whoever divorces his wife, let him give her a certificate of divorce.’ 32 However, I say to YOU that everyone divorcing his wife, except on account of fornication, makes her a subject for adultery, and whoever marries a divorced woman commits adultery.

33 “Again YOU heard that it was said to those of ancient times, ‘You must not swear without performing, but you must pay your vows to Jehovah.’ 34 However, I say to YOU: Do not swear at all, neither by heaven, because it is God’s throne; 35 nor by earth, because it is the footstool of his feet; nor by Jerusalem, because it is the city of the great King. 36 Nor by your head must you swear, because you cannot turn one hair white or black. 37 Just let YOUR word Yes mean Yes, YOUR No, No; for what is in excess of these is from the wicked one.

38 “YOU heard that it was said, ‘Eye for eye and tooth for tooth.’ 39 However, I say to YOU: Do not resist him that is wicked; but whoever slaps you on your right cheek, turn the other also to him. 40 And if a person wants to go to court with you and get possession of your inner garment, let your outer garment also go to him; 41 and if someone in authority impresses you into service for a mile, go with him two miles. 42 Give to the one asking you, and do not turn away from one that wants to borrow from you without interest.

43 “YOU heard that it was said, ‘You must love your neighbor and hate your enemy.’ 44 However, I say to YOU: Continue to love YOUR enemies and to pray for those persecuting YOU; 45 that YOU may prove yourselves sons of YOUR Father who is in the heavens, since he makes his sun rise upon wicked people and good and makes it rain upon righteous people and unrighteous. 46 For if YOU love those loving YOU, what reward do YOU have? Are not also the tax collectors doing the same thing? 47 And if YOU greet YOUR brothers only, what extraordinary thing are YOU doing? Are not also the people of the nations doing the same thing? 48 YOU must accordingly be perfect, as YOUR heavenly Father is perfect.

Matthew

19 Now when Jesus had finished these words, he departed from Gal′i·lee and came to the frontiers of Ju·de′a across the Jordan. 2 Also, great crowds followed him, and he cured them there.

3 And Pharisees came up to him, intent on tempting him and saying: “Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife on every sort of ground?” 4 In reply he said: “Did YOU not read that he who created them from the beginning made them male and female 5 and said, ‘For this reason a man will leave his father and his mother and will stick to his wife, and the two will be one flesh’? 6 So that they are no longer two, but one flesh. Therefore, what God has yoked together let no man put apart.” 7 They said to him: “Why, then, did Moses prescribe giving a certificate of dismissal and divorcing her?” 8 He said to them: “Moses, out of regard for YOUR hardheartedness, made the concession to YOU of divorcing YOUR wives, but such has not been the case from the beginning. 9 I say to YOU that whoever divorces his wife, except on the ground of fornication, and marries another commits adultery.”

10 The disciples said to him: “If such is the situation of a man with his wife, it is not advisable to marry.” 11 He said to them: “Not all men make room for the saying, but only those who have the gift. 12 For there are eunuchs that were born such from their mother’s womb, and there are eunuchs that were made eunuchs by men, and there are eunuchs that have made themselves eunuchs on account of the kingdom of the heavens. Let him that can make room for it make room for it.”

13 Then young children were brought to him, for him to put his hands upon them and offer prayer; but the disciples reprimanded them. 14 Jesus, however, said: “Let the young children alone, and stop hindering them from coming to me, for the kingdom of the heavens belongs to suchlike ones.” 15 And he put his hands upon them and went from there.

16 Now, look! a certain one came up to him and said: “Teacher, what good must I do in order to get everlasting life?” 17 He said to him: “Why do you ask me about what is good? One there is that is good. If, though, you want to enter into life, observe the commandments continually.” 18 He said to him: “Which ones?” Jesus said: “Why, You must not murder, You must not commit adultery, You must not steal, You must not bear false witness, 19 Honor your father and your mother, and, You must love your neighbor as yourself.” 20 The young man said to him: “I have kept all these; what yet am I lacking?” 21 Jesus said to him: “If you want to be perfect, go sell your belongings and give to the poor and you will have treasure in heaven, and come be my follower.” 22 When the young man heard this saying, he went away grieved, for he was holding many possessions. 23 But Jesus said to his disciples: “Truly I say to YOU that it will be a difficult thing for a rich man to get into the kingdom of the heavens. 24 Again I say to YOU, It is easier for a camel to get through a needle’s eye than for a rich man to get into the kingdom of God.”

25 When the disciples heard that, they expressed very great surprise, saying: “Who really can be saved?” 26 Looking them in the face, Jesus said to them: “With men this is impossible, but with God all things are possible.”

27 Then Peter said to him in reply: “Look! We have left all things and followed you; what actually will there be for us?” 28 Jesus said to them: “Truly I say to YOU, In the re-creation, when the Son of man sits down upon his glorious throne, YOU who have followed me will also yourselves sit upon twelve thrones, judging the twelve tribes of Israel. 29 And everyone that has left houses or brothers or sisters or father or mother or children or lands for the sake of my name will receive many times more and will inherit everlasting life.

30 “But many that are first will be last and the last first.

Matthew

20 “For the kingdom of the heavens is like a man, a householder, who went out early in the morning to hire workers for his vineyard. 2 When he had agreed with the workers for a de·nar′i·us a day, he sent them forth into his vineyard. 3 Going out also about the third hour, he saw others standing unemployed in the marketplace; 4 and to those he said, ‘YOU also, go into the vineyard, and whatever is just I will give YOU.’ 5 So off they went. Again he went out about the sixth and the ninth hour and did likewise. 6 Finally, about the eleventh hour he went out and found others standing, and he said to them, ‘Why have YOU been standing here all day unemployed?’ 7 They said to him, ‘Because nobody has hired us.’ He said to them, ‘YOU too go into the vineyard.’

8 “When it became evening, the master of the vineyard said to his man in charge, ‘Call the workers and pay them their wages, proceeding from the last to the first.’ 9 When the eleventh-hour men came, they each received a de·nar′i·us. 10 So, when the first came, they concluded they would receive more; but they also received pay at the rate of a de·nar′i·us. 11 On receiving it they began to murmur against the householder 12 and said, ‘These last put in one hour’s work; still you made them equal to us who bore the burden of the day and the burning heat!’ 13 But in reply to one of them he said, ‘Fellow, I do you no wrong. You agreed with me for a de·nar′i·us, did you not? 14 Take what is yours and go. I want to give to this last one the same as to you. 15 Is it not lawful for me to do what I want with my own things? Or is your eye wicked because I am good?’ 16 In this way the last ones will be first, and the first ones last.”

17 Being now about to go up to Jerusalem, Jesus took the twelve disciples off privately and said to them on the road: 18 “Look! We are going up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man will be delivered up to the chief priests and scribes, and they will condemn him to death, 19 and will deliver him up to men of the nations to make fun of and to scourge and to impale, and the third day he will be raised up.”

20 Then the mother of the sons of Zeb′e·dee approached him with her sons, doing obeisance and asking for something from him. 21 He said to her: “What do you want?” She said to him: “Give the word that these my two sons may sit down, one at your right hand and one at your left, in your kingdom.” 22 Jesus said in answer: “YOU men do not know what YOU are asking for. Can YOU drink the cup that I am about to drink?” They said to him: “We can.” 23 He said to them: “YOU will indeed drink my cup, but this sitting down at my right hand and at my left is not mine to give, but it belongs to those for whom it has been prepared by my Father.”

24 When the ten others heard of this, they became indignant at the two brothers. 25 But Jesus, calling them to him, said: “YOU know that the rulers of the nations lord it over them and the great men wield authority over them. 26 This is not the way among YOU; but whoever wants to become great among YOU must be YOUR minister, 27 and whoever wants to be first among YOU must be YOUR slave. 28 Just as the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his soul a ransom in exchange for many.”

29 Now as they were going out of Jer′i·cho a great crowd followed him. 30 And, look! two blind men sitting beside the road, when they heard that Jesus was passing by, cried out, saying: “Lord, have mercy on us, Son of David!” 31 But the crowd sternly told them to keep silent; yet they cried all the louder, saying: “Lord, have mercy on us, Son of David!” 32 So Jesus stopped, called them and said: “What do YOU want me to do for YOU?” 33 They said to him: “Lord, let our eyes be opened.” 34 Moved with pity, Jesus touched their eyes, and immediately they received sight, and they followed him.

Matthew

22 In further reply Jesus again spoke to them with illustrations, saying: 2 “The kingdom of the heavens has become like a man, a king, that made a marriage feast for his son. 3 And he sent forth his slaves to call those invited to the marriage feast, but they were unwilling to come. 4 Again he sent forth other slaves, saying, ‘Tell those invited: “Look! I have prepared my dinner, my bulls and fattened animals are slaughtered, and all things are ready. Come to the marriage feast.”’ 5 But unconcerned they went off, one to his own field, another to his commercial business; 6 but the rest, laying hold of his slaves, treated them insolently and killed them.

7 “But the king grew wrathful, and sent his armies and destroyed those murderers and burned their city. 8 Then he said to his slaves, ‘The marriage feast indeed is ready, but those invited were not worthy. 9 Therefore go to the roads leading out of the city, and anyone YOU find invite to the marriage feast.’ 10 Accordingly those slaves went out to the roads and gathered together all they found, both wicked and good; and the room for the wedding ceremonies was filled with those reclining at the table.

11 “When the king came in to inspect the guests he caught sight there of a man not clothed with a marriage garment. 12 So he said to him, ‘Fellow, how did you get in here not having on a marriage garment?’ He was rendered speechless. 13 Then the king said to his servants, ‘Bind him hand and foot and throw him out into the darkness outside. There is where his weeping and the gnashing of his teeth will be.’

14 “For there are many invited, but few chosen.”

15 Then the Pharisees went their way and took counsel together in order to trap him in his speech. 16 So they dispatched to him their disciples, together with party followers of Herod, saying: “Teacher, we know you are truthful and teach the way of God in truth, and you do not care for anybody, for you do not look upon men’s outward appearance. 17 Tell us, therefore, What do you think? Is it lawful to pay head tax to Caesar or not?” 18 But Jesus, knowing their wickedness, said: “Why do YOU put me to the test, hypocrites? 19 Show me the head tax coin.” They brought him a de·nar′i·us. 20 And he said to them: “Whose image and inscription is this?” 21 They said: “Caesar’s.” Then he said to them: “Pay back, therefore, Caesar’s things to Caesar, but God’s things to God.” 22 Well, when they heard that, they marveled, and leaving him they went off.

23 On that day Sadducees, who say there is no resurrection, came up to him and asked him: 24 “Teacher, Moses said, ‘If any man dies without having children, his brother must take his wife in marriage and raise up offspring for his brother.’ 25 Now there were seven brothers with us; and the first married and deceased, and, not having offspring, he left his wife for his brother. 26 It went the same way also with the second and the third, until through all seven. 27 Last of all the woman died. 28 Consequently, in the resurrection, to which of the seven will she be wife? For they all got her.”

29 In reply Jesus said to them: “YOU are mistaken, because YOU know neither the Scriptures nor the power of God; 30 for in the resurrection neither do men marry nor are women given in marriage, but are as angels in heaven. 31 As regards the resurrection of the dead, did YOU not read what was spoken to YOU by God, saying, 32 ‘I am the God of Abraham and the God of Isaac and the God of Jacob’? He is the God, not of the dead, but of the living.” 33 On hearing that, the crowds were astounded at his teaching.

34 After the Pharisees heard that he had put the Sadducees to silence, they came together in one group. 35 And one of them, versed in the Law, asked, testing him: 36 “Teacher, which is the greatest commandment in the Law?” 37 He said to him: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind.’ 38 This is the greatest and first commandment. 39 The second, like it, is this, ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ 40 On these two commandments the whole Law hangs, and the Prophets.”

41 Now while the Pharisees were gathered together Jesus asked them: 42 “What do YOU think about the Christ? Whose son is he?” They said to him: “David’s.” 43 He said to them: “How, then, is it that David by inspiration calls him ‘Lord,’ saying, 44 ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies beneath your feet”’? 45 If, therefore, David calls him ‘Lord,’ how is he his son?” 46 And nobody was able to say a word in reply to him, nor did anyone dare from that day on to question him any further.

Matthew

27 When it had become morning, all the chief priests and the older men of the people held a consultation against Jesus so as to put him to death. 2 And, after binding him, they led him off and handed him over to Pilate the governor.

3 Then Judas, who betrayed him, seeing he had been condemned, felt remorse and turned the thirty silver pieces back to the chief priests and older men, 4 saying: “I sinned when I betrayed righteous blood.” They said: “What is that to us? You must see to that!” 5 So he threw the silver pieces into the temple and withdrew, and went off and hanged himself. 6 But the chief priests took the silver pieces and said: “It is not lawful to drop them into the sacred treasury, because they are the price of blood.” 7 After consulting together, they bought with them the potter’s field to bury strangers. 8 Therefore that field has been called “Field of Blood” to this very day. 9 Then what was spoken through Jeremiah the prophet was fulfilled, saying: “And they took the thirty silver pieces, the price upon the man that was priced, the one on whom some of the sons of Israel set a price, 10 and they gave them for the potter’s field, according to what Jehovah had commanded me.”

11 Jesus now stood before the governor; and the governor put the question to him: “Are you the king of the Jews?” Jesus replied: “You yourself say it.” 12 But, while he was being accused by the chief priests and older men, he made no answer. 13 Then Pilate said to him: “Do you not hear how many things they are testifying against you?” 14 Yet he did not answer him, no, not a word, so that the governor wondered very much.

15 Now from festival to festival it was the custom of the governor to release a prisoner to the crowd, the one they wanted. 16 Just at that time they were holding a notorious prisoner called Bar·ab′bas. 17 Hence when they were gathered together Pilate said to them: “Which one do YOU want me to release to YOU, Bar·ab′bas or Jesus the so-called Christ?” 18 For he was aware that out of envy they had handed him over. 19 Moreover, while he was sitting on the judgment seat, his wife sent out to him, saying: “Have nothing to do with that righteous man, for I suffered a lot today in a dream because of him.” 20 But the chief priests and the older men persuaded the crowds to ask for Bar·ab′bas, but to have Jesus destroyed. 21 Now in responding the governor said to them: “Which of the two do YOU want me to release to YOU?” They said: “Bar·ab′bas.” 22 Pilate said to them: “What, then, shall I do with Jesus the so-called Christ?” They all said: “Let him be impaled!” 23 He said: “Why, what bad thing did he do?” Still they kept crying out all the more: “Let him be impaled!”

24 Seeing that it did no good but, rather, an uproar was arising, Pilate took water and washed his hands before the crowd, saying: “I am innocent of the blood of this man. YOU yourselves must see to it.” 25 At that all the people said in answer: “His blood come upon us and upon our children.” 26 Then he released Bar·ab′bas to them, but he had Jesus whipped and handed him over to be impaled.

27 Then the soldiers of the governor took Jesus into the governor’s palace and gathered the whole body of troops together to him. 28 And disrobing him, they draped him with a scarlet cloak, 29 and they braided a crown out of thorns and put it on his head and a reed in his right hand. And, kneeling before him, they made fun of him, saying: “Good day, you King of the Jews!” 30 And they spit upon him and took the reed and began hitting him upon his head. 31 Finally, when they had made fun of him, they took the cloak off and put his outer garments upon him and led him off for impaling.

32 As they were going out they found a native of Cy·re′ne named Simon. This man they impressed into service to lift up his torture stake. 33 And when they came to a place called Gol′go·tha, that is to say, Skull Place, 34 they gave him wine mixed with gall to drink; but, after tasting it, he refused to drink. 35 When they had impaled him they distributed his outer garments by casting lots, 36 and, as they sat, they watched over him there. 37 Also, they posted above his head the charge against him, in writing: “This is Jesus the King of the Jews.”

38 Then two robbers were impaled with him, one on his right and one on his left. 39 So the passersby began speaking abusively of him, wagging their heads 40 and saying: “O you would-be thrower-down of the temple and builder of it in three days, save yourself! If you are a son of God, come down off the torture stake!” 41 In like manner also the chief priests with the scribes and older men began making fun of him and saying: 42 “Others he saved; himself he cannot save! He is King of Israel; let him now come down off the torture stake and we will believe on him. 43 He has put his trust in God; let Him now rescue him if He wants him, for he said, ‘I am God’s Son.’” 44 In the same way even the robbers that were impaled together with him began reproaching him.

45 From the sixth hour on a darkness fell over all the land, until the ninth hour. 46 About the ninth hour Jesus called out with a loud voice, saying: “E′li, E′li, la′ma sa·bach·tha′ni?” that is, “My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?” 47 At hearing this, some of those standing there began to say: “This man is calling E·li′jah.” 48 And immediately one of them ran and took a sponge and soaked it with sour wine and put it on a reed and went giving him a drink. 49 But the rest of them said: “Let him be! Let us see whether E·li′jah comes to save him.” [[Another man took a spear and pierced his side, and blood and water came out.]] 50 Again Jesus cried out with a loud voice, and yielded up his spirit.

51 And, look! the curtain of the sanctuary was rent in two, from top to bottom, and the earth quaked, and the rock-masses were split. 52 And the memorial tombs were opened and many bodies of the holy ones that had fallen asleep were raised up, 53 (and persons, coming out from among the memorial tombs after his being raised up, entered into the holy city,) and they became visible to many people. 54 But the army officer and those with him watching over Jesus, when they saw the earthquake and the things happening, grew very much afraid, saying: “Certainly this was God’s Son.”

55 Moreover, many women were there viewing from a distance, who had accompanied Jesus from Gal′i·lee to minister to him; 56 among whom was Mary Mag′da·lene, also Mary the mother of James and Jo′ses, and the mother of the sons of Zeb′e·dee.

57 Now as it was late in the afternoon, there came a rich man of Ar·i·ma·the′a, named Joseph, who had also himself become a disciple of Jesus. 58 This man went up to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus. Then Pilate commanded it to be given over. 59 And Joseph took the body, wrapped it up in clean fine linen, 60 and laid it in his new memorial tomb, which he had quarried in the rock-mass. And, after rolling a big stone to the door of the memorial tomb, he left. 61 But Mary Mag′da·lene and the other Mary continued there, sitting before the grave.

62 The next day, which was after the Preparation, the chief priests and the Pharisees gathered together before Pilate, 63 saying: “Sir, we have called to mind that that impostor said while yet alive, ‘After three days I am to be raised up.’ 64 Therefore command the grave to be made secure until the third day, that his disciples may never come and steal him and say to the people, ‘He was raised up from the dead!’ and this last imposture will be worse than the first.” 65 Pilate said to them: “YOU have a guard. Go make it as secure as YOU know how.” 66 So they went and made the grave secure by sealing the stone and having the guard.

Mark

2 However, after some days he again entered into Ca·per′na·um and he was reported to be at home. 2 Consequently many gathered, so much so that there was no more room, not even about the door, and he began to speak the word to them. 3 And men came bringing him a paralytic carried by four. 4 But not being able to bring him right to Jesus on account of the crowd, they removed the roof over where he was, and having dug an opening they lowered the cot on which the paralytic was lying. 5 And when Jesus saw their faith he said to the paralytic: “Child, your sins are forgiven.” 6 Now there were some of the scribes there, sitting and reasoning in their hearts: 7 “Why is this man talking in this manner? He is blaspheming. Who can forgive sins except one, God?” 8 But Jesus, having discerned immediately by his spirit that they were reasoning that way in themselves, said to them: “Why are YOU reasoning these things in YOUR hearts? 9 Which is easier, to say to the paralytic, ‘Your sins are forgiven,’ or to say, ‘Get up and pick up your cot and walk’? 10 But in order for YOU men to know that the Son of man has authority to forgive sins upon the earth,”—he said to the paralytic: 11 “I say to you, Get up, pick up your cot, and go to your home.” 12 At that he did get up, and immediately picked up his cot and walked out in front of them all, so that they were all simply carried away, and they glorified God, saying: “We never saw the like of it.”

13 Again he went out beside the sea; and all the crowd kept coming to him, and he began to teach them. 14 But as he was passing along, he caught sight of Le′vi the son of Al·phae′us sitting at the tax office, and he said to him: “Be my follower.” And rising up he followed him. 15 Later he happened to be reclining at the table in his house, and many tax collectors and sinners were reclining with Jesus and his disciples, for there were many of them and they began following him. 16 But the scribes of the Pharisees, when they saw he was eating with the sinners and tax collectors, began saying to his disciples: “Does he eat with the tax collectors and sinners?” 17 Upon hearing this Jesus said to them: “Those who are strong do not need a physician, but those who are ill do. I came to call, not righteous people, but sinners.”

18 Now John’s disciples and the Pharisees practiced fasting. So they came and said to him: “Why is it the disciples of John and the disciples of the Pharisees practice fasting, but your disciples do not practice fasting?” 19 And Jesus said to them: “While the bridegroom is with them the friends of the bridegroom cannot fast, can they? As long as they have the bridegroom with them they cannot fast. 20 But days will come when the bridegroom will be taken away from them, and then they will fast in that day. 21 Nobody sews a patch of unshrunk cloth upon an old outer garment; if he does, its full strength pulls from it, the new from the old, and the tear becomes worse. 22 Also, nobody puts new wine into old wineskins; if he does, the wine bursts the skins, and the wine is lost as well as the skins. But people put new wine into new wineskins.”

23 Now it happened that he was proceeding through the grainfields on the sabbath, and his disciples started to make their way plucking the heads of grain. 24 So the Pharisees went saying to him: “Look here! Why are they doing on the sabbath what is not lawful?” 25 But he said to them: “Have YOU never once read what David did when he fell in need and got hungry, he and the men with him? 26 How he entered into the house of God, in the account about A·bi′a·thar the chief priest, and ate the loaves of presentation, which it is not lawful for anybody to eat except the priests, and he gave some also to the men who were with him?” 27 So he went on to say to them: “The sabbath came into existence for the sake of man, and not man for the sake of the sabbath; 28 hence the Son of man is Lord even of the sabbath.”

Mark

3 Once again he entered into a synagogue, and a man was there with a dried-up hand. 2 So they were watching him closely to see whether he would cure the man on the sabbath, in order that they might accuse him. 3 And he said to the man with the withered hand: “Get up and come to the center.” 4 Next he said to them: “Is it lawful on the sabbath to do a good deed or to do a bad deed, to save or to kill a soul?” But they kept silent. 5 And after looking around upon them with indignation, being thoroughly grieved at the insensibility of their hearts, he said to the man: “Stretch out your hand.” And he stretched it out, and his hand was restored. 6 At that the Pharisees went out and immediately began holding council with the party followers of Herod against him, in order to destroy him.

7 But Jesus with his disciples withdrew to the sea; and a great multitude from Gal′i·lee and from Ju·de′a followed him. 8 Even from Jerusalem and from Id·u·me′a and from across the Jordan and around Tyre and Si′don, a great multitude, on hearing of how many things he was doing, came to him. 9 And he told his disciples to have a little boat continually at his service so that the crowd might not press upon him. 10 For he cured many, with the result that all those who had grievous diseases were falling upon him to touch him. 11 Even the unclean spirits, whenever they would behold him, would prostrate themselves before him and cry out, saying: “You are the Son of God.” 12 But many times he sternly charged them not to make him known.

13 And he ascended a mountain and summoned those he wanted, and they went off to him. 14 And he formed a group of twelve, whom he also named “apostles,” that they might continue with him and that he might send them out to preach 15 and to have authority to expel the demons.

16 And the group of twelve that he formed were Simon, to whom he also gave the surname Peter, 17 and James the son of Zeb′e·dee and John the brother of James (he also gave these the surname Bo·a·ner′ges, which means Sons of Thunder), 18 and Andrew and Philip and Bar·thol′o·mew and Matthew and Thomas and James the son of Al·phae′us and Thad·dae′us and Simon the Ca·na·nae′an 19 and Judas Is·car′i·ot, who later betrayed him.

And he went into a house. 20 Once more the crowd gathered, so that they were not able even to eat a meal. 21 But when his relatives heard about it, they went out to lay hold of him, for they were saying: “He has gone out of his mind.” 22 Also, the scribes that came down from Jerusalem were saying: “He has Be·el′ze·bub, and he expels the demons by means of the ruler of the demons.” 23 So, after calling them to him, he began to say to them with illustrations: “How can Satan expel Satan? 24 Why, if a kingdom becomes divided against itself, that kingdom cannot stand; 25 and if a house becomes divided against itself, that house will not be able to stand. 26 Also, if Satan has risen up against himself and become divided, he cannot stand, but is coming to an end. 27 In fact, no one that has got into the house of a strong man is able to plunder his movable goods unless first he binds the strong man, and then he will plunder his house. 28 Truly I say to YOU that all things will be forgiven the sons of men, no matter what sins and blasphemies they blasphemously commit. 29 However, whoever blasphemes against the holy spirit has no forgiveness forever, but is guilty of everlasting sin.” 30 This, because they were saying: “He has an unclean spirit.”

31 Now his mother and his brothers came, and, as they were standing on the outside, they sent in to him to call him. 32 As it was, a crowd was sitting around him, so they said to him: “Look! Your mother and your brothers outside are seeking you.” 33 But in reply he said to them: “Who are my mother and my brothers?” 34 And having looked about upon those sitting around him in a circle, he said: “See, my mother and my brothers! 35 Whoever does the will of God, this one is my brother and sister and mother.”

Mark

5 Well, they got to the other side of the sea into the country of the Ger′a·senes. 2 And immediately after he got out of the boat a man under the power of an unclean spirit met him from among the memorial tombs. 3 He had his haunt among the tombs; and up to that time absolutely nobody was able to bind him fast even with a chain, 4 because he had oftentimes been bound with fetters and chains, but the chains were snapped apart by him and the fetters were actually smashed; and nobody had the strength to subdue him. 5 And continually, night and day, he was crying out in the tombs and in the mountains and slashing himself with stones. 6 But on catching sight of Jesus from a distance he ran and did obeisance to him, 7 and, when he had cried out with a loud voice, he said: “What have I to do with you, Jesus, Son of the Most High God? I put you under oath by God not to torment me.” 8 For he had been telling it: “Come out of the man, you unclean spirit.” 9 But he began to ask him: “What is your name?” And he said to him: “My name is Legion, because there are many of us.” 10 And he entreated him many times not to send the spirits out of the country.

11 Now a great herd of swine was there at the mountain feeding. 12 So they entreated him, saying: “Send us into the swine, that we may enter into them.” 13 And he permitted them. With that the unclean spirits came out and entered into the swine; and the herd rushed over the precipice into the sea, about two thousand of them, and they drowned one after another in the sea. 14 But the herders of them fled and reported it in the city and in the countryside; and people came to see what it was that had happened. 15 So they came to Jesus, and they beheld the demon-possessed man sitting clothed and in his sound mind, this man that had had the legion; and they grew fearful. 16 Also, those who had seen it related to them how this had happened to the demon-possessed man and about the swine. 17 And so they started to entreat him to go away from their districts.

18 Now as he was boarding the boat, the man that had been demon-possessed began entreating him that he might continue with him. 19 However, he did not let him, but said to him: “Go home to your relatives, and report to them all the things Jehovah has done for you and the mercy he had on you.” 20 And he went away and started to proclaim in the De·cap′o·lis all the things Jesus did for him, and all the people began to wonder.

21 After Jesus had crossed back again in the boat to the opposite shore a great crowd gathered together to him; and he was beside the sea. 22 Now one of the presiding officers of the synagogue, Ja′i·rus by name, came and, on catching sight of him, he fell at his feet 23 and entreated him many times, saying: “My little daughter is in an extreme condition. Would you please come and put your hands upon her that she may get well and live.” 24 At that he went off with him. And a great crowd was following him and pressing against him.

25 Now there was a woman subject to a flow of blood twelve years, 26 and she had been put to many pains by many physicians and had spent all her resources and had not been benefited but, rather, had got worse. 27 When she heard the things about Jesus, she came behind in the crowd and touched his outer garment; 28 for she kept saying: “If I touch just his outer garments I shall get well.” 29 And immediately her fountain of blood dried up, and she sensed in her body that she had been healed of the grievous sickness.

30 Immediately, also, Jesus recognized in himself that power had gone out of him, and he turned about in the crowd and began to say: “Who touched my outer garments?” 31 But his disciples began to say to him: “You see the crowd pressing in upon you, and do you say, ‘Who touched me?’” 32 However, he was looking around to see her that had done this. 33 But the woman, frightened and trembling, knowing what had happened to her, came and fell down before him and told him the whole truth. 34 He said to her: “Daughter, your faith has made you well. Go in peace, and be in good health from your grievous sickness.”

35 While he was yet speaking, some men from the home of the presiding officer of the synagogue came and said: “Your daughter died! Why bother the teacher any longer?” 36 But Jesus, overhearing the word being spoken, said to the presiding officer of the synagogue: “Have no fear, only exercise faith.” 37 Now he did not let anyone follow along with him except Peter and James and John the brother of James.

38 So they came to the house of the presiding officer of the synagogue, and he beheld the noisy confusion and those weeping and letting out many wails, 39 and, after stepping in, he said to them: “Why are YOU causing noisy confusion and weeping? The young child has not died, but is sleeping.” 40 At this they began to laugh scornfully at him. But, having put them all out, he took along the young child’s father and mother and those with him, and he went in where the young child was. 41 And, taking the hand of the young child, he said to her: “Tal′i·tha cu′mi,” which, translated, means: “Maiden, I say to you, Get up!” 42 And immediately the maiden rose and began walking, for she was twelve years old. And at once they were beside themselves with great ecstasy. 43 But he ordered them again and again to let no one learn of this, and he said that something should be given her to eat.

Mark

7 Now the Pharisees and some of the scribes that had come from Jerusalem gathered about him. 2 And when they saw some of his disciples eat their meal with defiled hands, that is, unwashed ones— 3 for the Pharisees and all the Jews do not eat unless they wash their hands up to the elbow, holding fast the tradition of the men of former times, 4 and, when back from market, they do not eat unless they cleanse themselves by sprinkling; and there are many other traditions that they have received to hold fast, baptisms of cups and pitchers and copper vessels;— 5 so these Pharisees and scribes asked him: “Why is it your disciples do not conduct themselves according to the tradition of the men of former times, but they take their meal with defiled hands?” 6 He said to them: “Isaiah aptly prophesied about YOU hypocrites, as it is written, ‘This people honor me with their lips, but their hearts are far removed from me. 7 It is in vain that they keep worshiping me, because they teach as doctrines commands of men.’ 8 Letting go the commandment of God, YOU hold fast the tradition of men.”

9 Further, he went on to say to them: “Adroitly YOU set aside the commandment of God in order to retain YOUR tradition. 10 For example, Moses said, ‘Honor your father and your mother,’ and, ‘Let him that reviles father or mother end up in death.’ 11 But YOU men say, ‘If a man says to his father or his mother: “Whatever I have by which you may get benefit from me is corban, (that is, a gift dedicated to God,)”’— 12 YOU men no longer let him do a single thing for his father or his mother, 13 and thus YOU make the word of God invalid by YOUR tradition which YOU handed down. And many things similar to this YOU do.” 14 So, calling the crowd to him again, he proceeded to say to them: “Listen to me, all of YOU, and get the meaning. 15 There is nothing from outside a man that passes into him that can defile him; but the things that issue forth out of a man are the things that defile a man.” 16 ——

17 Now when he had entered a house away from the crowd, his disciples began to question him respecting the illustration. 18 So he said to them: “Are YOU also without perception like them? Are YOU not aware that nothing from outside that passes into a man can defile him, 19 since it passes, not into his heart, but into his intestines, and it passes out into the sewer?” Thus he declared all foods clean. 20 Further, he said: “That which issues forth out of a man is what defiles a man; 21 for from inside, out of the heart of men, injurious reasonings issue forth: fornications, thieveries, murders, 22 adulteries, covetings, acts of wickedness, deceit, loose conduct, an envious eye, blasphemy, haughtiness, unreasonableness. 23 All these wicked things issue forth from within and defile a man.”

24 From there he rose up and went into the regions of Tyre and Si′don. And he entered into a house and did not want anyone to get to know it. Yet he could not escape notice; 25 but immediately a woman whose little daughter had an unclean spirit heard about him and came and prostrated herself at his feet. 26 The woman was a Grecian, a Sy·ro·phoe·ni′cian nationally; and she kept asking him to expel the demon from her daughter. 27 But he began by saying to her: “First let the children be satisfied, for it is not right to take the bread of the children and throw it to the little dogs.” 28 In reply, however, she said to him: “Yes, sir, and yet the little dogs underneath the table eat of the crumbs of the little children.” 29 At that he said to her: “Because of saying this, go; the demon has gone out of your daughter.” 30 So she went away to her home and found the young child laid on the bed and the demon gone out.

31 Now coming back out of the regions of Tyre he went through Si′don to the sea of Gal′i·lee up through the midst of the regions of De·cap′o·lis. 32 Here they brought him a man deaf and with a speech impediment, and they entreated him to lay his hand upon him. 33 And he took him away from the crowd privately and put his fingers into the man’s ears and, after spitting, he touched his tongue. 34 And with a look up into heaven he sighed deeply and said to him: “Eph′pha·tha,” that is, “Be opened.” 35 Well, his hearing powers were opened, and the impediment of his tongue was loosed, and he began speaking normally. 36 With that he charged them not to tell anyone; but the more he would charge them, that much more they would proclaim it. 37 Indeed, they were being astounded in a most extraordinary way and they said: “He has done all things well. He even makes the deaf hear and the speechless speak.”

Mark

8 In those days, when there was again a big crowd and they had nothing to eat, he summoned the disciples and said to them: 2 “I feel pity for the crowd, because it is already three days that they have remained near me and they have nothing to eat; 3 and if I should send them off to their homes fasting, they will give out on the road. Indeed, some of them are from far away.” 4 But his disciples answered him: “From where will anybody here in an isolated place be able to satisfy these people with loaves?” 5 Still he went on to ask them: “How many loaves have YOU?” They said: “Seven.” 6 And he instructed the crowd to recline on the ground, and he took the seven loaves, gave thanks, broke them, and began to give them to his disciples to serve, and they served them to the crowd. 7 They also had a few little fishes; and, having blessed these, he told them also to serve these. 8 Accordingly they ate and were satisfied, and they took up surpluses of fragments, seven provision baskets full. 9 Yet there were about four thousand men. Finally he sent them away.

10 And immediately he boarded the boat with his disciples and came into the parts of Dal·ma·nu′tha. 11 Here the Pharisees came out and started disputing with him, seeking from him a sign from heaven, to put him to the test. 12 So he groaned deeply with his spirit, and said: “Why does this generation seek a sign? Truly I say, No sign will be given to this generation.” 13 With that he left them, got aboard again, and went off to the opposite shore.

14 As it was, they forgot to take loaves along, and except for one loaf they had nothing with them in the boat. 15 And he began to order them expressly and say: “Keep YOUR eyes open, look out for the leaven of the Pharisees and the leaven of Herod.” 16 So they went arguing with one another over the fact that they had no loaves. 17 Noting this, he said to them: “Why do YOU argue over YOUR having no loaves? Do YOU not yet perceive and get the meaning? Do YOU have YOUR hearts dull of understanding? 18 ‘Though having eyes, do YOU not see; and though having ears, do YOU not hear?’ And do YOU not remember, 19 when I broke the five loaves for the five thousand men, how many baskets full of fragments YOU took up?” They said to him: “Twelve.” 20 “When I broke the seven for the four thousand men, how many provision baskets full of fragments did YOU take up?” And they said to him: “Seven.” 21 With that he said to them: “Do YOU not yet get the meaning?”

22 Now they put in at Beth·sa′i·da. Here people brought him a blind man, and they entreated him to touch him. 23 And he took the blind man by the hand, brought him outside the village, and, having spit upon his eyes, he laid his hands upon him and began to ask him: “Do you see anything?” 24 And the man looked up and began saying: “I see men, because I observe what seem to be trees, but they are walking about.” 25 Then he laid his hands again upon the man’s eyes, and the man saw clearly, and he was restored, and he was seeing everything distinctly. 26 So he sent him off home, saying: “But do not enter into the village.”

27 Jesus and his disciples now left for the villages of Caes·a·re′a Phi·lip′pi, and on the way he began questioning his disciples, saying to them: “Who are men saying that I am?” 28 They said to him: “John the Baptist, and others, E·li′jah, still others, One of the prophets.” 29 And he put the question to them: “YOU, though, who do YOU say I am?” In answer Peter said to him: “You are the Christ.” 30 At that he strictly charged them not to tell anyone about him. 31 Also, he started teaching them that the Son of man must undergo many sufferings and be rejected by the older men and the chief priests and the scribes and be killed, and rise three days later. 32 Indeed, with outspokenness he was making that statement. But Peter took him aside and started rebuking him. 33 He turned, looked at his disciples and rebuked Peter, and said: “Get behind me, Satan, because you think, not God’s thoughts, but those of men.”

34 He now called the crowd to him with his disciples and said to them: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake and follow me continually. 35 For whoever wants to save his soul will lose it; but whoever loses his soul for the sake of me and the good news will save it. 36 Really, of what benefit is it for a man to gain the whole world and to forfeit his soul? 37 What, really, would a man give in exchange for his soul? 38 For whoever becomes ashamed of me and my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of man will also be ashamed of him when he arrives in the glory of his Father with the holy angels.”

Mark

9 Furthermore, he went on to say to them: “Truly I say to YOU, There are some of those standing here that will not taste death at all until first they see the kingdom of God already come in power.” 2 Accordingly six days later Jesus took Peter and James and John along, and brought them up into a lofty mountain to themselves alone. And he was transfigured before them, 3 and his outer garments became glistening, far whiter than any clothes cleaner on earth could whiten them. 4 Also, E·li′jah with Moses appeared to them, and they were conversing with Jesus. 5 And responsively Peter said to Jesus: “Rabbi, it is fine for us to be here, so let us erect three tents, one for you and one for Moses and one for E·li′jah.” 6 In fact, he did not know what response he should make, for they became quite fearful. 7 And a cloud formed, overshadowing them, and a voice came out of the cloud: “This is my Son, the beloved; listen to him.” 8 Suddenly, however, they looked around and saw no one with them any longer, except Jesus alone.

9 As they were coming down out of the mountain, he expressly ordered them not to relate to anybody what they saw, until after the Son of man had risen from the dead. 10 And they took the word to heart, but discussed among themselves what this rising from the dead meant. 11 And they began to question him, saying: “Why do the scribes say that first E·li′jah must come?” 12 He said to them: “E·li′jah does come first and restore all things; but how is it that it is written respecting the Son of man that he must undergo many sufferings and be treated as of no account? 13 But I say to YOU, E·li′jah, in fact, has come, and they did to him as many things as they wanted, just as it is written respecting him.”

14 When, now, they came toward the other disciples, they noticed a great crowd about them and scribes disputing with them. 15 But as soon as all the crowd caught sight of him they were stunned, and, running up to him, they began to greet him. 16 And he asked them: “What are YOU disputing with them?” 17 And one of the crowd answered him: “Teacher, I brought my son to you because he has a speechless spirit; 18 and wherever it seizes him it dashes him to the ground, and he foams and grinds his teeth and loses his strength. And I told your disciples to expel it, but they were not capable.” 19 In response he said to them: “O faithless generation, how long must I continue with YOU? How long must I put up with YOU? Bring him to me.” 20 So they brought him to him. But at the sight of him the spirit at once threw the child into convulsions, and after falling on the ground he kept rolling about, foaming. 21 And he asked his father: “How long has this been happening to him?” He said: “From childhood on; 22 and time and again it would throw him both into the fire and into the water to destroy him. But if you can do anything, have pity on us and help us.” 23 Jesus said to him: “That expression, ‘If you can’! Why, all things can be to one if one has faith.” 24 Immediately crying out, the father of the young child was saying: “I have faith! Help me out where I need faith!”

25 Jesus, now noticing that a crowd was running together upon them, rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to it: “You speechless and deaf spirit, I order you, get out of him and enter into him no more.” 26 And after crying out and going through many convulsions it got out; and he became as dead, so that the greater number of them were saying: “He is dead!” 27 But Jesus took him by the hand and raised him up, and he rose. 28 So after he entered into a house his disciples proceeded to ask him privately: “Why could we not expel it?” 29 And he said to them: “This kind cannot get out by anything except by prayer.”

30 From there they departed and went their way through Gal′i·lee, but he did not want anyone to get to know it. 31 For he was teaching his disciples and telling them: “The Son of man is to be delivered into men’s hands, and they will kill him, but, despite being killed, he will rise three days later.” 32 However, they were not understanding the saying, and they were afraid to question him.

33 And they came into Ca·per′na·um. Now when he was inside the house he put the question to them: “What were YOU arguing over on the road?” 34 They kept silent, for on the road they had argued among themselves who is greater. 35 So he sat down and called the twelve and said to them: “If anyone wants to be first, he must be last of all and minister of all.” 36 And he took a young child, stood it in their midst and put his arms around it and said to them: 37 “Whoever receives one of such young children on the basis of my name, receives me; and whoever receives me, receives, not me only, but also him that sent me forth.”

38 John said to him: “Teacher, we saw a certain man expelling demons by the use of your name and we tried to prevent him, because he was not accompanying us.” 39 But Jesus said: “Do not try to prevent him, for there is no one that will do a powerful work on the basis of my name that will quickly be able to revile me; 40 for he that is not against us is for us. 41 For whoever gives YOU a cup of water to drink on the ground that YOU belong to Christ, I truly tell YOU, he will by no means lose his reward. 42 But whoever stumbles one of these little ones that believe, it would be finer for him if a millstone such as is turned by an ass were put around his neck and he were actually pitched into the sea.

43 “And if ever your hand makes you stumble, cut it off; it is finer for you to enter into life maimed than with two hands to go off into Ge·hen′na, into the fire that cannot be put out. 44 —— 45 And if your foot makes you stumble, cut it off; it is finer for you to enter into life lame than with two feet to be pitched into Ge·hen′na. 46 —— 47 And if your eye makes you stumble, throw it away; it is finer for you to enter one-eyed into the kingdom of God than with two eyes to be pitched into Ge·hen′na, 48 where their maggot does not die and the fire is not put out.

49 “For everyone must be salted with fire. 50 Salt is fine; but if ever the salt loses its strength, with what will YOU season it itself? Have salt in yourselves, and keep peace between one another.”

Mark

10 From there he rose and came to the frontiers of Ju·de′a and across the Jordan, and again crowds came together to him, and as he was accustomed to do he again went teaching them. 2 Pharisees now approached and, to put him to the test, began questioning him whether it was lawful for a man to divorce a wife. 3 In answer he said to them: “What did Moses command YOU?” 4 They said: “Moses allowed the writing of a certificate of dismissal and divorcing her.” 5 But Jesus said to them: “Out of regard for YOUR hardheartedness he wrote YOU this commandment. 6 However, from the beginning of creation ‘He made them male and female. 7 On this account a man will leave his father and mother, 8 and the two will be one flesh’; so that they are no longer two, but one flesh. 9 Therefore what God yoked together let no man put apart.” 10 When again in the house the disciples began to question him concerning this. 11 And he said to them: “Whoever divorces his wife and marries another commits adultery against her, 12 and if ever a woman, after divorcing her husband, marries another, she commits adultery.”

13 Now people began bringing him young children for him to touch these; but the disciples reprimanded them. 14 At seeing this Jesus was indignant and said to them: “Let the young children come to me; do not try to stop them, for the kingdom of God belongs to suchlike ones. 15 Truly I say to YOU, Whoever does not receive the kingdom of God like a young child will by no means enter into it.” 16 And he took the children into his arms and began blessing them, laying his hands upon them.

17 And as he was going out on his way, a certain man ran up and fell upon his knees before him and put the question to him: “Good Teacher, what must I do to inherit everlasting life?” 18 Jesus said to him: “Why do you call me good? Nobody is good, except one, God. 19 You know the commandments, ‘Do not murder, Do not commit adultery, Do not steal, Do not bear false witness, Do not defraud, Honor your father and mother.’” 20 The man said to him: “Teacher, all these things I have kept from my youth on.” 21 Jesus looked upon him and felt love for him and said to him: “One thing is missing about you: Go, sell what things you have and give to the poor, and you will have treasure in heaven, and come be my follower.” 22 But he grew sad at the saying and went off grieved, for he was holding many possessions.

23 After looking around Jesus said to his disciples: “How difficult a thing it will be for those with money to enter into the kingdom of God!” 24 But the disciples gave way to surprise at his words. In response Jesus again said to them: “Children, how difficult a thing it is to enter into the kingdom of God! 25 It is easier for a camel to go through a needle’s eye than for a rich man to enter into the kingdom of God.” 26 They became still more astounded and said to him: “Who, in fact, can be saved?” 27 Looking straight at them Jesus said: “With men it is impossible, but not so with God, for all things are possible with God.” 28 Peter started to say to him: “Look! We left all things and have been following you.” 29 Jesus said: “Truly I say to YOU men, No one has left house or brothers or sisters or mother or father or children or fields for my sake and for the sake of the good news 30 who will not get a hundredfold now in this period of time, houses and brothers and sisters and mothers and children and fields, with persecutions, and in the coming system of things everlasting life. 31 However, many that are first will be last, and the last first.”

32 Now they were advancing on the road up to Jerusalem, and Jesus was going in front of them, and they felt amazement; but those who followed began to fear. Once again he took the twelve aside and started to tell them these things destined to befall him: 33 “Here we are, advancing up to Jerusalem, and the Son of man will be delivered to the chief priests and the scribes, and they will condemn him to death and will deliver him to men of the nations, 34 and they will make fun of him and will spit upon him and scourge him and kill him, but three days later he will rise.”

35 And James and John, the two sons of Zeb′e·dee, stepped up to him and said to him: “Teacher, we want you to do for us whatever it is we ask you for.” 36 He said to them: “What do YOU want me to do for YOU?” 37 They said to him: “Grant us to sit down, one at your right hand and one at your left, in your glory.” 38 But Jesus said to them: “YOU do not know what YOU are asking for. Are YOU able to drink the cup which I am drinking, or to be baptized with the baptism with which I am being baptized?” 39 They said to him: “We are able.” At that Jesus said to them: “The cup I am drinking YOU will drink, and with the baptism with which I am being baptized YOU will be baptized. 40 However, this sitting down at my right or at my left is not mine to give, but it belongs to those for whom it has been prepared.”

41 Well, when the ten others heard about it, they started to be indignant at James and John. 42 But Jesus, after calling them to him, said to them: “YOU know that those who appear to be ruling the nations lord it over them and their great ones wield authority over them. 43 This is not the way among YOU; but whoever wants to become great among YOU must be YOUR minister, 44 and whoever wants to be first among YOU must be the slave of all. 45 For even the Son of man came, not to be ministered to, but to minister and to give his soul a ransom in exchange for many.”

46 And they came into Jer′i·cho. But as he and his disciples and a considerable crowd were going out of Jer′i·cho, Bar·ti·mae′us (the son of Ti·mae′us), a blind beggar, was sitting beside the road. 47 When he heard that it was Jesus the Naz·a·rene′, he started shouting and saying: “Son of David, Jesus, have mercy on me!” 48 At this many began sternly telling him to be silent; but he kept shouting that much more: “Son of David, have mercy on me!” 49 So Jesus stopped and said: “CALL him.” And they called the blind man, saying to him: “Take courage, get up, he is calling you.” 50 Throwing off his outer garment, he leaped to his feet and went to Jesus. 51 And in answer to him Jesus said: “What do you want me to do for you?” The blind man said to him: “Rab·bo′ni, let me recover sight.” 52 And Jesus said to him: “Go, your faith has made you well.” And immediately he recovered sight, and he began to follow him on the road.

Mark

11 Now when they were getting near to Jerusalem, to Beth′pha·ge and Beth′a·ny at the Mount of Olives, he dispatched two of his disciples 2 and told them: “Go into the village that is within sight of YOU, and as soon as YOU pass into it YOU will find a colt tied, on which none of mankind has yet sat; loose it and bring it. 3 And if anyone says to YOU, ‘Why are YOU doing this?’ say, ‘The Lord needs it, and will at once send it off back here.’” 4 So they went away and found the colt tied at the door, outside on the side street, and they loosed it. 5 But some of those standing there began to say to them: “What are YOU doing loosing the colt?” 6 They said to these just as Jesus had said; and they let them go.

7 And they brought the colt to Jesus, and they put their outer garments upon it, and he sat on it. 8 Also, many spread their outer garments on the road, but others cut down foliage from the fields. 9 And those going in front and those coming behind kept crying out: “Save, we pray! Blessed is he that comes in Jehovah’s name! 10 Blessed is the coming kingdom of our father David! Save, we pray, in the heights above!” 11 And he entered into Jerusalem, into the temple; and he looked around upon all things, and, as the hour was already late, he went out to Beth′a·ny with the twelve.

12 The next day, when they had come out from Beth′a·ny, he became hungry. 13 And from a distance he caught sight of a fig tree that had leaves, and he went to see whether he would perhaps find something on it. But, on coming to it, he found nothing but leaves, for it was not the season of figs. 14 So, in response, he said to it: “Let no one eat fruit from you anymore forever.” And his disciples were listening.

15 Now they came to Jerusalem. There he entered into the temple and started to throw out those selling and buying in the temple, and he overturned the tables of the money changers and the benches of those selling doves; 16 and he would not let anyone carry a utensil through the temple, 17 but he kept teaching and saying: “Is it not written, ‘My house will be called a house of prayer for all the nations’? But YOU have made it a cave of robbers.” 18 And the chief priests and the scribes heard it, and they began to seek how to destroy him; for they were in fear of him, for all the crowd was continually being astounded at his teaching.

19 And when it became late in the day, they would go out of the city. 20 But when they were passing by early in the morning, they saw the fig tree already withered up from the roots. 21 So Peter, remembering it, said to him: “Rabbi, see! the fig tree that you cursed has withered up.” 22 And in reply Jesus said to them: “Have faith in God. 23 Truly I say to YOU that whoever tells this mountain, ‘Be lifted up and thrown into the sea,’ and does not doubt in his heart but has faith that what he says is going to occur, he will have it so. 24 This is why I tell YOU, All the things YOU pray and ask for have faith that YOU have practically received, and YOU will have them. 25 And when YOU stand praying, forgive whatever YOU have against anyone; in order that YOUR Father who is in the heavens may also forgive YOU YOUR trespasses.” 26 ——

27 And they came again to Jerusalem. And as he was walking in the temple, the chief priests and the scribes and the older men came to him 28 and began to say to him: “By what authority do you do these things? or who gave you this authority to do these things?” 29 Jesus said to them: “I will ask YOU one question. YOU answer me, and I will also tell YOU by what authority I do these things. 30 Was the baptism by John from heaven or from men? Answer me.” 31 So they began to reason among themselves, saying: “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why is it, therefore, YOU did not believe him?’ 32 But dare we say, ‘From men’?”—They were in fear of the crowd, for these all held that John had really been a prophet. 33 Well, in reply to Jesus they said: “We do not know.” And Jesus said to them: “Neither am I telling YOU by what authority I do these things.”

Mark

12 Also, he started to speak to them with illustrations: “A man planted a vineyard, and put a fence around it, and dug a vat for the winepress and erected a tower, and let it out to cultivators, and traveled abroad. 2 Now in due season he sent forth a slave to the cultivators, that he might get some of the fruits of the vineyard from the cultivators. 3 But they took him, beat him up and sent him away empty. 4 And again he sent forth another slave to them; and that one they struck on the head and dishonored. 5 And he sent forth another, and that one they killed; and many others, some of whom they beat up and some of whom they killed. 6 One more he had, a beloved son. He sent him forth last to them, saying, ‘They will respect my son.’ 7 But those cultivators said among themselves, ‘This is the heir. Come, let us kill him, and the inheritance will be ours.’ 8 So they took him and killed him, and threw him outside the vineyard. 9 What will the owner of the vineyard do? He will come and destroy the cultivators, and will give the vineyard to others. 10 Did YOU never read this scripture, ‘The stone that the builders rejected, this has become the chief cornerstone. 11 From Jehovah this has come to be, and it is marvelous in our eyes’?”

12 At that they began seeking how to seize him, but they feared the crowd, for they took note that he spoke the illustration with them in mind. So they left him and went away.

13 Next they sent forth to him some of the Pharisees and of the party followers of Herod, to catch him in his speech. 14 On arrival these said to him: “Teacher, we know you are truthful and you do not care for anybody, for you do not look upon men’s outward appearance, but you teach the way of God in line with truth: Is it lawful to pay head tax to Caesar or not? 15 Shall we pay, or shall we not pay?” Detecting their hypocrisy, he said to them: “Why do YOU put me to the test? Bring me a de·nar′i·us to look at.” 16 They brought one. And he said to them: “Whose image and inscription is this?” They said to him: “Caesar’s.” 17 Jesus then said: “Pay back Caesar’s things to Caesar, but God’s things to God.” And they began to marvel at him.

18 Now Sadducees came to him, who say there is no resurrection, and they put the question to him: 19 “Teacher, Moses wrote us that if someone’s brother dies and leaves a wife behind but does not leave a child, his brother should take the wife and raise up offspring from her for his brother. 20 There were seven brothers; and the first took a wife, but when he died he left no offspring. 21 And the second took her, but died without leaving offspring; and the third the same way. 22 And the seven did not leave any offspring. Last of all the woman also died. 23 In the resurrection to which of them will she be wife? For the seven got her as wife.” 24 Jesus said to them: “Is not this why YOU are mistaken, YOUR not knowing either the Scriptures or the power of God? 25 For when they rise from the dead, neither do men marry nor are women given in marriage, but are as angels in the heavens. 26 But concerning the dead, that they are raised up, did YOU not read in the book of Moses, in the account about the thornbush, how God said to him, ‘I am the God of Abraham and God of Isaac and God of Jacob’? 27 He is a God, not of the dead, but of the living. YOU are much mistaken.”

28 Now one of the scribes that had come up and heard them disputing, knowing that he had answered them in a fine way, asked him: “Which commandment is first of all?” 29 Jesus answered: “The first is, ‘Hear, O Israel, Jehovah our God is one Jehovah, 30 and you must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole mind and with your whole strength.’ 31 The second is this, ‘You must love your neighbor as yourself.’ There is no other commandment greater than these.” 32 The scribe said to him: “Teacher, you well said in line with truth, ‘He is One, and there is no other than He’; 33 and this loving him with one’s whole heart and with one’s whole understanding and with one’s whole strength and this loving one’s neighbor as oneself is worth far more than all the whole burnt offerings and sacrifices.” 34 At this Jesus, discerning he had answered intelligently, said to him: “You are not far from the kingdom of God.” But nobody had the courage anymore to question him.

35 However, when making a reply, Jesus began to say as he taught in the temple: “How is it that the scribes say that the Christ is David’s son? 36 By the holy spirit David himself said, ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand until I put your enemies beneath your feet.”’ 37 David himself calls him ‘Lord,’ but how does it come that he is his son?”

And the great crowd was listening to him with pleasure. 38 And in his teaching he went on to say: “Look out for the scribes that want to walk around in robes and want greetings in the marketplaces 39 and front seats in the synagogues and most prominent places at evening meals. 40 They are the ones devouring the houses of the widows and for a pretext making long prayers; these will receive a heavier judgment.”

41 And he sat down with the treasury chests in view and began observing how the crowd was dropping money into the treasury chests; and many rich people were dropping in many coins. 42 Now a poor widow came and dropped in two small coins, which have very little value. 43 So he called his disciples to him and said to them: “Truly I say to YOU that this poor widow dropped in more than all those dropping money into the treasury chests; 44 for they all dropped in out of their surplus, but she, out of her want, dropped in all of what she had, her whole living.”

Mark

15 And immediately at dawn the chief priests with the older men and the scribes, even the whole San′he·drin, conducted a consultation, and they bound Jesus and led him off and handed him over to Pilate. 2 So Pilate put the question to him: “Are you the king of the Jews?” In answer to him he said: “You yourself say it.” 3 But the chief priests proceeded to accuse him of many things. 4 Now Pilate began questioning him again, saying: “Have you no reply to make? See how many charges they are bringing against you.” 5 But Jesus made no further answer, so that Pilate began to marvel.

6 Well, from festival to festival he used to release to them one prisoner, whom they petitioned for. 7 At the time there was the so-called Bar·ab′bas in bonds with the seditionists, who in their sedition had committed murder. 8 So the crowd came on up and started to make petition according to what he used to do for them. 9 Pilate responded to them, saying: “Do YOU want me to release to YOU the king of the Jews?” 10 For he was aware that because of envy the chief priests had handed him over. 11 But the chief priests stirred up the crowd to have him release Bar·ab′bas to them, instead. 12 Again in reply Pilate was saying to them: “What, then, shall I do with him whom YOU call the king of the Jews?” 13 Once more they cried out: “Impale him!” 14 But Pilate went on to say to them: “Why, what bad thing did he do?” Still they cried out all the more: “Impale him!” 15 At that Pilate, wishing to satisfy the crowd, released Bar·ab′bas to them, and, after having Jesus whipped, he handed him over to be impaled.

16 The soldiers now led him off into the courtyard, that is, into the governor’s palace; and they called the whole body of troops together, 17 and they decked him with purple and braided a crown of thorns and put it on him. 18 And they started greeting him: “Good day, you King of the Jews!” 19 Also, they would hit him on the head with a reed and spit upon him and, bending their knees, they would do obeisance to him. 20 Finally, when they had made fun of him, they stripped him of the purple and put his outer garments upon him. And they led him out to impale him. 21 Also, they impressed into service a passerby, a certain Simon of Cy·re′ne, coming from the country, the father of Alexander and Ru′fus, that he should lift up his torture stake.

22 So they brought him to the place Gol′go·tha, which means, when translated, Skull Place. 23 Here they tried to give him wine drugged with myrrh, but he would not take it. 24 And they impaled him and distributed his outer garments by casting the lot over them as to who takes what. 25 It was now the third hour, and they impaled him. 26 And the inscription of the charge against him was written above, “The King of the Jews.” 27 Moreover, they impaled two robbers with him, one on his right and one on his left. 28 —— 29 And those going by would speak abusively to him, wagging their heads and saying: “Bah! You would-be thrower-down of the temple and builder of it in three days’ time, 30 save yourself by coming down off the torture stake.” 31 In like manner also the chief priests were making fun among themselves with the scribes and saying: “Others he saved; himself he cannot save! 32 Let the Christ the King of Israel now come down off the torture stake, that we may see and believe.” Even those impaled together with him were reproaching him.

33 When it became the sixth hour a darkness fell over the whole land until the ninth hour. 34 And at the ninth hour Jesus called out with a loud voice: “E′li, E′li, la′ma sa·bach·tha′ni?” which means, when translated: “My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?” 35 And some of those standing near, on hearing it, began to say: “See! He is calling E·li′jah.” 36 But a certain one ran, soaked a sponge with sour wine, put it on a reed, and began giving him a drink, saying: “LET him be! Let us see whether E·li′jah comes to take him down.” 37 But Jesus let out a loud cry and expired. 38 And the curtain of the sanctuary was rent in two from top to bottom. 39 Now, when the army officer that was standing by with him in view saw he had expired under these circumstances, he said: “Certainly this man was God’s Son.”

40 There were also women viewing from a distance, among them Mary Mag′da·lene as well as Mary the mother of James the Less and of Jo′ses, and Sa·lo′me, 41 who used to accompany him and minister to him when he was in Gal′i·lee, and many other women who had come up together with him to Jerusalem.

42 Now as it was already late in the afternoon, and since it was Preparation, that is, the day before the sabbath, 43 there came Joseph of Ar·i·ma·the′a, a reputable member of the Council, who also himself was waiting for the kingdom of God. He took courage to go in before Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus. 44 But Pilate wondered whether he was already dead, and, summoning the army officer, he asked him whether he had already died. 45 So after making certain from the army officer, he granted the corpse to Joseph. 46 Accordingly he bought fine linen and took him down, wrapped him in the fine linen and laid him in a tomb which was quarried out of a rock-mass; and he rolled a stone up to the door of the memorial tomb. 47 But Mary Mag′da·lene and Mary the mother of Jo′ses continued looking at where he had been laid.

Luke

4 Now Jesus, full of holy spirit, turned away from the Jordan, and he was led about by the spirit in the wilderness 2 for forty days, while being tempted by the Devil. Furthermore, he ate nothing in those days, and so, when they were concluded, he felt hungry. 3 At this the Devil said to him: “If you are a son of God, tell this stone to become a loaf of bread.” 4 But Jesus replied to him: “It is written, ‘Man must not live by bread alone.’”

5 So he brought him up and showed him all the kingdoms of the inhabited earth in an instant of time; 6 and the Devil said to him: “I will give you all this authority and the glory of them, because it has been delivered to me, and to whomever I wish I give it. 7 You, therefore, if you do an act of worship before me, it will all be yours.” 8 In reply Jesus said to him: “It is written, ‘It is Jehovah your God you must worship, and it is to him alone you must render sacred service.’”

9 Now he led him into Jerusalem and stationed him upon the battlement of the temple and said to him: “If you are a son of God, hurl yourself down from here; 10 for it is written, ‘He will give his angels a charge concerning you, to preserve you,’ 11 and, ‘They will carry you on their hands, that you may at no time strike your foot against a stone.’” 12 In answer Jesus said to him: “It is said, ‘You must not put Jehovah your God to the test.’” 13 So the Devil, having concluded all the temptation, retired from him until another convenient time.

14 Now Jesus returned in the power of the spirit into Gal′i·lee. And good talk concerning him spread out through all the surrounding country. 15 Also, he began to teach in their synagogues, being held in honor by all.

16 And he came to Naz′a·reth, where he had been reared; and, according to his custom on the sabbath day, he entered into the synagogue, and he stood up to read. 17 So the scroll of the prophet Isaiah was handed him, and he opened the scroll and found the place where it was written: 18 “Jehovah’s spirit is upon me, because he anointed me to declare good news to the poor, he sent me forth to preach a release to the captives and a recovery of sight to the blind, to send the crushed ones away with a release, 19 to preach Jehovah’s acceptable year.” 20 With that he rolled up the scroll, handed it back to the attendant and sat down; and the eyes of all in the synagogue were intently fixed upon him. 21 Then he started to say to them: “Today this scripture that YOU just heard is fulfilled.”

22 And they all began to give favorable witness about him and to marvel at the winsome words proceeding out of his mouth, and they were saying: “This is a son of Joseph, is it not?” 23 At this he said to them: “No doubt YOU will apply this illustration to me, ‘Physician, cure yourself; the things we heard as having happened in Ca·per′na·um do also here in your home territory.’” 24 But he said: “Truly I tell YOU that no prophet is accepted in his home territory. 25 For instance, I tell YOU in truth, There were many widows in Israel in the days of E·li′jah, when the heaven was shut up three years and six months, so that a great famine fell upon all the land, 26 yet E·li′jah was sent to none of those women, but only to Zar′e·phath in the land of Si′don to a widow. 27 Also, there were many lepers in Israel in the time of E·li′sha the prophet, yet not one of them was cleansed, but Na′a·man the man of Syria.” 28 Now all those hearing these things in the synagogue became filled with anger; 29 and they rose up and hurried him outside the city, and they led him to the brow of the mountain upon which their city had been built, in order to throw him down headlong. 30 But he went through the midst of them and continued on his way.

31 And he went down to Ca·per′na·um, a city of Gal′i·lee. And he was teaching them on the sabbath; 32 and they were astounded at his way of teaching, because his speech was with authority. 33 Now in the synagogue there was a man with a spirit, an unclean demon, and he shouted with a loud voice: 34 “Ah! What have we to do with you, Jesus you Naz·a·rene′? Did you come to destroy us? I know exactly who you are, the Holy One of God.” 35 But Jesus rebuked it, saying: “Be silent, and come out of him.” So, after throwing the man down in their midst, the demon came out of him without hurting him. 36 At this, astonishment fell upon all, and they began to converse with one another, saying: “What sort of speech is this, because with authority and power he orders the unclean spirits, and out they come?” 37 So the news concerning him kept going out into every corner of the surrounding country.

38 After getting up out of the synagogue he entered into Simon’s home. Now Simon’s mother-in-law was distressed with a high fever, and they made request of him for her. 39 So he stood over her and rebuked the fever, and it left her. Instantly she rose and began ministering to them.

40 But when the sun was setting, all those who had people sick with various diseases brought them to him. By laying his hands upon each one of them he would cure them. 41 Demons also would come out of many, crying out and saying: “You are the Son of God.” But, rebuking them, he would not permit them to speak, because they knew him to be the Christ.

42 However, when it became day, he went out and proceeded to a lonely place. But the crowds began hunting about for him and came out as far as he was, and they tried to detain him from going away from them. 43 But he said to them: “Also to other cities I must declare the good news of the kingdom of God, because for this I was sent forth.” 44 Accordingly he went on preaching in the synagogues of Ju·de′a.

Luke

7 When he had completed all his sayings in the hearing of the people, he entered into Ca·per′na·um. 2 Now a certain army officer’s slave, who was dear to him, was ailing and was about to pass away. 3 When he heard about Jesus, he sent forth older men of the Jews to him to ask him to come and bring his slave safely through. 4 Then those that came up to Jesus began to entreat him earnestly, saying: “He is worthy of your conferring this upon him, 5 for he loves our nation and he himself built the synagogue for us.” 6 So Jesus started off with them. But when he was not far from the house, the army officer had already sent friends to say to him: “Sir, do not bother, for I am not fit to have you come in under my roof. 7 For that reason I did not consider myself worthy to come to you. But say the word, and let my servant be healed. 8 For I too am a man placed under authority, having soldiers under me, and I say to this one, ‘Be on your way!’ and he is on his way, and to another, ‘Come!’ and he comes, and to my slave, ‘Do this!’ and he does it.” 9 Well, when Jesus heard these things he marveled at him, and he turned to the crowd following him and said: “I tell YOU, Not even in Israel have I found so great a faith.” 10 And those that had been sent, on getting back to the house, found the slave in good health.

11 Closely following this he traveled to a city called Na′in, and his disciples and a great crowd were traveling with him. 12 As he got near the gate of the city, why, look! there was a dead man being carried out, the only-begotten son of his mother. Besides, she was a widow. A considerable crowd from the city was also with her. 13 And when the Lord caught sight of her, he was moved with pity for her, and he said to her: “Stop weeping.” 14 With that he approached and touched the bier, and the bearers stood still, and he said: “Young man, I say to you, Get up!” 15 And the dead man sat up and started to speak, and he gave him to his mother. 16 Now fear seized them all, and they began to glorify God, saying: “A great prophet has been raised up among us,” and, “God has turned his attention to his people.” 17 And this news concerning him spread out into all Ju·de′a and all the surrounding country.

18 Now John’s disciples reported to him about all these things. 19 So John summoned a certain two of his disciples and sent them to the Lord to say: “Are you the Coming One or are we to expect a different one?” 20 When they came up to him the men said: “John the Baptist dispatched us to you to say, ‘Are you the Coming One or are we to expect another?’” 21 In that hour he cured many of sicknesses and grievous diseases and wicked spirits, and granted many blind persons the favor of seeing. 22 Hence in answer he said to the two: “Go YOUR way, report to John what YOU saw and heard: the blind are receiving sight, the lame are walking, the lepers are being cleansed and the deaf are hearing, the dead are being raised up, the poor are being told the good news. 23 And happy is he who has not stumbled over me.”

24 When the messengers of John had gone away, he started to say to the crowds concerning John: “What did YOU go out into the wilderness to behold? A reed being tossed by the wind? 25 What, then, did YOU go out to see? A man dressed in soft outer garments? Why, those in splendid dress and existing in luxury are in royal houses. 26 Really, then, what did YOU go out to see? A prophet? Yes, I tell YOU, and far more than a prophet. 27 This is he concerning whom it is written, ‘Look! I am sending forth my messenger before your face, who will prepare your way ahead of you.’ 28 I tell YOU, Among those born of women there is none greater than John; but a person that is a lesser one in the kingdom of God is greater than he is.” 29 (And all the people and the tax collectors, when they heard this, declared God to be righteous, they having been baptized with the baptism of John. 30 But the Pharisees and those versed in the Law disregarded the counsel of God to them, they not having been baptized by him.)

31 “With whom, therefore, shall I compare the men of this generation, and whom are they like? 32 They are like young children sitting in a marketplace and crying out to one another, and who say, ‘We played the flute for YOU, but YOU did not dance; we wailed, but YOU did not weep.’ 33 Correspondingly, John the Baptist has come neither eating bread nor drinking wine, but YOU say, ‘He has a demon.’ 34 The Son of man has come eating and drinking, but YOU say, ‘Look! A man gluttonous and given to drinking wine, a friend of tax collectors and sinners!’ 35 All the same, wisdom is proved righteous by all its children.”

36 Now a certain one of the Pharisees kept asking him to dine with him. Accordingly he entered into the house of the Pharisee and reclined at the table. 37 And, look! a woman who was known in the city to be a sinner learned that he was reclining at a meal in the house of the Pharisee, and she brought an alabaster case of perfumed oil, 38 and, taking a position behind at his feet, she wept and started to wet his feet with her tears and she would wipe them off with the hair of her head. Also, she tenderly kissed his feet and greased them with the perfumed oil. 39 At the sight the Pharisee that invited him said within himself: “This man, if he were a prophet, would know who and what kind of woman it is that is touching him, that she is a sinner.” 40 But in reply Jesus said to him: “Simon, I have something to say to you.” He said: “Teacher, say it!”

41 “Two men were debtors to a certain lender; the one was in debt for five hundred de·nar′i·i, but the other for fifty. 42 When they did not have anything with which to pay back, he freely forgave them both. Therefore, which of them will love him the more?” 43 In answer Simon said: “I suppose it is the one to whom he freely forgave the more.” He said to him: “You judged correctly.” 44 With that he turned to the woman and said to Simon: “Do you behold this woman? I entered into your house; you gave me no water for my feet. But this woman wet my feet with her tears and wiped them off with her hair. 45 You gave me no kiss; but this woman, from the hour that I came in, did not leave off tenderly kissing my feet. 46 You did not grease my head with oil; but this woman greased my feet with perfumed oil. 47 By virtue of this, I tell you, her sins, many though they are, are forgiven, because she loved much; but he who is forgiven little, loves little.” 48 Then he said to her: “Your sins are forgiven.” 49 At this those reclining at the table with him started to say within themselves: “Who is this man who even forgives sins?” 50 But he said to the woman: “Your faith has saved you; go your way in peace.”

Luke

9 Then he called the twelve together and gave them power and authority over all the demons and to cure sicknesses. 2 And so he sent them forth to preach the kingdom of God and to heal, 3 and he said to them: “Carry nothing for the trip, neither staff nor food pouch, nor bread nor silver money; neither have two undergarments. 4 But wherever YOU enter into a home, stay there and leave from there. 5 And wherever people do not receive YOU, on going out of that city shake the dust off YOUR feet for a witness against them.” 6 Then starting out they went through the territory from village to village, declaring the good news and performing cures everywhere.

7 Now Herod the district ruler heard of all the things happening, and he was in great perplexity because of its being said by some that John had been raised up from the dead, 8 but by others that E·li′jah had appeared, but by still others that a certain one of the ancient prophets had risen. 9 Herod said: “John I beheaded. Who, then, is this about whom I am hearing such things?” So he was seeking to see him.

10 And when the apostles returned they recounted to him what things they had done. With that he took them along and withdrew to privacy into a city called Beth·sa′i·da. 11 But the crowds, getting to know it, followed him. And he received them kindly and began to speak to them about the kingdom of God, and he healed those needing a cure. 12 Then the day started to decline. The twelve now came up and said to him: “Dismiss the crowd, that they may go into the villages and countryside round about and procure lodging and find provisions, because out here we are in a lonely place.” 13 But he said to them: “YOU give them something to eat.” They said: “We have nothing more than five loaves and two fishes, unless perhaps we ourselves go and buy foodstuffs for all these people.” 14 They were, in fact, about five thousand men. But he said to his disciples: “Have them recline as at meals, in groups of about fifty each.” 15 And they did so and had them all recline. 16 Then taking the five loaves and the two fishes, he looked up to heaven, blessed them and broke them up and began to give them to the disciples to set before the crowd. 17 So they all ate and were satisfied, and the surplus that they had was taken up, twelve baskets of fragments.

18 Later, while he was praying alone, the disciples came together to him, and he questioned them, saying: “Who are the crowds saying that I am?” 19 In reply they said: “John the Baptist; but others, E·li′jah, and still others, that one of the ancient prophets has risen.” 20 Then he said to them: “YOU, though, who do YOU say I am?” Peter said in reply: “The Christ of God.” 21 Then in a stern talk to them he instructed them not to be telling this to anybody, 22 but said: “The Son of man must undergo many sufferings and be rejected by the older men and chief priests and scribes, and be killed, and on the third day be raised up.”

23 Then he went on to say to all: “If anyone wants to come after me, let him disown himself and pick up his torture stake day after day and follow me continually. 24 For whoever wants to save his soul will lose it; but whoever loses his soul for my sake is the one that will save it. 25 Really, what does a man benefit himself if he gains the whole world but loses his own self or suffers damage? 26 For whoever becomes ashamed of me and of my words, the Son of man will be ashamed of this one when he arrives in his glory and that of the Father and of the holy angels. 27 But I tell YOU truthfully, There are some of those standing here that will not taste death at all until first they see the kingdom of God.”

28 In actual fact, about eight days after these words, he took Peter and John and James along and climbed up into the mountain to pray. 29 And as he was praying the appearance of his face became different and his apparel became glitteringly white. 30 Also, look! two men were conversing with him, who were Moses and E·li′jah. 31 These appeared with glory and began talking about his departure that he was destined to fulfill at Jerusalem. 32 Now Peter and those with him were weighed down with sleep; but when they got fully awake they saw his glory and the two men standing with him. 33 And as these were being separated from him, Peter said to Jesus: “Instructor, it is fine for us to be here, so let us erect three tents, one for you and one for Moses and one for E·li′jah,” he not realizing what he was saying. 34 But as he was saying these things a cloud formed and began to overshadow them. As they entered into the cloud, they became fearful. 35 And a voice came out of the cloud, saying: “This is my Son, the one that has been chosen. Listen to him.” 36 And as the voice occurred Jesus was found alone. But they kept quiet and did not report to anyone in those days any of the things they saw.

37 On the succeeding day, when they got down from the mountain, a great crowd met him. 38 And, look! a man cried out from the crowd, saying: “Teacher, I beg you to take a look at my son, because he is my only-begotten, 39 and, look! a spirit takes him, and suddenly he cries out, and it throws him into convulsions with foam, and it scarcely withdraws from him after bruising him. 40 And I begged your disciples to expel it, but they could not.” 41 In response Jesus said: “O faithless and twisted generation, how long must I continue with YOU and put up with YOU? Lead your son over here.” 42 But even as he was approaching, the demon dashed him to the ground and violently convulsed him. However, Jesus rebuked the unclean spirit and healed the boy and delivered him to his father. 43 Well, they all began to be astounded at the majestic power of God.

Now as they were all marveling at all the things he was doing, he said to his disciples: 44 “Give lodgment to these words in YOUR ears, for the Son of man is destined to be delivered into the hands of men.” 45 But they continued without understanding of this saying. In fact, it was concealed from them that they might not see through it, and they were afraid to question him about this saying.

46 Then a reasoning entered among them as to who would be the greatest of them. 47 Jesus, knowing the reasoning of their hearts, took a young child, set it beside him 48 and said to them: “Whoever receives this young child on the basis of my name receives me too, and whoever receives me receives him also that sent me forth. For he that conducts himself as a lesser one among all of YOU is the one that is great.”

49 In response John said: “Instructor, we saw a certain man expelling demons by the use of your name and we tried to prevent him, because he is not following with us.” 50 But Jesus said to him: “Do not YOU men try to prevent him, for he that is not against YOU is for YOU.”

51 As the days were now coming to the full for him to be taken up, he firmly set his face to go to Jerusalem. 52 So he sent forth messengers in advance of him. And they went their way and entered into a village of Sa·mar′i·tans, to make preparation for him; 53 but they did not receive him, because his face was set for going to Jerusalem. 54 When the disciples James and John saw this they said: “Lord, do you want us to tell fire to come down from heaven and annihilate them?” 55 But he turned and rebuked them. 56 So they went to a different village.

57 Now as they were going on the road, someone said to him: “I will follow you to wherever you may depart.” 58 And Jesus said to him: “Foxes have dens and birds of heaven have roosts, but the Son of man has nowhere to lay down his head.” 59 Then he said to another: “Be my follower.” The man said: “Permit me first to leave and bury my father.” 60 But he said to him: “Let the dead bury their dead, but you go away and declare abroad the kingdom of God.” 61 And still another said: “I will follow you, Lord; but first permit me to say good-bye to those in my household.” 62 Jesus said to him: “No man that has put his hand to a plow and looks at the things behind is well fitted for the kingdom of God.”

Luke

10 After these things the Lord designated seventy others and sent them forth by twos in advance of him into every city and place to which he himself was going to come. 2 Then he began to say to them: “The harvest, indeed, is great, but the workers are few. Therefore beg the Master of the harvest to send out workers into his harvest. 3 Go forth. Look! I am sending YOU forth as lambs in among wolves. 4 Do not carry a purse, nor a food pouch, nor sandals, and do not embrace anybody in greeting along the road. 5 Wherever YOU enter into a house say first, ‘May this house have peace.’ 6 And if a friend of peace is there, YOUR peace will rest upon him. But if there is not, it will turn back to YOU. 7 So stay in that house, eating and drinking the things they provide, for the worker is worthy of his wages. Do not be transferring from house to house.

8 “Also, wherever YOU enter into a city and they receive YOU, eat the things set before YOU, 9 and cure the sick ones in it, and go on telling them, ‘The kingdom of God has come near to YOU.’ 10 But wherever YOU enter into a city and they do not receive YOU, go out into its broad ways and say, 11 ‘Even the dust that got stuck to our feet from YOUR city we wipe off against YOU. Nevertheless, keep this in mind, that the kingdom of God has come near.’ 12 I tell YOU that it will be more endurable for Sod′om in that day than for that city.

13 “Woe to you, Cho·ra′zin! Woe to you, Beth·sa′i·da! because if the powerful works that have taken place in YOU had taken place in Tyre and Si′don, they would long ago have repented sitting in sackcloth and ashes. 14 Consequently it will be more endurable for Tyre and Si′don in the judgment than for YOU. 15 And you, Ca·per′na·um, will you perhaps be exalted to heaven? Down to Ha′des you will come!

16 “He that listens to YOU listens to me too. And he that disregards YOU disregards me too. Moreover, he that disregards me disregards also him that sent me forth.”

17 Then the seventy returned with joy, saying: “Lord, even the demons are made subject to us by the use of your name.” 18 At that he said to them: “I began to behold Satan already fallen like lightning from heaven. 19 Look! I have given YOU the authority to trample underfoot serpents and scorpions, and over all the power of the enemy, and nothing will by any means do YOU hurt. 20 Nevertheless, do not rejoice over this, that the spirits are made subject to YOU, but rejoice because YOUR names have been inscribed in the heavens.” 21 In that very hour he became overjoyed in the holy spirit and said: “I publicly praise you, Father, Lord of heaven and earth, because you have carefully hidden these things from wise and intellectual ones, and have revealed them to babes. Yes, O Father, because to do thus came to be the way approved by you. 22 All things have been delivered to me by my Father, and who the Son is no one knows but the Father; and who the Father is, no one knows but the Son, and he to whom the Son is willing to reveal him.”

23 With that he turned to the disciples by themselves and said: “Happy are the eyes that behold the things YOU are beholding. 24 For I say to YOU, Many prophets and kings desired to see the things YOU are beholding but did not see them, and to hear the things YOU are hearing but did not hear them.”

25 Now, look! a certain man versed in the Law rose up, to test him out, and said: “Teacher, by doing what shall I inherit everlasting life?” 26 He said to him: “What is written in the Law? How do you read?” 27 In answer he said: “‘You must love Jehovah your God with your whole heart and with your whole soul and with your whole strength and with your whole mind,’ and, ‘your neighbor as yourself.’” 28 He said to him: “You answered correctly; ‘keep on doing this and you will get life.’”

29 But, wanting to prove himself righteous, the man said to Jesus: “Who really is my neighbor?” 30 In reply Jesus said: “A certain man was going down from Jerusalem to Jer′i·cho and fell among robbers, who both stripped him and inflicted blows, and went off, leaving him half-dead. 31 Now, by coincidence, a certain priest was going down over that road, but, when he saw him, he went by on the opposite side. 32 Likewise, a Levite also, when he got down to the place and saw him, went by on the opposite side. 33 But a certain Sa·mar′i·tan traveling the road came upon him and, at seeing him, he was moved with pity. 34 So he approached him and bound up his wounds, pouring oil and wine upon them. Then he mounted him upon his own beast and brought him to an inn and took care of him. 35 And the next day he took out two de·nar′i·i, gave them to the innkeeper, and said, ‘Take care of him, and whatever you spend besides this, I will repay you when I come back here.’ 36 Who of these three seems to you to have made himself neighbor to the man that fell among the robbers?” 37 He said: “The one that acted mercifully toward him.” Jesus then said to him: “Go your way and be doing the same yourself.”

38 Now as they were going their way he entered into a certain village. Here a certain woman named Martha received him as guest into the house. 39 This woman also had a sister called Mary, who, however, sat down at the feet of the Lord and kept listening to his word. 40 Martha, on the other hand, was distracted with attending to many duties. So, she came near and said: “Lord, does it not matter to you that my sister has left me alone to attend to things? Tell her, therefore, to join in helping me.” 41 In answer the Lord said to her: “Martha, Martha, you are anxious and disturbed about many things. 42 A few things, though, are needed, or just one. For her part, Mary chose the good portion, and it will not be taken away from her.”

Luke

13 At that very season there were certain ones present that reported to him about the Gal·i·le′ans whose blood Pilate had mixed with their sacrifices. 2 So in reply he said to them: “Do YOU imagine that these Gal·i·le′ans were proved worse sinners than all other Gal·i·le′ans because they have suffered these things? 3 No, indeed, I tell YOU; but, unless YOU repent, YOU will all likewise be destroyed. 4 Or those eighteen upon whom the tower in Si·lo′am fell, thereby killing them, do YOU imagine that they were proved greater debtors than all other men inhabiting Jerusalem? 5 No, indeed, I tell YOU; but, unless YOU repent, YOU will all be destroyed in the same way.”

6 Then he went on to tell this illustration: “A certain man had a fig tree planted in his vineyard, and he came looking for fruit on it, but found none. 7 Then he said to the vinedresser, ‘Here it is three years that I have come looking for fruit on this fig tree, but have found none. Cut it down! Why really should it keep the ground useless?’ 8 In reply he said to him, ‘Master, let it alone also this year, until I dig around it and put on manure; 9 and if then it produces fruit in the future, well and good; but if not, you shall cut it down.’”

10 Now he was teaching in one of the synagogues on the sabbath. 11 And, look! a woman with a spirit of weakness for eighteen years, and she was bent double and was unable to raise herself up at all. 12 When he saw her, Jesus addressed her and said to her: “Woman, you are released from your weakness.” 13 And he laid his hands on her; and instantly she straightened up, and began to glorify God. 14 But in response the presiding officer of the synagogue, indignant because Jesus did the cure on the sabbath, began to say to the crowd: “There are six days on which work ought to be done; on them, therefore, come and be cured, and not on the sabbath day.” 15 However, the Lord answered him and said: “Hypocrites, does not each one of YOU on the sabbath untie his bull or his ass from the stall and lead it away to give it drink? 16 Was it not due, then, for this woman who is a daughter of Abraham, and whom Satan held bound, look! eighteen years, to be loosed from this bond on the sabbath day?” 17 Well, when he said these things, all his opposers began to feel shame; but all the crowd began to rejoice at all the glorious things done by him.

18 Therefore he went on to say: “What is the kingdom of God like, and with what shall I compare it? 19 It is like a mustard grain that a man took and put in his garden, and it grew and became a tree, and the birds of heaven took up lodging in its branches.”

20 And again he said: “With what shall I compare the kingdom of God? 21 It is like leaven, which a woman took and hid in three large measures of flour until the whole mass was fermented.”

22 And he journeyed through from city to city and from village to village, teaching and continuing on his journey to Jerusalem. 23 Now a certain man said to him: “Lord, are those who are being saved few?” He said to them: 24 “Exert yourselves vigorously to get in through the narrow door, because many, I tell YOU, will seek to get in but will not be able, 25 when once the householder has got up and locked the door, and YOU start to stand outside and to knock at the door, saying, ‘Sir, open to us.’ But in answer he will say to YOU, ‘I do not know where YOU are from.’ 26 Then YOU will start saying, ‘We ate and drank in front of you, and you taught in our broad ways.’ 27 But he will speak and say to YOU, ‘I do not know where YOU are from. Get away from me, all YOU workers of unrighteousness!’ 28 There is where YOUR weeping and the gnashing of YOUR teeth will be, when YOU see Abraham and Isaac and Jacob and all the prophets in the kingdom of God, but yourselves thrown outside. 29 Furthermore, people will come from eastern parts and western, and from north and south, and will recline at the table in the kingdom of God. 30 And, look! there are those last who will be first, and there are those first who will be last.”

31 In that very hour certain Pharisees came up, saying to him: “Get out and be on your way from here, because Herod wants to kill you.” 32 And he said to them: “Go and tell that fox, ‘Look! I am casting out demons and accomplishing healing today and tomorrow, and the third day I shall be finished.’ 33 Nevertheless, I must go on my way today and tomorrow and the following day, because it is not admissible for a prophet to be destroyed outside of Jerusalem. 34 Jerusalem, Jerusalem, the killer of the prophets and stoner of those sent forth to her—how often I wanted to gather your children together in the manner that a hen gathers her brood of chicks under her wings, but YOU people did not want it! 35 Look! YOUR house is abandoned to YOU. I tell YOU, YOU will by no means see me until YOU say, ‘Blessed is he that comes in Jehovah’s name!’”

Luke

15 Now all the tax collectors and the sinners kept drawing near to him to hear him. 2 Consequently both the Pharisees and the scribes kept muttering, saying: “This man welcomes sinners and eats with them.” 3 Then he spoke this illustration to them, saying: 4 “What man of YOU with a hundred sheep, on losing one of them, will not leave the ninety-nine behind in the wilderness and go for the lost one until he finds it? 5 And when he has found it he puts it upon his shoulders and rejoices. 6 And when he gets home he calls his friends and his neighbors together, saying to them, ‘Rejoice with me, because I have found my sheep that was lost.’ 7 I tell YOU that thus there will be more joy in heaven over one sinner that repents than over ninety-nine righteous ones who have no need of repentance.

8 “Or what woman with ten drachma coins, if she loses one drachma coin, does not light a lamp and sweep her house and search carefully until she finds it? 9 And when she has found it she calls the women who are her friends and neighbors together, saying, ‘Rejoice with me, because I have found the drachma coin that I lost.’ 10 Thus, I tell YOU, joy arises among the angels of God over one sinner that repents.”

11 Then he said: “A certain man had two sons. 12 And the younger of them said to his father, ‘Father, give me the part of the property that falls to my share.’ Then he divided his means of living to them. 13 Later, after not many days, the younger son gathered all things together and traveled abroad into a distant country, and there squandered his property by living a debauched life. 14 When he had spent everything, a severe famine occurred throughout that country, and he started to be in need. 15 He even went and attached himself to one of the citizens of that country, and he sent him into his fields to herd swine. 16 And he used to desire to be filled with the carob pods which the swine were eating, and no one would give him anything.

17 “When he came to his senses, he said, ‘How many hired men of my father are abounding with bread, while I am perishing here from famine! 18 I will rise and journey to my father and say to him: “Father, I have sinned against heaven and against you. 19 I am no longer worthy of being called your son. Make me as one of your hired men.”’ 20 So he rose and went to his father. While he was yet a long way off, his father caught sight of him and was moved with pity, and he ran and fell upon his neck and tenderly kissed him. 21 Then the son said to him, ‘Father, I have sinned against heaven and against you. I am no longer worthy of being called your son. Make me as one of your hired men.’ 22 But the father said to his slaves, ‘Quick! bring out a robe, the best one, and clothe him with it, and put a ring on his hand and sandals on his feet. 23 And bring the fattened young bull, slaughter it and let us eat and enjoy ourselves, 24 because this my son was dead and came to life again; he was lost and was found.’ And they started to enjoy themselves.

25 “Now his older son was in the field; and as he came and got near the house he heard a music concert and dancing. 26 So he called one of the servants to him and inquired what these things meant. 27 He said to him, ‘Your brother has come, and your father slaughtered the fattened young bull, because he got him back in good health.’ 28 But he became wrathful and was unwilling to go in. Then his father came out and began to entreat him. 29 In reply he said to his father, ‘Here it is so many years I have slaved for you and never once did I transgress your commandment, and yet to me you never once gave a kid for me to enjoy myself with my friends. 30 But as soon as this your son who ate up your means of living with harlots arrived, you slaughtered the fattened young bull for him.’ 31 Then he said to him, ‘Child, you have always been with me, and all the things that are mine are yours; 32 but we just had to enjoy ourselves and rejoice, because this your brother was dead and came to life, and he was lost and was found.’”

Luke

19 And he entered Jer′i·cho and was going through. 2 Now here there was a man called by the name Zac·chae′us; and he was a chief tax collector, and he was rich. 3 Well, he was seeking to see who this Jesus was, but he could not for the crowd, because he was small in size. 4 So he ran ahead to an advance position and climbed a fig-mulberry tree in order to see him, because he was about to go through that way. 5 Now when Jesus got to the place, he looked up and said to him: “Zac·chae′us, hurry and get down, for today I must stay in your house.” 6 With that he hurried and got down and with rejoicing he received him as guest. 7 But when they saw it, they all fell to muttering, saying: “With a man that is a sinner he went in to lodge.” 8 But Zac·chae′us stood up and said to the Lord: “Look! The half of my belongings, Lord, I am giving to the poor, and whatever I extorted from anyone by false accusation I am restoring fourfold.” 9 At this Jesus said to him: “This day salvation has come to this house, because he also is a son of Abraham. 10 For the Son of man came to seek and to save what was lost.”

11 While they were listening to these things he spoke in addition an illustration, because he was near Jerusalem and they were imagining that the kingdom of God was going to display itself instantly. 12 Therefore he said: “A certain man of noble birth traveled to a distant land to secure kingly power for himself and to return. 13 Calling ten slaves of his he gave them ten mi′nas and told them, ‘Do business till I come.’ 14 But his citizens hated him and sent out a body of ambassadors after him, to say, ‘We do not want this man to become king over us.’

15 “Eventually when he got back after having secured the kingly power, he commanded to be called to him these slaves to whom he had given the silver money, in order to ascertain what they had gained by business activity. 16 Then the first one presented himself, saying, ‘Lord, your mi′na gained ten mi′nas.’ 17 So he said to him, ‘Well done, good slave! Because in a very small matter you have proved yourself faithful, hold authority over ten cities.’ 18 Now the second came, saying, ‘Your mi′na, Lord, made five mi′nas.’ 19 He said to this one also, ‘You, too, be in charge of five cities.’ 20 But a different one came, saying, ‘Lord, here is your mi′na, that I kept laid away in a cloth. 21 You see, I was in fear of you, because you are a harsh man; you take up what you did not deposit and you reap what you did not sow.’ 22 He said to him, ‘Out of your own mouth I judge you, wicked slave. You knew, did you, that I am a harsh man, taking up what I did not deposit and reaping what I did not sow? 23 Hence why is it you did not put my silver money in a bank? Then on my arrival I would have collected it with interest.’

24 “With that he said to those standing by, ‘Take the mi′na from him and give it to him that has the ten mi′nas.’ 25 But they said to him, ‘Lord, he has ten mi′nas!’— 26 ‘I say to YOU, To everyone that has, more will be given; but from the one that does not have, even what he has will be taken away. 27 Moreover, these enemies of mine that did not want me to become king over them BRING here and slaughter them before me.’”

28 So, after he had said these things, he began to go on ahead, going up to Jerusalem. 29 And when he got near to Beth′pha·ge and Beth′a·ny at the mountain called Mount of Olives, he sent forth two of the disciples, 30 saying: “Go into the village that is within sight of YOU, and in it after YOU pass in YOU will find a colt tied, on which none of mankind ever sat. Loose it and bring it. 31 But if anyone asks YOU, ‘Why is it YOU are loosing it?’ YOU must speak in this way, ‘The Lord needs it.’” 32 So those who were sent forth departed and found it just as he said to them. 33 But as they were loosing the colt the owners of it said to them: “Why are YOU loosing the colt?” 34 They said: “The Lord needs it.” 35 And they led it to Jesus, and they threw their outer garments upon the colt and set Jesus upon it.

36 As he moved along they kept spreading their outer garments on the road. 37 As soon as he got near the road down the Mount of Olives all the multitude of the disciples started to rejoice and praise God with a loud voice concerning all the powerful works they had seen, 38 saying: “Blessed is the One coming as the King in Jehovah’s name! Peace in heaven, and glory in the highest places!” 39 However, some of the Pharisees from the crowd said to him: “Teacher, rebuke your disciples.” 40 But in reply he said: “I tell YOU, If these remained silent, the stones would cry out.”

41 And when he got nearby, he viewed the city and wept over it, 42 saying: “If you, even you, had discerned in this day the things having to do with peace—but now they have been hid from your eyes. 43 Because the days will come upon you when your enemies will build around you a fortification with pointed stakes and will encircle you and distress you from every side, 44 and they will dash you and your children within you to the ground, and they will not leave a stone upon a stone in you, because you did not discern the time of your being inspected.”

45 And he entered into the temple and started to throw out those who were selling, 46 saying to them: “It is written, ‘And my house will be a house of prayer,’ but YOU made it a cave of robbers.”

47 Furthermore, he went teaching daily in the temple. But the chief priests and the scribes and the principal ones of the people were seeking to destroy him; 48 and yet they did not find the effective thing for them to do, for the people one and all kept hanging onto him to hear him.

Luke

20 On one of the days while he was teaching the people in the temple and declaring the good news, the chief priests and the scribes with the older men came near, 2 and they spoke up, saying to him: “Tell us by what authority you do these things, or who it is that gave you this authority.” 3 In reply he said to them: “I will also ask YOU a question, and YOU tell me: 4 Was the baptism of John from heaven or from men?” 5 Then among themselves they drew conclusions, saying: “If we say, ‘From heaven,’ he will say, ‘Why is it YOU did not believe him?’ 6 But if we say, ‘From men,’ the people one and all will stone us, for they are persuaded that John was a prophet.” 7 So they replied that they did not know its source. 8 And Jesus said to them: “Neither am I telling YOU by what authority I do these things.”

9 Then he started to tell the people this illustration: “A man planted a vineyard and let it out to cultivators, and he traveled abroad for considerable time. 10 But in due season he sent out a slave to the cultivators, that they might give him some of the fruit of the vineyard. The cultivators, however, sent him away empty, after beating him up. 11 But he repeated and sent them a different slave. That one also they beat up and dishonored and sent away empty. 12 Yet again he sent a third; this one also they wounded and threw out. 13 At this the owner of the vineyard said, ‘What shall I do? I will send my son the beloved. Likely they will respect this one.’ 14 When the cultivators caught sight of him they went reasoning with one another, saying, ‘This is the heir; let us kill him, that the inheritance may become ours.’ 15 With that they threw him outside the vineyard and killed him. What, therefore, will the owner of the vineyard do to them? 16 He will come and destroy these cultivators and will give the vineyard to others.”

On hearing this they said: “Never may that happen!” 17 But he looked upon them and said: “What, then, does this that is written mean, ‘The stone which the builders rejected, this has become the chief cornerstone’? 18 Everyone falling upon that stone will be shattered. As for anyone upon whom it falls, it will pulverize him.”

19 The scribes and the chief priests now sought to get their hands on him in that very hour, but they feared the people; for they perceived that he spoke this illustration with them in mind. 20 And, after observing him closely, they sent out men secretly hired to pretend that they were righteous, in order that they might catch him in speech, so as to turn him over to the government and to the authority of the governor. 21 And they questioned him, saying: “Teacher, we know you speak and teach correctly and show no partiality, but you teach the way of God in line with truth: 22 Is it lawful for us to pay tax to Caesar or not?” 23 But he detected their cunning and said to them: 24 “Show me a de·nar′i·us. Whose image and inscription does it have?” They said: “Caesar’s.” 25 He said to them: “By all means, then, pay back Caesar’s things to Caesar, but God’s things to God.” 26 Well, they were not able to catch him in this saying before the people, but, in amazement at his answer, they said nothing.

27 However, some of the Sadducees, those who say there is no resurrection, came up and questioned him, 28 saying: “Teacher, Moses wrote us, ‘If a man’s brother dies having a wife, but this one remained childless, his brother should take the wife and raise up offspring from her for his brother.’ 29 Accordingly there were seven brothers; and the first took a wife and died childless. 30 So the second, 31 and the third took her. Likewise even the seven: they did not leave children behind, but died off. 32 Lastly, the woman also died. 33 Consequently, in the resurrection, of which one of them does she become the wife? For the seven got her as wife.”

34 Jesus said to them: “The children of this system of things marry and are given in marriage, 35 but those who have been counted worthy of gaining that system of things and the resurrection from the dead neither marry nor are given in marriage. 36 In fact, neither can they die anymore, for they are like the angels, and they are God’s children by being children of the resurrection. 37 But that the dead are raised up even Moses disclosed, in the account about the thornbush, when he calls Jehovah ‘the God of Abraham and God of Isaac and God of Jacob.’ 38 He is a God, not of the dead, but of the living, for they are all living to him.” 39 In response some of the scribes said: “Teacher, you spoke well.” 40 For no longer did they have the courage to ask him a single question.

41 In turn he said to them: “How is it they say that the Christ is David’s son? 42 For David himself says in the book of Psalms, ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand 43 until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”’ 44 David, therefore, calls him ‘Lord’; so how is he his son?”

45 Then, while all the people were listening he said to the disciples: 46 “Look out for the scribes who desire to walk around in robes and like greetings in the marketplaces and front seats in the synagogues and most prominent places at evening meals, 47 and who devour the houses of the widows and for a pretext make long prayers. These will receive a heavier judgment.”

Luke

23 So the multitude of them rose, one and all, and led him to Pilate. 2 Then they started to accuse him, saying: “This man we found subverting our nation and forbidding the paying of taxes to Caesar and saying he himself is Christ a king.” 3 Now Pilate asked him the question: “Are you the king of the Jews?” In answer to him he said: “You yourself are saying it.” 4 Then Pilate said to the chief priests and the crowds: “I find no crime in this man.” 5 But they began to be insistent, saying: “He stirs up the people by teaching throughout all Ju·de′a, even starting out from Gal′i·lee to here.” 6 On hearing that, Pilate asked whether the man was a Gal·i·le′an, 7 and, after ascertaining that he was from the jurisdiction of Herod, he sent him on to Herod, who was also himself in Jerusalem in these days.

8 When Herod saw Jesus he rejoiced greatly, for over a considerable time he was wanting to see him because of having heard about him, and he was hoping to see some sign performed by him. 9 Now he began to question him with a good many words; but he made him no answer. 10 However, the chief priests and the scribes kept standing up and vehemently accusing him. 11 Then Herod together with his soldier guards discredited him, and he made fun of him by clothing him with a bright garment and sent him back to Pilate. 12 Both Herod and Pilate now became friends with each other on that very day; for before that they had continued at enmity between themselves.

13 Pilate then called the chief priests and the rulers and the people together 14 and said to them: “YOU brought this man to me as one inciting the people to revolt, and, look! I examined him in front of YOU but found in this man no ground for the charges YOU are bringing against him. 15 In fact, neither did Herod, for he sent him back to us; and, look! nothing deserving of death has been committed by him. 16 I will therefore chastise him and release him.” 17 —— 18 But with their whole multitude they cried out, saying: “Take this one away, but release Bar·ab′bas to us!” 19 (Which man had been thrown into prison for a certain sedition occurring in the city and for murder.) 20 Again Pilate called out to them, because he wanted to release Jesus. 21 Then they began to yell, saying: “Impale! Impale him!” 22 The third time he said to them: “Why, what bad thing did this man do? I found nothing deserving of death in him; I will therefore chastise and release him.” 23 At this they began to be urgent, with loud voices, demanding that he be impaled; and their voices began to win out. 24 So Pilate gave sentence for their demand to be met: 25 he released the man that had been thrown into prison for sedition and murder and whom they were demanding, but he surrendered Jesus to their will.

26 Now as they led him away, they laid hold of Simon, a certain native of Cy·re′ne, coming from the country, and they placed the torture stake upon him to bear it behind Jesus. 27 But there was following him a great multitude of the people and of women who kept beating themselves in grief and bewailing him. 28 Jesus turned to the women and said: “Daughters of Jerusalem, stop weeping for me. On the contrary, weep for yourselves and for YOUR children; 29 because, look! days are coming in which people will say, ‘Happy are the barren women, and the wombs that did not give birth and the breasts that did not nurse!’ 30 Then they will start to say to the mountains, ‘Fall over us!’ and to the hills, ‘Cover us over!’ 31 Because if they do these things when the tree is moist, what will occur when it is withered?”

32 But two other men, evildoers, were also being led to be executed with him. 33 And when they got to the place called Skull, there they impaled him and the evildoers, one on his right and one on his left. 34 [[But Jesus was saying: “Father, forgive them, for they do not know what they are doing.”]] Furthermore, to distribute his garments, they cast lots. 35 And the people stood looking on. But the rulers were sneering, saying: “Others he saved; let him save himself, if this one is the Christ of God, the Chosen One.” 36 Even the soldiers made fun of him, coming close and offering him sour wine 37 and saying: “If you are the king of the Jews, save yourself.” 38 There was also an inscription over him: “This is the king of the Jews.”

39 But one of the hung evildoers began to say abusively to him: “You are the Christ, are you not? Save yourself and us.” 40 In reply the other rebuked him and said: “Do you not fear God at all, now that you are in the same judgment? 41 And we, indeed, justly so, for we are receiving in full what we deserve for things we did; but this man did nothing out of the way.” 42 And he went on to say: “Jesus, remember me when you get into your kingdom.” 43 And he said to him: “Truly I tell you today, You will be with me in Paradise.”

44 Well, by now it was about the sixth hour, and yet a darkness fell over all the earth until the ninth hour, 45 because the sunlight failed; then the curtain of the sanctuary was rent down the middle. 46 And Jesus called with a loud voice and said: “Father, into your hands I entrust my spirit.” When he had said this, he expired. 47 Because of seeing what occurred the army officer began to glorify God, saying: “Really this man was righteous.” 48 And all the crowds that were gathered together there for this spectacle, when they beheld the things that occurred, began to return, beating their breasts. 49 Moreover, all those acquainted with him were standing at a distance. Also, women, who together had followed him from Gal′i·lee, were standing beholding these things.

50 And, look! a man named Joseph, who was a member of the Council, a good and righteous man— 51 this man had not voted in support of their design and action—he was from Ar·i·ma·the′a, a city of the Ju·de′ans, and was waiting for the kingdom of God; 52 this man went to Pilate and asked for the body of Jesus. 53 And he took it down and wrapped it up in fine linen, and he laid him in a tomb carved in the rock, in which no man had yet lain. 54 Now it was the day of Preparation, and the evening light of the sabbath was approaching. 55 But the women, who had come with him out of Gal′i·lee, followed along and took a look at the memorial tomb and how his body was laid; 56 and they went back to prepare spices and perfumed oils. But, of course, they rested on the sabbath according to the commandment.

According to John

1 In the beginning the Word was, and the Word was with God, and the Word was a god. 2 This one was in the beginning with God. 3 All things came into existence through him, and apart from him not even one thing came into existence.

What has come into existence 4 by means of him was life, and the life was the light of men. 5 And the light is shining in the darkness, but the darkness has not overpowered it.

6 There arose a man that was sent forth as a representative of God: his name was John. 7 This man came for a witness, in order to bear witness about the light, that people of all sorts might believe through him. 8 He was not that light, but he was meant to bear witness about that light.

9 The true light that gives light to every sort of man was about to come into the world. 10 He was in the world, and the world came into existence through him, but the world did not know him. 11 He came to his own home, but his own people did not take him in. 12 However, as many as did receive him, to them he gave authority to become God’s children, because they were exercising faith in his name; 13 and they were born, not from blood or from a fleshly will or from man’s will, but from God.

14 So the Word became flesh and resided among us, and we had a view of his glory, a glory such as belongs to an only-begotten son from a father; and he was full of undeserved kindness and truth. 15 (John bore witness about him, yes, he actually cried out—this was the one who said it—saying: “The one coming behind me has advanced in front of me, because he existed before me.”) 16 For we all received from out of his fullness, even undeserved kindness upon undeserved kindness. 17 Because the Law was given through Moses, the undeserved kindness and the truth came to be through Jesus Christ. 18 No man has seen God at any time; the only-begotten god who is in the bosom position with the Father is the one that has explained him.

19 Now this is the witness of John when the Jews sent forth priests and Levites from Jerusalem to him to ask him: “Who are you?” 20 And he confessed and did not deny, but confessed: “I am not the Christ.” 21 And they asked him: “What, then? Are you E·li′jah?” And he said: “I am not.” “Are you The Prophet?” And he answered: “No!” 22 Therefore they said to him: “Who are you? that we may give an answer to those who sent us. What do you say about yourself?” 23 He said: “I am a voice of someone crying out in the wilderness, ‘MAKE the way of Jehovah straight,’ just as Isaiah the prophet said.” 24 Now those sent forth were from the Pharisees. 25 So they questioned him and said to him: “Why, then, do you baptize if you yourself are not the Christ or E·li′jah or The Prophet?” 26 John answered them, saying: “I baptize in water. In the midst of YOU one is standing whom YOU do not know, 27 the one coming behind me, but the lace of whose sandal I am not worthy to untie.” 28 These things took place in Beth′a·ny across the Jordan, where John was baptizing.

29 The next day he beheld Jesus coming toward him, and he said: “See, the Lamb of God that takes away the sin of the world! 30 This is the one about whom I said, Behind me there comes a man who has advanced in front of me, because he existed before me. 31 Even I did not know him, but the reason why I came baptizing in water was that he might be made manifest to Israel.” 32 John also bore witness, saying: “I viewed the spirit coming down as a dove out of heaven, and it remained upon him. 33 Even I did not know him, but the very One who sent me to baptize in water said to me, ‘Whoever it is upon whom you see the spirit coming down and remaining, this is the one that baptizes in holy spirit.’ 34 And I have seen it, and I have borne witness that this one is the Son of God.”

35 Again the next day John was standing with two of his disciples, 36 and as he looked at Jesus walking he said: “See, the Lamb of God!” 37 And the two disciples heard him speak, and they followed Jesus. 38 Then Jesus turned and, getting a view of them following, he said to them: “What are YOU looking for?” They said to him: “Rabbi, (which means, when translated, Teacher,) where are you staying?” 39 He said to them: “Come, and YOU will see.” Accordingly they went and saw where he was staying, and they stayed with him that day; it was about the tenth hour. 40 Andrew the brother of Simon Peter was one of the two that heard what John said and followed Jesus. 41 First this one found his own brother, Simon, and said to him: “We have found the Mes·si′ah” (which means, when translated, Christ). 42 He led him to Jesus. When Jesus looked upon him he said: “You are Simon the son of John; you will be called Ce′phas” (which is translated Peter).

43 The next day he desired to depart for Gal′i·lee. So Jesus found Philip and said to him: “Be my follower.” 44 Now Philip was from Beth·sa′i·da, from the city of Andrew and Peter. 45 Philip found Na·than′a·el and said to him: “We have found the one of whom Moses, in the Law, and the Prophets wrote, Jesus, the son of Joseph, from Naz′a·reth.” 46 But Na·than′a·el said to him: “Can anything good come out of Naz′a·reth?” Philip said to him: “Come and see.” 47 Jesus saw Na·than′a·el coming toward him and said about him: “See, an Israelite for a certainty, in whom there is no deceit.” 48 Na·than′a·el said to him: “How does it come that you know me?” Jesus in answer said to him: “Before Philip called you, while you were under the fig tree, I saw you.” 49 Na·than′a·el answered him: “Rabbi, you are the Son of God, you are King of Israel.” 50 Jesus in answer said to him: “Because I told you I saw you underneath the fig tree do you believe? You will see things greater than these.” 51 He further said to him: “Most truly I say to YOU men, YOU will see heaven opened up and the angels of God ascending and descending to the Son of man.”

John

2 Now on the third day a marriage feast took place in Ca′na of Gal′i·lee, and the mother of Jesus was there. 2 Jesus and his disciples were also invited to the marriage feast.

3 When the wine ran short the mother of Jesus said to him: “They have no wine.” 4 But Jesus said to her: “What have I to do with you, woman? My hour has not yet come.” 5 His mother said to those ministering: “Whatever he tells YOU, do.” 6 As it was, there were six stone water jars sitting there as required by the purification rules of the Jews, each able to hold two or three liquid measures. 7 Jesus said to them: “Fill the water jars with water.” And they filled them to the brim. 8 And he said to them: “Draw some out now and take it to the director of the feast.” So they took it. 9 When, now, the director of the feast tasted the water that had been turned into wine but did not know what its source was, although those ministering who had drawn out the water knew, the director of the feast called the bridegroom 10 and said to him: “Every other man puts out the fine wine first, and when people are intoxicated, the inferior. You have reserved the fine wine until now.” 11 Jesus performed this in Ca′na of Gal′i·lee as the beginning of his signs, and he made his glory manifest; and his disciples put their faith in him.

12 After this he and his mother and brothers and his disciples went down to Ca·per′na·um, but they did not stay there many days.

13 Now the passover of the Jews was near, and Jesus went up to Jerusalem. 14 And he found in the temple those selling cattle and sheep and doves and the money brokers in their seats. 15 So, after making a whip of ropes, he drove all those with the sheep and cattle out of the temple, and he poured out the coins of the money changers and overturned their tables. 16 And he said to those selling the doves: “Take these things away from here! Stop making the house of my Father a house of merchandise!” 17 His disciples called to mind that it is written: “The zeal for your house will eat me up.”

18 Therefore, in answer, the Jews said to him: “What sign have you to show us, since you are doing these things?” 19 In answer Jesus said to them: “Break down this temple, and in three days I will raise it up.” 20 Therefore the Jews said: “This temple was built in forty-six years, and will you raise it up in three days?” 21 But he was talking about the temple of his body. 22 When, though, he was raised up from the dead, his disciples called to mind that he used to say this; and they believed the Scripture and the saying that Jesus said.

23 However, when he was in Jerusalem at the passover, at its festival, many people put their faith in his name, viewing his signs that he was performing. 24 But Jesus himself was not entrusting himself to them because of his knowing them all 25 and because he was in no need to have anyone bear witness about man, for he himself knew what was in man.

John

10 “Most truly I say to YOU, He that does not enter into the sheepfold through the door but climbs up some other place, that one is a thief and a plunderer. 2 But he that enters through the door is shepherd of the sheep. 3 The doorkeeper opens to this one, and the sheep listen to his voice, and he calls his own sheep by name and leads them out. 4 When he has got all his own out, he goes before them, and the sheep follow him, because they know his voice. 5 A stranger they will by no means follow but will flee from him, because they do not know the voice of strangers.” 6 Jesus spoke this comparison to them; but they did not know what the things meant that he was speaking to them.

7 Therefore Jesus said again: “Most truly I say to YOU, I am the door of the sheep. 8 All those that have come in place of me are thieves and plunderers; but the sheep have not listened to them. 9 I am the door; whoever enters through me will be saved, and he will go in and out and find pasturage. 10 The thief does not come unless it is to steal and slay and destroy. I have come that they might have life and might have it in abundance. 11 I am the fine shepherd; the fine shepherd surrenders his soul in behalf of the sheep. 12 The hired man, who is no shepherd and to whom the sheep do not belong as his own, beholds the wolf coming and abandons the sheep and flees—and the wolf snatches them and scatters them— 13 because he is a hired man and does not care for the sheep. 14 I am the fine shepherd, and I know my sheep and my sheep know me, 15 just as the Father knows me and I know the Father; and I surrender my soul in behalf of the sheep.

16 “And I have other sheep, which are not of this fold; those also I must bring, and they will listen to my voice, and they will become one flock, one shepherd. 17 This is why the Father loves me, because I surrender my soul, in order that I may receive it again. 18 No man has taken it away from me, but I surrender it of my own initiative. I have authority to surrender it, and I have authority to receive it again. The commandment on this I received from my Father.”

19 Again a division resulted among the Jews because of these words. 20 Many of them were saying: “He has a demon and is mad. Why do YOU listen to him?” 21 Others would say: “These are not the sayings of a demonized man. A demon cannot open blind people’s eyes, can it?”

22 At that time the festival of dedication took place in Jerusalem. It was wintertime, 23 and Jesus was walking in the temple in the colonnade of Sol′o·mon. 24 Therefore the Jews encircled him and began to say to him: “How long are you to keep our souls in suspense? If you are the Christ, tell us outspokenly.” 25 Jesus answered them: “I told YOU, and yet YOU do not believe. The works that I am doing in the name of my Father, these bear witness about me. 26 But YOU do not believe, because YOU are none of my sheep. 27 My sheep listen to my voice, and I know them, and they follow me. 28 And I give them everlasting life, and they will by no means ever be destroyed, and no one will snatch them out of my hand. 29 What my Father has given me is something greater than all other things, and no one can snatch them out of the hand of the Father. 30 I and the Father are one.”

31 Once more the Jews lifted up stones to stone him. 32 Jesus replied to them: “I displayed to YOU many fine works from the Father. For which of those works are YOU stoning me?” 33 The Jews answered him: “We are stoning you, not for a fine work, but for blasphemy, even because you, although being a man, make yourself a god.” 34 Jesus answered them: “Is it not written in YOUR Law, ‘I said: “YOU are gods”’? 35 If he called ‘gods’ those against whom the word of God came, and yet the Scripture cannot be nullified, 36 do YOU say to me whom the Father sanctified and dispatched into the world, ‘You blaspheme,’ because I said, I am God’s Son? 37 If I am not doing the works of my Father, do not believe me. 38 But if I am doing them, even though YOU do not believe me, believe the works, in order that YOU may come to know and may continue knowing that the Father is in union with me and I am in union with the Father.” 39 Therefore they tried again to seize him; but he got out of their reach.

40 So he went off again across the Jordan to the place where John was baptizing at first, and he stayed there. 41 And many people came to him, and they began saying: “John, indeed, did not perform a single sign, but as many things as John said about this man were all true.” 42 And many put faith in him there.

John

13 Now, because he knew before the festival of the passover that his hour had come for him to move out of this world to the Father, Jesus, having loved his own that were in the world, loved them to the end. 2 So, while the evening meal was going on, the Devil having already put it into the heart of Judas Is·car′i·ot, the son of Simon, to betray him, 3 he, knowing that the Father had given all things into his hands and that he came forth from God and was going to God, 4 got up from the evening meal and laid aside his outer garments. And, taking a towel, he girded himself. 5 After that he put water into a basin and started to wash the feet of the disciples and to dry them off with the towel with which he was girded. 6 And so he came to Simon Peter. He said to him: “Lord, are you washing my feet?” 7 In answer Jesus said to him: “What I am doing you do not understand at present, but you will understand after these things.” 8 Peter said to him: “You will certainly never wash my feet.” Jesus answered him: “Unless I wash you, you have no part with me.” 9 Simon Peter said to him: “Lord, not my feet only, but also my hands and my head.” 10 Jesus said to him: “He that has bathed does not need to have more than his feet washed, but is wholly clean. And YOU men are clean, but not all.” 11 He knew, indeed, the man betraying him. This is why he said: “Not all of YOU are clean.”

12 When, now, he had washed their feet and had put his outer garments on and laid himself down at the table again, he said to them: “Do YOU know what I have done to YOU? 13 YOU address me, ‘Teacher,’ and, ‘Lord,’ and YOU speak rightly, for I am such. 14 Therefore, if I, although Lord and Teacher, washed YOUR feet, YOU also ought to wash the feet of one another. 15 For I set the pattern for YOU, that, just as I did to YOU, YOU should do also. 16 Most truly I say to YOU, A slave is not greater than his master, nor is one that is sent forth greater than the one that sent him. 17 If YOU know these things, happy YOU are if YOU do them. 18 I am not talking about all of YOU; I know the ones I have chosen. But it is in order that the Scripture might be fulfilled, ‘He that used to feed on my bread has lifted up his heel against me.’ 19 From this moment on I am telling YOU before it occurs, in order that when it does occur YOU may believe that I am he. 20 Most truly I say to YOU, He that receives anyone I send receives me also. In turn he that receives me, receives also him that sent me.”

21 After saying these things, Jesus became troubled in spirit, and he bore witness and said: “Most truly I say to YOU, One of YOU will betray me.” 22 The disciples began to look at one another, being at a loss as to which one he was saying it about. 23 There was reclining in front of Jesus’ bosom one of his disciples, and Jesus loved him. 24 Therefore Simon Peter nodded to this one and said to him: “Tell who it is about whom he is saying it.” 25 So the latter leaned back upon the breast of Jesus and said to him: “Lord, who is it?” 26 Therefore Jesus answered: “It is that one to whom I shall give the morsel that I dip.” And so, having dipped the morsel, he took and gave it to Judas, the son of Simon Is·car′i·ot. 27 And after the morsel then Satan entered into the latter. Jesus, therefore, said to him: “What you are doing get done more quickly.” 28 However, none of those reclining at the table knew for what purpose he said this to him. 29 Some, in fact, were imagining, since Judas was holding the money box, that Jesus was telling him: “Buy what things we need for the festival,” or that he should give something to the poor. 30 Therefore, after he received the morsel, he went out immediately. And it was night.

31 Hence when he had gone out, Jesus said: “Now the Son of man is glorified, and God is glorified in connection with him. 32 And God will himself glorify him, and he will glorify him immediately. 33 Little children, I am with YOU a little longer. YOU will look for me; and just as I said to the Jews, ‘Where I go YOU cannot come,’ I say also to YOU at present. 34 I am giving YOU a new commandment, that YOU love one another; just as I have loved YOU, that YOU also love one another. 35 By this all will know that YOU are my disciples, if YOU have love among yourselves.”

36 Simon Peter said to him: “Lord, where are you going?” Jesus answered: “Where I am going you cannot follow me now, but you will follow afterwards.” 37 Peter said to him: “Lord, why is it I cannot follow you at present? I will surrender my soul in your behalf.” 38 Jesus answered: “Will you surrender your soul in my behalf? Most truly I say to you, A cock will by no means crow until you have disowned me three times.”

John

19 At that time, therefore, Pilate took Jesus and scourged him. 2 And the soldiers braided a crown of thorns and put it on his head and arrayed him with a purple outer garment; 3 and they began coming up to him and saying: “Good day, you King of the Jews!” Also, they would give him slaps in the face. 4 And Pilate went outside again and said to them: “See! I bring him outside to YOU in order for YOU to know I find no fault in him.” 5 Accordingly Jesus came outside, wearing the thorny crown and the purple outer garment. And he said to them: “Look! The man!” 6 However, when the chief priests and the officers saw him, they shouted, saying: “Impale him! Impale him!” Pilate said to them: “Take him yourselves and impale him, for I do not find any fault in him.” 7 The Jews answered him: “We have a law, and according to the law he ought to die, because he made himself God’s son.”

8 When, therefore, Pilate heard this saying, he became more fearful; 9 and he entered into the governor’s palace again and said to Jesus: “Where are you from?” But Jesus gave him no answer. 10 Hence Pilate said to him: “Are you not speaking to me? Do you not know I have authority to release you and I have authority to impale you?” 11 Jesus answered him: “You would have no authority at all against me unless it had been granted to you from above. This is why the man that handed me over to you has greater sin.”

12 For this reason Pilate kept on seeking how to release him. But the Jews shouted, saying: “If you release this man, you are not a friend of Caesar. Every man making himself a king speaks against Caesar.” 13 Therefore Pilate, after hearing these words, brought Jesus outside, and he sat down on a judgment seat in a place called The Stone Pavement, but, in Hebrew, Gab′ba·tha. 14 Now it was preparation of the passover; it was about the sixth hour. And he said to the Jews: “See! YOUR king!” 15 However, they shouted: “Take him away! Take him away! Impale him!” Pilate said to them: “Shall I impale YOUR king?” The chief priests answered: “We have no king but Caesar.” 16 At that time, therefore, he handed him over to them to be impaled.

Then they took charge of Jesus. 17 And, bearing the torture stake for himself, he went out to the so-called Skull Place, which is called Gol′go·tha in Hebrew; 18 and there they impaled him, and two other men with him, one on this side and one on that, but Jesus in the middle. 19 Pilate wrote a title also and put it on the torture stake. It was written: “Jesus the Naz·a·rene′ the King of the Jews.” 20 Therefore many of the Jews read this title, because the place where Jesus was impaled was near the city; and it was written in Hebrew, in Latin, in Greek. 21 However, the chief priests of the Jews began to say to Pilate: “Do not write ‘The King of the Jews,’ but that he said, ‘I am King of the Jews.’” 22 Pilate answered: “What I have written I have written.”

23 Now when the soldiers had impaled Jesus, they took his outer garments and made four parts, for each soldier a part, and the inner garment. But the inner garment was without a seam, being woven from the top throughout its length. 24 Therefore they said to one another: “Let us not tear it, but let us determine by lots over it whose it will be.” This was that the scripture might be fulfilled: “They apportioned my outer garments among themselves, and upon my apparel they cast lots.” And so the soldiers really did these things.

25 By the torture stake of Jesus, however, there were standing his mother and the sister of his mother; Mary the wife of Clo′pas, and Mary Mag′da·lene. 26 Therefore Jesus, seeing his mother and the disciple whom he loved standing by, said to his mother: “Woman, see! Your son!” 27 Next he said to the disciple: “See! Your mother!” And from that hour on the disciple took her to his own home.

28 After this, when Jesus knew that by now all things had been accomplished, in order that the scripture might be accomplished he said: “I am thirsty.” 29 A vessel was sitting there full of sour wine. Therefore they put a sponge full of the sour wine upon a hyssop stalk and brought it to his mouth. 30 When, now, he had received the sour wine, Jesus said: “It has been accomplished!” and, bowing his head, he delivered up his spirit.

31 Then the Jews, since it was Preparation, in order that the bodies might not remain upon the torture stakes on the Sabbath, (for the day of that Sabbath was a great one,) requested Pilate to have their legs broken and the bodies taken away. 32 The soldiers came, therefore, and broke the legs of the first man and those of the other man that had been impaled with him. 33 But on coming to Jesus, as they saw that he was already dead, they did not break his legs. 34 Yet one of the soldiers jabbed his side with a spear, and immediately blood and water came out. 35 And he that has seen it has borne witness, and his witness is true, and that man knows he tells true things, in order that YOU also may believe. 36 In fact, these things took place in order for the scripture to be fulfilled: “Not a bone of his will be crushed.” 37 And, again, a different scripture says: “They will look to the One whom they pierced.”

38 Now after these things Joseph from Ar·i·ma·the′a, who was a disciple of Jesus but a secret one out of his fear of the Jews, requested Pilate that he might take away the body of Jesus; and Pilate gave him permission. Therefore he came and took his body away. 39 Nic·o·de′mus also, the man that came to him in the night the first time, came bringing a roll of myrrh and aloes, about a hundred pounds of it. 40 So they took the body of Jesus and bound it up with bandages with the spices, just the way the Jews have the custom of preparing for burial. 41 Incidentally, at the place where he was impaled there was a garden, and in the garden a new memorial tomb, in which no one had ever yet been laid. 42 There, then, on account of the preparation of the Jews, they laid Jesus, because the memorial tomb was nearby.

John

20 On the first day of the week Mary Mag′da·lene came to the memorial tomb early, while there was still darkness, and she beheld the stone already taken away from the memorial tomb. 2 Therefore she ran and came to Simon Peter and to the other disciple, for whom Jesus had affection, and she said to them: “They have taken away the Lord out of the memorial tomb, and we do not know where they have laid him.”

3 Then Peter and the other disciple went out and started for the memorial tomb. 4 Yes, the two together began to run; but the other disciple ran ahead of Peter with greater speed and reached the memorial tomb first. 5 And, stooping forward, he beheld the bandages lying, yet he did not go in. 6 Then Simon Peter also came following him, and he entered into the memorial tomb. And he viewed the bandages lying, 7 also the cloth that had been upon his head not lying with the bandages but separately rolled up in one place. 8 At that time, therefore, the other disciple who had reached the memorial tomb first also went in, and he saw and believed. 9 For they did not yet discern the scripture that he must rise from the dead. 10 And so the disciples went back to their homes.

11 Mary, however, kept standing outside near the memorial tomb, weeping. Then, while she was weeping, she stooped forward to look into the memorial tomb 12 and she viewed two angels in white sitting one at the head and one at the feet where the body of Jesus had been lying. 13 And they said to her: “Woman, why are you weeping?” She said to them: “They have taken my Lord away, and I do not know where they have laid him.” 14 After saying these things, she turned back and viewed Jesus standing, but she did not discern it was Jesus. 15 Jesus said to her: “Woman, why are you weeping? Whom are you looking for?” She, imagining it was the gardener, said to him: “Sir, if you have carried him off, tell me where you have laid him, and I will take him away.” 16 Jesus said to her: “Mary!” Upon turning around, she said to him, in Hebrew: “Rab·bo′ni!” (which means “Teacher!”) 17 Jesus said to her: “Stop clinging to me. For I have not yet ascended to the Father. But be on your way to my brothers and say to them, ‘I am ascending to my Father and YOUR Father and to my God and YOUR God.’” 18 Mary Mag′da·lene came and brought the news to the disciples: “I have seen the Lord!” and that he said these things to her.

19 Therefore, when it was late on that day, the first of the week, and, although the doors were locked where the disciples were for fear of the Jews, Jesus came and stood in their midst and said to them: “May YOU have peace.” 20 And after he said this he showed them both his hands and his side. Then the disciples rejoiced at seeing the Lord. 21 Jesus, therefore, said to them again: “May YOU have peace. Just as the Father has sent me forth, I also am sending YOU.” 22 And after he said this he blew upon them and said to them: “Receive holy spirit. 23 If YOU forgive the sins of any persons, they stand forgiven to them; if YOU retain those of any persons, they stand retained.”

24 But Thomas, one of the twelve, who was called The Twin, was not with them when Jesus came. 25 Consequently the other disciples would say to him: “We have seen the Lord!” But he said to them: “Unless I see in his hands the print of the nails and stick my finger into the print of the nails and stick my hand into his side, I will certainly not believe.”

26 Well, eight days later his disciples were again indoors, and Thomas with them. Jesus came, although the doors were locked, and he stood in their midst and said: “May YOU have peace.” 27 Next he said to Thomas: “Put your finger here, and see my hands, and take your hand and stick it into my side, and stop being unbelieving but become believing.” 28 In answer Thomas said to him: “My Lord and my God!” 29 Jesus said to him: “Because you have seen me have you believed? Happy are those who do not see and yet believe.”

30 To be sure, Jesus performed many other signs also before the disciples, which are not written down in this scroll. 31 But these have been written down that YOU may believe that Jesus is the Christ the Son of God, and that, because of believing, YOU may have life by means of his name.

John

21 After these things Jesus manifested himself again to the disciples at the sea of Ti·be′ri·as; but he made the manifestation in this way. 2 There were in company Simon Peter and Thomas, who was called The Twin, and Na·than′a·el from Ca′na of Gal′i·lee and the sons of Zeb′e·dee and two others of his disciples. 3 Simon Peter said to them: “I am going fishing.” They said to him: “We also are coming with you.” Out they went and got aboard the boat, but during that night they caught nothing.

4 However, just as it was getting to be morning, Jesus stood on the beach, but the disciples did not, of course, discern that it was Jesus. 5 Then Jesus said to them: “Young children, YOU do not have anything to eat, do YOU?” They answered “No!” to him. 6 He said to them: “Cast the net on the right side of the boat and YOU will find some.” Then they cast it, but they were no longer able to draw it in because of the multitude of the fishes. 7 Therefore that disciple whom Jesus used to love said to Peter: “It is the Lord!” Hence Simon Peter, upon hearing that it was the Lord, girded about himself his top garment, for he was naked, and plunged into the sea. 8 But the other disciples came in the little boat, for they were not a long way from land, only about three hundred feet away, dragging the net of fishes.

9 However, when they disembarked onto land they beheld lying there a charcoal fire and fish lying upon it and bread. 10 Jesus said to them: “Bring some of the fish YOU just now caught.” 11 Simon Peter, therefore, went on board and drew the net to land full of big fishes, one hundred and fifty-three of them. But although there were so many the net did not burst. 12 Jesus said to them: “Come, take YOUR breakfast.” Not one of the disciples had the courage to inquire of him: “Who are you?” because they knew it was the Lord. 13 Jesus came and took the bread and gave it to them, and the fish likewise. 14 This was now the third time that Jesus appeared to the disciples after his being raised up from the dead.

15 When, now, they had breakfasted, Jesus said to Simon Peter: “Simon son of John, do you love me more than these?” He said to him: “Yes, Lord, you know I have affection for you.” He said to him: “Feed my lambs.” 16 Again he said to him, a second time: “Simon son of John, do you love me?” He said to him: “Yes, Lord, you know I have affection for you.” He said to him: “Shepherd my little sheep.” 17 He said to him the third time: “Simon son of John, do you have affection for me?” Peter became grieved that he said to him the third time: “Do you have affection for me?” So he said to him: “Lord, you know all things; you are aware that I have affection for you.” Jesus said to him: “Feed my little sheep. 18 Most truly I say to you, When you were younger, you used to gird yourself and walk about where you wanted. But when you grow old you will stretch out your hands and another man will gird you and bear you where you do not wish.” 19 This he said to signify by what sort of death he would glorify God. So, when he had said this, he said to him: “Continue following me.”

20 Upon turning about Peter saw the disciple whom Jesus used to love following, the one who at the evening meal had also leaned back upon his breast and said: “Lord, who is the one betraying you?” 21 Accordingly, when he caught sight of him, Peter said to Jesus: “Lord, what will this man do?” 22 Jesus said to him: “If it is my will for him to remain until I come, of what concern is that to you? You continue following me.” 23 In consequence, this saying went out among the brothers, that that disciple would not die. However, Jesus did not say to him that he would not die, but: “If it is my will for him to remain until I come, of what concern is that to you?”

24 This is the disciple that bears witness about these things and that wrote these things, and we know that the witness he gives is true.

25 There are, in fact, many other things also which Jesus did, which, if ever they were written in full detail, I suppose, the world itself could not contain the scrolls written.

Acts

2 Now while the day of the festival of Pentecost was in progress they were all together at the same place, 2 and suddenly there occurred from heaven a noise just like that of a rushing stiff breeze, and it filled the whole house in which they were sitting. 3 And tongues as if of fire became visible to them and were distributed about, and one sat upon each one of them, 4 and they all became filled with holy spirit and started to speak with different tongues, just as the spirit was granting them to make utterance.

5 As it was, there were dwelling in Jerusalem Jews, reverent men, from every nation of those under heaven. 6 So, when this sound occurred, the multitude came together and were bewildered, because each one heard them speaking in his own language. 7 Indeed, they were astonished and began to wonder and say: “See here, all these who are speaking are Gal·i·le′ans, are they not? 8 And yet how is it we are hearing, each one of us, his own language in which we were born? 9 Par′thi·ans and Medes and E′lam·ites, and the inhabitants of Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a, and Ju·de′a and Cap·pa·do′ci·a, Pon′tus and the district of Asia, 10 and Phryg′i·a and Pam·phyl′i·a, Egypt and the parts of Lib′y·a, which is toward Cy·re′ne, and sojourners from Rome, both Jews and proselytes, 11 Cre′tans and Arabians, we hear them speaking in our tongues about the magnificent things of God.” 12 Yes, they were all astonished and were in perplexity, saying one to another: “What does this thing purport to be?” 13 However, different ones mocked at them and began to say: “They are full of sweet wine.”

14 But Peter stood up with the eleven and raised his voice and made this utterance to them: “Men of Ju·de′a and all YOU inhabitants of Jerusalem, let this be known to YOU and give ear to my sayings. 15 These people are, in fact, not drunk, as YOU suppose, for it is the third hour of the day. 16 On the contrary, this is what was said through the prophet Joel, 17 ‘“And in the last days,” God says, “I shall pour out some of my spirit upon every sort of flesh, and YOUR sons and YOUR daughters will prophesy and YOUR young men will see visions and YOUR old men will dream dreams; 18 and even upon my men slaves and upon my women slaves I will pour out some of my spirit in those days, and they will prophesy. 19 And I will give portents in heaven above and signs on earth below, blood and fire and smoke mist; 20 the sun will be turned into darkness and the moon into blood before the great and illustrious day of Jehovah arrives. 21 And everyone who calls on the name of Jehovah will be saved.”’

22 “Men of Israel, hear these words: Jesus the Naz·a·rene′, a man publicly shown by God to YOU through powerful works and portents and signs that God did through him in YOUR midst, just as YOU yourselves know, 23 this man, as one delivered up by the determined counsel and foreknowledge of God, YOU fastened to a stake by the hand of lawless men and did away with. 24 But God resurrected him by loosing the pangs of death, because it was not possible for him to continue to be held fast by it. 25 For David says respecting him, ‘I had Jehovah constantly before my eyes; because he is at my right hand that I may never be shaken. 26 On this account my heart became cheerful and my tongue rejoiced greatly. Moreover, even my flesh will reside in hope; 27 because you will not leave my soul in Ha′des, neither will you allow your loyal one to see corruption. 28 You have made life’s ways known to me, you will fill me with good cheer with your face.’

29 “Men, brothers, it is allowable to speak with freeness of speech to YOU concerning the family head David, that he both deceased and was buried and his tomb is among us to this day. 30 Therefore, because he was a prophet and knew that God had sworn to him with an oath that he would seat one from the fruitage of his loins upon his throne, 31 he saw beforehand and spoke concerning the resurrection of the Christ, that neither was he forsaken in Ha′des nor did his flesh see corruption. 32 This Jesus God resurrected, of which fact we are all witnesses. 33 Therefore because he was exalted to the right hand of God and received the promised holy spirit from the Father, he has poured out this which YOU see and hear. 34 Actually David did not ascend to the heavens, but he himself says, ‘Jehovah said to my Lord: “Sit at my right hand, 35 until I place your enemies as a stool for your feet.”’ 36 Therefore let all the house of Israel know for a certainty that God made him both Lord and Christ, this Jesus whom YOU impaled.”

37 Now when they heard this they were stabbed to the heart, and they said to Peter and the rest of the apostles: “Men, brothers, what shall we do?” 38 Peter said to them: “Repent, and let each one of YOU be baptized in the name of Jesus Christ for forgiveness of YOUR sins, and YOU will receive the free gift of the holy spirit. 39 For the promise is to YOU and to YOUR children and to all those afar off, just as many as Jehovah our God may call to him.” 40 And with many other words he bore thorough witness and kept exhorting them, saying: “Get saved from this crooked generation.” 41 Therefore those who embraced his word heartily were baptized, and on that day about three thousand souls were added. 42 And they continued devoting themselves to the teaching of the apostles and to sharing with one another, to taking of meals and to prayers.

43 Indeed, fear began to fall upon every soul, and many portents and signs began to occur through the apostles. 44 All those who became believers were together in having all things in common, 45 and they went selling their possessions and properties and distributing the proceeds to all, just as anyone would have the need. 46 And day after day they were in constant attendance at the temple with one accord, and they took their meals in private homes and partook of food with great rejoicing and sincerity of heart, 47 praising God and finding favor with all the people. At the same time Jehovah continued to join to them daily those being saved.

Acts

7 But the high priest said: “Are these things so?” 2 He said: “Men, brothers and fathers, hear. The God of glory appeared to our forefather Abraham while he was in Mes·o·po·ta′mi·a, before he took up residence in Ha′ran, 3 and he said to him, ‘Go out from your land and from your relatives and come on into the land I shall show you.’ 4 Then he went out from the land of the Chal·de′ans and took up residence in Ha′ran. And from there, after his father died, God caused him to change his residence to this land in which YOU now dwell. 5 And yet he did not give him any inheritable possession in it, no, not a footbreadth; but he promised to give it to him as a possession, and after him to his seed, while as yet he had no child. 6 Moreover, God spoke to this effect, that his seed would be alien residents in a foreign land and the people would enslave them and afflict them for four hundred years. 7 ‘And that nation for which they will slave I shall judge,’ God said, ‘and after these things they will come out and will render sacred service to me in this place.’

8 “He also gave him a covenant of circumcision; and thus he became the father of Isaac and circumcised him on the eighth day, and Isaac of Jacob, and Jacob of the twelve family heads. 9 And the family heads became jealous of Joseph and sold him into Egypt. But God was with him, 10 and he delivered him out of all his tribulations and gave him graciousness and wisdom in the sight of Phar′aoh king of Egypt. And he appointed him to govern Egypt and his whole house. 11 But a famine came upon the whole of Egypt and Ca′naan, even a great tribulation; and our forefathers were not finding any provisions. 12 But Jacob heard there were foodstuffs in Egypt and he sent our forefathers out the first time. 13 And during the second time Joseph was made known to his brothers; and the family stock of Joseph became manifest to Phar′aoh. 14 So Joseph sent out and called Jacob his father and all his relatives from that place, to the number of seventy-five souls. 15 Jacob went down into Egypt. And he deceased; and so did our forefathers, 16 and they were transferred to She′chem and were laid in the tomb that Abraham had bought for a price with silver money from the sons of Ha′mor in She′chem.

17 “Just as the time was approaching for fulfillment of the promise that God had openly declared to Abraham, the people grew and multiplied in Egypt, 18 until there rose a different king over Egypt, who did not know of Joseph. 19 This one used statecraft against our race and wrongfully forced the fathers to expose their infants, that they might not be preserved alive. 20 In that particular time Moses was born, and he was divinely beautiful. And he was nursed three months in his father’s home. 21 But when he was exposed, the daughter of Phar′aoh picked him up and brought him up as her own son. 22 Consequently Moses was instructed in all the wisdom of the Egyptians. In fact, he was powerful in his words and deeds.

23 “Now when the time of his fortieth year was being fulfilled, it came into his heart to make an inspection of his brothers, the sons of Israel. 24 And when he caught sight of a certain one being unjustly treated, he defended him and executed vengeance for the one being abused by striking the Egyptian down. 25 He was supposing his brothers would grasp that God was giving them salvation by his hand, but they did not grasp it. 26 And the next day he appeared to them as they were fighting, and he tried to bring them together again in peace, saying, ‘Men, YOU are brothers. Why do YOU treat each other unjustly?’ 27 But the one that was treating his neighbor unjustly thrust him away, saying, ‘Who appointed you ruler and judge over us? 28 You do not want to do away with me in the same manner that you did away with the Egyptian yesterday, do you?’ 29 At this speech Moses took to flight and became an alien resident in the land of Mid′i·an, where he became the father of two sons.

30 “And when forty years were fulfilled, there appeared to him in the wilderness of Mount Si′nai an angel in the fiery flame of a thornbush. 31 Now when Moses saw it he marveled at the sight. But as he was approaching to investigate, Jehovah’s voice came, 32 ‘I am the God of your forefathers, the God of Abraham and of Isaac and of Jacob.’ Seized with trembling, Moses did not dare to investigate further. 33 Jehovah said to him, ‘Take the sandals off your feet, for the place on which you are standing is holy ground. 34 I have certainly seen the wrongful treatment of my people who are in Egypt, and I have heard their groaning and I have come down to deliver them. And now come, I will send you off to Egypt.’ 35 This Moses, whom they disowned, saying, ‘Who appointed you ruler and judge?’ this man God sent off as both ruler and deliverer by the hand of the angel that appeared to him in the thornbush. 36 This man led them out after doing portents and signs in Egypt and in the Red Sea and in the wilderness for forty years.

37 “This is the Moses that said to the sons of Israel, ‘God will raise up for YOU from among YOUR brothers a prophet like me.’ 38 This is he that came to be among the congregation in the wilderness with the angel that spoke to him on Mount Si′nai and with our forefathers, and he received living sacred pronouncements to give YOU. 39 To him our forefathers refused to become obedient, but they thrust him aside and in their hearts they turned back to Egypt, 40 saying to Aaron, ‘Make gods for us to go ahead of us. For this Moses, who led us out of the land of Egypt, we do not know what has happened to him.’ 41 So they made a calf in those days and brought up a sacrifice to the idol and began to enjoy themselves in the works of their hands. 42 So God turned and handed them over to render sacred service to the army of heaven, just as it is written in the book of the prophets, ‘It was not to me that YOU offered victims and sacrifices for forty years in the wilderness, was it, O house of Israel? 43 But it was the tent of Mo′loch and the star of the god Re′phan that YOU took up, the figures which YOU made to worship them. Consequently I will deport YOU beyond Babylon.’

44 “Our forefathers had the tent of the witness in the wilderness, just as he gave orders when speaking to Moses to make it according to the pattern he had seen. 45 And our forefathers who succeeded to it also brought it in with Joshua into the land possessed by the nations, whom God thrust out from before our forefathers. Here it remained until the days of David. 46 He found favor in the sight of God and asked for the privilege of providing a habitation for the God of Jacob. 47 However, Sol′o·mon built a house for him. 48 Nevertheless, the Most High does not dwell in houses made with hands; just as the prophet says, 49 ‘The heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool. What sort of house will YOU build for me? Jehovah says. Or what is the place for my resting? 50 My hand made all these things, did it not?’

51 “Obstinate men and uncircumcised in hearts and ears, YOU are always resisting the holy spirit; as YOUR forefathers did, so YOU do. 52 Which one of the prophets did YOUR forefathers not persecute? Yes, they killed those who made announcement in advance concerning the coming of the righteous One, whose betrayers and murderers YOU have now become, 53 YOU who received the Law as transmitted by angels but have not kept it.”

54 Well, at hearing these things they felt cut to their hearts and began to gnash their teeth at him. 55 But he, being full of holy spirit, gazed into heaven and caught sight of God’s glory and of Jesus standing at God’s right hand, 56 and he said: “Look! I behold the heavens opened up and the Son of man standing at God’s right hand.” 57 At this they cried out at the top of the voice and put their hands over their ears and rushed upon him with one accord. 58 And after throwing him outside the city, they began casting stones at him. And the witnesses laid down their outer garments at the feet of a young man called Saul. 59 And they went on casting stones at Stephen as he made appeal and said: “Lord Jesus, receive my spirit.” 60 Then, bending his knees, he cried out with a strong voice: “Jehovah, do not charge this sin against them.” And after saying this he fell asleep in death.

Acts

8 Saul, for his part, was approving of the murder of him.

On that day great persecution arose against the congregation that was in Jerusalem; all except the apostles were scattered throughout the regions of Ju·de′a and Sa·mar′i·a. 2 But reverent men carried Stephen to the burial, and they made a great lamentation over him. 3 Saul, though, began to deal outrageously with the congregation. Invading one house after another and, dragging out both men and women, he would turn them over to prison.

4 However, those who had been scattered went through the land declaring the good news of the word. 5 Philip, for one, went down to the city of Sa·mar′i·a and began to preach the Christ to them. 6 With one accord the crowds were paying attention to the things said by Philip while they listened and looked at the signs he was performing. 7 For there were many that had unclean spirits, and these would cry out with a loud voice and come out. Moreover, many that were paralyzed and lame were cured. 8 So there came to be a great deal of joy in that city.

9 Now in the city there was a certain man named Simon, who, prior to this, had been practicing magical arts and amazing the nation of Sa·mar′i·a, saying he himself was somebody great. 10 And all of them, from the least to the greatest, would pay attention to him and say: “This man is the Power of God, which can be called Great.” 11 So they would pay attention to him because of his having amazed them for quite a while by his magical arts. 12 But when they believed Philip, who was declaring the good news of the kingdom of God and of the name of Jesus Christ, they proceeded to be baptized, both men and women. 13 Simon himself also became a believer, and, after being baptized, he was in constant attendance upon Philip; and he was amazed at beholding signs and great powerful works taking place.

14 When the apostles in Jerusalem heard that Sa·mar′i·a had accepted the word of God, they dispatched Peter and John to them; 15 and these went down and prayed for them to get holy spirit. 16 For it had not yet fallen upon any one of them, but they had only been baptized in the name of the Lord Jesus. 17 Then they went laying their hands upon them, and they began to receive holy spirit.

18 Now when Simon saw that through the laying on of the hands of the apostles the spirit was given, he offered them money, 19 saying: “Give me also this authority, that anyone upon whom I lay my hands may receive holy spirit.” 20 But Peter said to him: “May your silver perish with you, because you thought through money to get possession of the free gift of God. 21 You have neither part nor lot in this matter, for your heart is not straight in the sight of God. 22 Repent, therefore, of this badness of yours, and supplicate Jehovah that, if possible, the device of your heart may be forgiven you; 23 for I see you are a poisonous gall and a bond of unrighteousness.” 24 In answer Simon said: “YOU men, make supplication for me to Jehovah that none of the things YOU have said may come upon me.”

25 Therefore, when they had given the witness thoroughly and had spoken the word of Jehovah, they turned back to Jerusalem, and they went declaring the good news to many villages of the Sa·mar′i·tans.

26 However, Jehovah’s angel spoke to Philip, saying: “Rise and go to the south to the road that runs down from Jerusalem to Ga′za.” (This is a desert road.) 27 With that he rose and went, and, look! an E·thi·o′pi·an eunuch, a man in power under Can·da′ce queen of the E·thi·o′pi·ans, and who was over all her treasure. He had gone to Jerusalem to worship, 28 but he was returning and was sitting in his chariot and reading aloud the prophet Isaiah. 29 So the spirit said to Philip: “Approach and join yourself to this chariot.” 30 Philip ran alongside and heard him reading aloud Isaiah the prophet, and he said: “Do you actually know what you are reading?” 31 He said: “Really, how could I ever do so, unless someone guided me?” And he entreated Philip to get on and sit down with him. 32 Now the passage of Scripture that he was reading aloud was this: “As a sheep he was brought to the slaughter, and as a lamb that is voiceless before its shearer, so he does not open his mouth. 33 During his humiliation the judgment was taken away from him. Who will tell the details of his generation? Because his life is taken away from the earth.”

34 In answer the eunuch said to Philip: “I beg you, About whom does the prophet say this? About himself or about some other man?” 35 Philip opened his mouth and, starting with this Scripture, he declared to him the good news about Jesus. 36 Now as they were going over the road, they came to a certain body of water, and the eunuch said: “Look! A body of water; what prevents me from getting baptized?” 37 —— 38 With that he commanded the chariot to halt, and they both went down into the water, both Philip and the eunuch; and he baptized him. 39 When they had come up out of the water, Jehovah’s spirit quickly led Philip away, and the eunuch did not see him anymore, for he kept going on his way rejoicing. 40 But Philip was found to be in Ash′dod, and he went through the territory and kept on declaring the good news to all the cities until he got to Caes·a·re′a.

Acts

12 About that particular time Herod the king applied his hands to mistreating some of those of the congregation. 2 He did away with James the brother of John by the sword. 3 As he saw it was pleasing to the Jews, he went on to arrest Peter also. (As it was, those were days of the unfermented cakes.) 4 And laying hold of him, he put him in prison, turning him over to four shifts of four soldiers each to guard him, as he intended to produce him for the people after the passover. 5 Consequently Peter was being kept in the prison; but prayer to God for him was being carried on intensely by the congregation.

6 Now when Herod was about to produce him, that night Peter was sleeping bound with two chains between two soldiers, and guards before the door were keeping the prison. 7 But, look! Jehovah’s angel stood by, and a light shone in the prison cell. Striking Peter on the side, he roused him, saying: “Rise quickly!” And his chains fell off his hands. 8 The angel said to him: “Gird yourself and bind your sandals on.” He did so. Finally he said to him: “Put your outer garment on and keep following me.” 9 And he went out and kept following him, but he did not know that what was happening through the angel was real. In fact, he supposed he was seeing a vision. 10 Going through the first sentinel guard and the second they got to the iron gate leading into the city, and this opened to them of its own accord. And after they went out they advanced down one street, and immediately the angel departed from him. 11 And Peter, coming to himself, said: “Now I actually know that Jehovah sent his angel forth and delivered me out of Herod’s hand and from all that the people of the Jews were expecting.”

12 And after he considered it, he went to the house of Mary the mother of John who was surnamed Mark, where quite a few were gathered together and praying. 13 When he knocked at the door of the gateway, a servant girl named Rhoda came to attend to the call, 14 and, upon recognizing the voice of Peter, out of joy she did not open the gate, but ran inside and reported that Peter was standing before the gateway. 15 They said to her: “You are mad.” But she kept on strongly asserting it was so. They began to say: “It is his angel.” 16 But Peter remained there knocking. When they opened, they saw him and were astonished. 17 But he motioned to them with his hand to be silent and told them in detail how Jehovah brought him out of the prison, and he said: “Report these things to James and the brothers.” With that he went out and journeyed to another place.

18 Well, when it became day, there was no little stir among the soldiers over what really had become of Peter. 19 Herod made diligent search for him and, when not finding him, he examined the guards and commanded them to be led off to punishment; and he went down from Ju·de′a to Caes·a·re′a and spent some time there.

20 Now he was in a fighting mood against the people of Tyre and of Si′don. So with one accord they came to him and, after persuading Blastus, who was in charge of the bedchamber of the king, they began suing for peace, because their country was supplied with food from that of the king. 21 But on a set day Herod clothed himself with royal raiment and sat down upon the judgment seat and began giving them a public address. 22 In turn the assembled people began shouting: “A god’s voice, and not a man’s!” 23 Instantly the angel of Jehovah struck him, because he did not give the glory to God; and he became eaten up with worms and expired.

24 But the word of Jehovah went on growing and spreading.

25 As for Bar′na·bas and Saul, after having fully carried out the relief ministration in Jerusalem, they returned and took along with them John, the one surnamed Mark.

Acts

18 After these things he departed from Athens and came to Corinth. 2 And he found a certain Jew named Aq′ui·la, a native of Pon′tus who had recently come from Italy, and Pris·cil′la his wife, because of the fact that Claudius had ordered all the Jews to depart from Rome. So he went to them 3 and on account of being of the same trade he stayed at their home, and they worked, for they were tentmakers by trade. 4 However, he would give a talk in the synagogue every sabbath and would persuade Jews and Greeks.

5 When, now, both Silas and Timothy came down from Mac·e·do′ni·a, Paul began to be intensely occupied with the word, witnessing to the Jews to prove that Jesus is the Christ. 6 But after they kept on opposing and speaking abusively, he shook out his garments and said to them: “Let YOUR blood be upon YOUR own heads. I am clean. From now on I will go to people of the nations.” 7 Accordingly he transferred from there and went into the house of a man named Titius Justus, a worshiper of God, whose house was adjoining the synagogue. 8 But Cris′pus the presiding officer of the synagogue became a believer in the Lord, and so did all his household. And many of the Corinthians that heard began to believe and be baptized. 9 Moreover, by night the Lord said to Paul through a vision: “Have no fear, but keep on speaking and do not keep silent, 10 because I am with you and no man will assault you so as to do you injury; for I have many people in this city.” 11 So he stayed set there a year and six months, teaching among them the word of God.

12 Now while Gal′li·o was proconsul of A·cha′ia, the Jews rose up with one accord against Paul and led him to the judgment seat, 13 saying: “Contrary to the law this person leads men to another persuasion in worshiping God.” 14 But as Paul was going to open his mouth, Gal′li·o said to the Jews: “If it were, indeed, some wrong or a wicked act of villainy, O Jews, I would with reason put up patiently with YOU. 15 But if it is controversies over speech and names and the law among YOU, YOU yourselves must see to it. I do not wish to be a judge of these things.” 16 With that he drove them away from the judgment seat. 17 So they all laid hold of Sos′the·nes the presiding officer of the synagogue and went to beating him in front of the judgment seat. But Gal′li·o would not concern himself at all with these things.

18 However, after staying quite some days longer, Paul said good-bye to the brothers and proceeded to sail away for Syria, and with him Pris·cil′la and Aq′ui·la, as he had the hair of his head clipped short in Cen′chre·ae, for he had a vow. 19 So they arrived at Eph′e·sus, and he left them there; but he himself entered into the synagogue and reasoned with the Jews. 20 Although they kept requesting him to remain for a longer time, he would not consent 21 but said good-bye and told them: “I will return to YOU again, if Jehovah is willing.” And he put out to sea from Eph′e·sus 22 and came down to Caes·a·re′a. And he went up and greeted the congregation, and went down to Antioch.

23 And when he had passed some time there he departed and went from place to place through the country of Ga·la′ti·a and Phryg′i·a, strengthening all the disciples.

24 Now a certain Jew named A·pol′los, a native of Alexandria, an eloquent man, arrived in Eph′e·sus; and he was well versed in the Scriptures. 25 This man had been orally instructed in the way of Jehovah and, as he was aglow with the spirit, he went speaking and teaching with correctness the things about Jesus, but being acquainted with only the baptism of John. 26 And this man started to speak boldly in the synagogue. When Pris·cil′la and Aq′ui·la heard him, they took him into their company and expounded the way of God more correctly to him. 27 Further, because he was desiring to go across into A·cha′ia, the brothers wrote the disciples, exhorting them to receive him kindly. So when he got there, he greatly helped those who had believed on account of God’s undeserved kindness; 28 for with intensity he thoroughly proved the Jews to be wrong publicly, while he demonstrated by the Scriptures that Jesus was the Christ.

Acts

22 “Men, brothers and fathers, hear my defense to YOU now.” 2 (Well, when they heard he was addressing them in the Hebrew language, they kept all the more silent, and he said:) 3 “I am a Jew, born in Tarsus of Ci·li′cia, but educated in this city at the feet of Ga·ma′li·el, instructed according to the strictness of the ancestral Law, being zealous for God just as all of YOU are this day. 4 And I persecuted this Way to the death, binding and handing over to prisons both men and women, 5 as both the high priest and all the assembly of older men can bear me witness. From them I also procured letters to the brothers in Damascus, and I was on my way to bring also those who were there bound to Jerusalem to be punished.

6 “But as I was journeying and drawing close to Damascus, about midday, suddenly out of heaven a great light flashed all around me, 7 and I fell to the ground and heard a voice say to me, ‘Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me?’ 8 I answered, ‘Who are you, Lord?’ And he said to me, ‘I am Jesus the Naz·a·rene′, whom you are persecuting.’ 9 Now the men that were with me beheld, indeed, the light but did not hear the voice of the one speaking to me. 10 At that I said, ‘What shall I do, Lord?’ The Lord said to me, ‘Rise, go your way into Damascus, and there you will be told about everything it is appointed for you to do.’ 11 But as I could not see anything for the glory of that light, I arrived in Damascus, being led by the hand of those who were with me.

12 “Now An·a·ni′as, a certain man reverent according to the Law, well reported on by all the Jews dwelling there, 13 came to me and, standing by me, he said to me, ‘Saul, brother, have your sight again!’ And I looked up at him that very hour. 14 He said, ‘The God of our forefathers has chosen you to come to know his will and to see the righteous One and to hear the voice of his mouth, 15 because you are to be a witness for him to all men of things you have seen and heard. 16 And now why are you delaying? Rise, get baptized and wash your sins away by your calling upon his name.’

17 “But when I had returned to Jerusalem and was praying in the temple, I fell into a trance 18 and saw him saying to me, ‘Hurry up and get out of Jerusalem quickly, because they will not agree to your witness concerning me.’ 19 And I said, ‘Lord, they themselves well know that I used to imprison and flog in one synagogue after another those believing upon you; 20 and when the blood of Stephen your witness was being spilled, I myself was also standing by and approving and guarding the outer garments of those doing away with him.’ 21 And yet he said to me, ‘Get on your way, because I shall send you out to nations far off.’”

22 Now they kept listening to him down to this word, and they raised their voices, saying: “Take such a man away from the earth, for he was not fit to live!” 23 And because they were crying out and throwing their outer garments about and tossing dust into the air, 24 the military commander ordered him to be brought into the soldiers’ quarters and said he should be examined under scourging, that he might know fully for what cause they were shouting against him this way. 25 But when they had stretched him out for the whipping, Paul said to the army officer standing there: “Is it lawful for YOU men to scourge a man that is a Roman and uncondemned?” 26 Well, when the army officer heard this, he went to the military commander and made report, saying: “What are you intending to do? Why, this man is a Roman.” 27 So the military commander approached and said to him: “Tell me, Are you a Roman?” He said: “Yes.” 28 The military commander responded: “I purchased these rights as a citizen for a large sum of money.” Paul said: “But I was even born in them.”

29 Immediately, therefore, the men that were about to examine him with torture withdrew from him; and the military commander became afraid on ascertaining that he was a Roman and that he had bound him.

30 So, the next day, as he desired to know for sure just why he was being accused by the Jews, he let him loose and commanded the chief priests and all the San′he·drin to assemble. And he brought Paul down and stood him among them.

Acts

24 Five days later the high priest An·a·ni′as came down with some older men and a public speaker, a certain Ter·tul′lus, and they gave information to the governor against Paul. 2 When he was called, Ter·tul′lus started accusing him, saying:

“Seeing that we enjoy great peace through you and that reforms are taking place in this nation through your forethought, 3 at all times and also in all places we receive it, Your Excellency Felix, with the greatest thankfulness. 4 But that I may not hinder you any further, I beseech you to hear us briefly in your kindliness. 5 For we have found this man a pestilent fellow and stirring up seditions among all the Jews throughout the inhabited earth and a spearhead of the sect of the Naz·a·renes′, 6 one who also tried to profane the temple and whom we seized. 7 —— 8 From him you yourself can by examination find out about all these things of which we are accusing him.”

9 With that the Jews also joined in the attack, asserting that these things were so. 10 And Paul, when the governor nodded to him to speak, answered:

“Knowing well that this nation has had you as judge for many years, I readily speak in my defense the things about myself, 11 as you are in a position to find out that for me it has not been more than twelve days since I went up to worship in Jerusalem; 12 and they found me neither in the temple arguing with anyone nor causing a mob to rush together, either in the synagogues or throughout the city. 13 Nor can they prove to you the things of which they are accusing me right now. 14 But I do admit this to you, that, according to the way that they call a ‘sect,’ in this manner I am rendering sacred service to the God of my forefathers, as I believe all the things set forth in the Law and written in the Prophets; 15 and I have hope toward God, which hope these men themselves also entertain, that there is going to be a resurrection of both the righteous and the unrighteous. 16 In this respect, indeed, I am exercising myself continually to have a consciousness of committing no offense against God and men. 17 So after quite a number of years I arrived to bring gifts of mercy to my nation, and offerings. 18 While I was at these matters they found me ceremonially cleansed in the temple, but not with a crowd or with a tumult. But there were certain Jews from the district of Asia, 19 who ought to be present before you and to accuse me if they might have anything against me. 20 Or, let the men here say for themselves what wrong they found as I stood before the San′he·drin, 21 except with respect to this one utterance which I cried out while standing among them, ‘Over the resurrection of the dead I am today being judged before YOU!’”

22 However, Felix, knowing quite accurately the matters concerning this Way, began to put the men off and said: “Whenever Lys′i·as the military commander comes down, I shall decide upon these matters involving YOU.” 23 And he ordered the army officer that the man be kept and have some relaxation of custody, and that he forbid no one of his people to wait upon him.

24 Some days later Felix arrived with Dru·sil′la his wife, who was a Jewess, and he sent for Paul and listened to him on the belief in Christ Jesus. 25 But as he talked about righteousness and self-control and the judgment to come, Felix became frightened and answered: “For the present go your way, but when I get an opportune time I shall send for you again.” 26 At the same time, though, he was hoping for money to be given him by Paul. On that account he sent for him even more frequently and would converse with him. 27 But, when two years had elapsed, Felix was succeeded by Porcius Festus; and because Felix desired to gain favor with the Jews, he left Paul bound.

Acts

25 Therefore Festus, after entering upon the government of the province, went up three days later to Jerusalem from Caes·a·re′a; 2 and the chief priests and the principal men of the Jews gave him information against Paul. So they began to entreat him, 3 asking for themselves as a favor against the man that he would send for him to come to Jerusalem, as they were laying an ambush to do away with him along the road. 4 However, Festus answered that Paul was to be kept in Caes·a·re′a and that he himself was about to depart shortly for there. 5 “Hence let those who are in power among YOU,” he said, “come down with me and accuse him, if there is anything out of the way about the man.”

6 So when he had spent not more than eight or ten days among them, he went down to Caes·a·re′a, and the next day he sat down on the judgment seat and commanded Paul to be brought in. 7 When he arrived, the Jews that had come down from Jerusalem stood round about him, leveling against him many and serious charges for which they were unable to show evidence.

8 But Paul said in defense: “Neither against the Law of the Jews nor against the temple nor against Caesar have I committed any sin.” 9 Festus, desiring to gain favor with the Jews, said in reply to Paul: “Do you wish to go up to Jerusalem and be judged there before me concerning these things?” 10 But Paul said: “I am standing before the judgment seat of Caesar, where I ought to be judged. I have done no wrong to the Jews, as you also are finding out quite well. 11 If, on the one hand, I am really a wrongdoer and have committed anything deserving of death, I do not beg off from dying; if, on the other hand, none of those things exists of which these men accuse me, no man can hand me over to them as a favor. I appeal to Caesar!” 12 Then Festus, after speaking with the assembly of counselors, replied: “To Caesar you have appealed; to Caesar you shall go.”

13 Now when some days had passed, A·grip′pa the king and Ber·ni′ce arrived in Caes·a·re′a for a visit of courtesy to Festus. 14 So, as they were spending a number of days there, Festus laid before the king the matters respecting Paul, saying:

“There is a certain man left prisoner by Felix, 15 and when I was in Jerusalem the chief priests and the older men of the Jews brought information about him, asking a judgment of condemnation against him. 16 But I replied to them that it is not Roman procedure to hand any man over as a favor before the accused man meets his accusers face to face and gets a chance to speak in his defense concerning the complaint. 17 Therefore when they got together here, I made no delay, but the next day I sat down on the judgment seat and commanded the man to be brought in. 18 Taking the stand, the accusers produced no charge of the wicked things I had supposed concerning him. 19 They simply had certain disputes with him concerning their own worship of the deity and concerning a certain Jesus who was dead but who Paul kept asserting was alive. 20 So, being perplexed as to the dispute over these matters, I proceeded to ask if he would like to go to Jerusalem and there be judged concerning these matters. 21 But when Paul appealed to be kept for the decision by the August One, I commanded him to be kept until I should send him on up to Caesar.”

22 Here A·grip′pa said to Festus: “I myself would also like to hear the man.” “Tomorrow,” he said, “you shall hear him.” 23 Therefore, on the next day, A·grip′pa and Ber·ni′ce came with much pompous show and entered into the audience chamber together with military commanders as well as men of eminence in the city, and when Festus gave the command, Paul was brought in. 24 And Festus said: “King A·grip′pa and all YOU men who are present with us, YOU are beholding this man concerning whom all the multitude of the Jews together have applied to me both in Jerusalem and here, shouting that he ought not to live any longer. 25 But I perceived he had committed nothing deserving of death. So when this man himself appealed to the August One, I decided to send him. 26 But concerning him I have nothing certain to write to my Lord. Therefore I brought him forth before YOU, and especially before you, King A·grip′pa, in order that, after the judicial examination has taken place, I might get something to write. 27 For it seems unreasonable to me to send a prisoner and not also to signify the charges against him.”

Acts

26 A·grip′pa said to Paul: “You are permitted to speak in behalf of yourself.” Then Paul stretched his hand out and proceeded to say in his defense:

2 “Concerning all the things of which I am accused by Jews, King A·grip′pa, I count myself happy that it is before you I am to make my defense this day, 3 especially as you are expert on all the customs as well as the controversies among Jews. Therefore I beg you to hear me patiently.

4 “Indeed, as to the manner of life from youth up that I led from the beginning among my nation and in Jerusalem, all the Jews 5 that have been previously acquainted with me from the first know, if they but wish to bear witness, that according to the strictest sect of our form of worship I lived a Pharisee. 6 And yet now for the hope of the promise that was made by God to our forefathers I stand called to judgment; 7 whereas our twelve tribes are hoping to attain to the fulfillment of this promise by intensely rendering him sacred service night and day. Concerning this hope I am accused by Jews, O king.

8 “Why is it judged unbelievable among YOU men that God raises up the dead? 9 I, for one, really thought within myself I ought to commit many acts of opposition against the name of Jesus the Naz·a·rene′; 10 which, in fact, I did in Jerusalem, and many of the holy ones I locked up in prisons, as I had received authority from the chief priests; and when they were to be executed, I cast my vote against them. 11 And by punishing them many times in all the synagogues I tried to force them to make a recantation; and since I was extremely mad against them, I went so far as to persecuting them even in outside cities.

12 “Amid these efforts as I was journeying to Damascus with authority and a commission from the chief priests, 13 I saw at midday on the road, O king, a light beyond the brilliance of the sun flash from heaven about me and about those journeying with me. 14 And when we had all fallen to the ground I heard a voice say to me in the Hebrew language, ‘Saul, Saul, why are you persecuting me? To keep kicking against the goads makes it hard for you.’ 15 But I said, ‘Who are you, Lord?’ And the Lord said, ‘I am Jesus, whom you are persecuting. 16 Nevertheless, rise and stand on your feet. For to this end I have made myself visible to you, in order to choose you as an attendant and a witness both of things you have seen and things I shall make you see respecting me; 17 while I deliver you from this people and from the nations, to whom I am sending you, 18 to open their eyes, to turn them from darkness to light and from the authority of Satan to God, in order for them to receive forgiveness of sins and an inheritance among those sanctified by their faith in me.’

19 “Wherefore, King A·grip′pa, I did not become disobedient to the heavenly sight, 20 but both to those in Damascus first and to those in Jerusalem, and over all the country of Ju·de′a, and to the nations I went bringing the message that they should repent and turn to God by doing works that befit repentance. 21 On account of these things Jews seized me in the temple and attempted to slay me. 22 However, because I have obtained the help that is from God I continue to this day bearing witness to both small and great, but saying nothing except things the Prophets as well as Moses stated were going to take place, 23 that the Christ was to suffer and, as the first to be resurrected from the dead, he was going to publish light both to this people and to the nations.”

24 Now as he was saying these things in his defense, Festus said in a loud voice: “You are going mad, Paul! Great learning is driving you into madness!” 25 But Paul said: “I am not going mad, Your Excellency Festus, but I am uttering sayings of truth and of soundness of mind. 26 In reality, the king to whom I am speaking with freeness of speech well knows about these things; for I am persuaded that not one of these things escapes his notice, for this thing has not been done in a corner. 27 Do you, King A·grip′pa, believe the Prophets? I know you believe.” 28 But A·grip′pa said to Paul: “In a short time you would persuade me to become a Christian.” 29 At this Paul said: “I could wish to God that whether in a short time or in a long time not only you but also all those who hear me today would become men such as I also am, with the exception of these bonds.”

30 And the king rose and so did the governor and Ber·ni′ce and the men seated with them. 31 But as they withdrew they began talking with one another, saying: “This man practices nothing deserving death or bonds.” 32 Moreover, A·grip′pa said to Festus: “This man could have been released if he had not appealed to Caesar.”

Romans

9 I am telling the truth in Christ; I am not lying, since my conscience bears witness with me in holy spirit, 2 that I have great grief and unceasing pain in my heart. 3 For I could wish that I myself were separated as the cursed one from the Christ in behalf of my brothers, my relatives according to the flesh, 4 who, as such, are Israelites, to whom belong the adoption as sons and the glory and the covenants and the giving of the Law and the sacred service and the promises; 5 to whom the forefathers belong and from whom the Christ sprang according to the flesh: God, who is over all, be blessed forever. Amen.

6 However, it is not as though the word of God had failed. For not all who spring from Israel are really “Israel.” 7 Neither because they are Abraham’s seed are they all children, but: “What will be called ‘your seed’ will be through Isaac.” 8 That is, the children in the flesh are not really the children of God, but the children by the promise are counted as the seed. 9 For the word of promise was as follows: “At this time I will come and Sarah will have a son.” 10 Yet not that case alone, but also when Re·bek′ah conceived twins from the one man, Isaac our forefather: 11 for when they had not yet been born nor had practiced anything good or vile, in order that the purpose of God respecting the choosing might continue dependent, not upon works, but upon the One who calls, 12 it was said to her: “The older will be the slave of the younger.” 13 Just as it is written: “I loved Jacob, but E′sau I hated.”

14 What shall we say, then? Is there injustice with God? Never may that become so! 15 For he says to Moses: “I will have mercy upon whomever I do have mercy, and I will show compassion to whomever I do show compassion.” 16 So, then, it depends, not upon the one wishing nor upon the one running, but upon God, who has mercy. 17 For the Scripture says to Phar′aoh: “For this very cause I have let you remain, that in connection with you I may show my power, and that my name may be declared in all the earth.” 18 So, then, upon whom he wishes he has mercy, but whom he wishes he lets become obstinate.

19 You will therefore say to me: “Why does he yet find fault? For who has withstood his express will?” 20 O man, who, then, really are you to be answering back to God? Shall the thing molded say to him that molded it, “Why did you make me this way?” 21 What? Does not the potter have authority over the clay to make from the same lump one vessel for an honorable use, another for a dishonorable use? 22 If, now, God, although having the will to demonstrate his wrath and to make his power known, tolerated with much long-suffering vessels of wrath made fit for destruction, 23 in order that he might make known the riches of his glory upon vessels of mercy, which he prepared beforehand for glory, 24 namely, us, whom he called not only from among Jews but also from among nations, what of it? 25 It is as he says also in Ho·se′a: “Those not my people I will call ‘my people,’ and her who was not beloved ‘beloved’; 26 and in the place where it was said to them, ‘YOU are not my people,’ there they will be called ‘sons of the living God.’”

27 Moreover, Isaiah cries out concerning Israel: “Although the number of the sons of Israel may be as the sand of the sea, it is the remnant that will be saved. 28 For Jehovah will make an accounting on the earth, concluding it and cutting it short.” 29 Also, just as Isaiah had said aforetime: “Unless Jehovah of armies had left a seed to us, we should have become just like Sod′om, and we should have been made just like Go·mor′rah.”

30 What shall we say, then? That people of the nations, although not pursuing righteousness, caught up with righteousness, the righteousness that results from faith; 31 but Israel, although pursuing a law of righteousness, did not attain to the law. 32 For what reason? Because he pursued it, not by faith, but as by works. They stumbled on the “stone of stumbling”; 33 as it is written: “Look! I am laying in Zion a stone of stumbling and a rock-mass of offense, but he that rests his faith on it will not come to disappointment.”

The First to the Corinthians

1 Paul, called to be an apostle of Jesus Christ through God’s will, and Sos′the·nes our brother 2 to the congregation of God that is in Corinth, to YOU who have been sanctified in union with Christ Jesus, called to be holy ones, together with all who everywhere are calling upon the name of our Lord, Jesus Christ, their Lord and ours:

3 May YOU have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

4 I always thank God for YOU in view of the undeserved kindness of God given to YOU in Christ Jesus; 5 that in everything YOU have been enriched in him, in full ability to speak and in full knowledge, 6 even as the witness about the Christ has been rendered firm among YOU, 7 so that YOU do not fall short in any gift at all, while YOU are eagerly waiting for the revelation of our Lord Jesus Christ. 8 He will also make YOU firm to the end, that YOU may be open to no accusation in the day of our Lord Jesus Christ. 9 God is faithful, by whom YOU were called into a sharing with his Son Jesus Christ our Lord.

10 Now I exhort YOU, brothers, through the name of our Lord Jesus Christ that YOU should all speak in agreement, and that there should not be divisions among YOU, but that YOU may be fitly united in the same mind and in the same line of thought. 11 For the disclosure was made to me about YOU, my brothers, by those of the house of Chlo′e, that dissensions exist among YOU. 12 What I mean is this, that each one of YOU says: “I belong to Paul,” “But I to A·pol′los,” “But I to Ce′phas,” “But I to Christ.” 13 The Christ exists divided. Paul was not impaled for YOU, was he? Or were YOU baptized in the name of Paul? 14 I am thankful I baptized none of YOU except Cris′pus and Ga′ius, 15 so that no one may say that YOU were baptized in my name. 16 Yes, I also baptized the household of Steph′a·nas. As for the rest, I do not know whether I baptized anybody else. 17 For Christ dispatched me, not to go baptizing, but to go declaring the good news, not with wisdom of speech, that the torture stake of the Christ should not be made useless.

18 For the speech about the torture stake is foolishness to those who are perishing, but to us who are being saved it is God’s power. 19 For it is written: “I will make the wisdom of the wise men perish, and the intelligence of the intellectual men I will shove aside.” 20 Where is the wise man? Where the scribe? Where the debater of this system of things? Did not God make the wisdom of the world foolish? 21 For since, in the wisdom of God, the world through its wisdom did not get to know God, God saw good through the foolishness of what is preached to save those believing.

22 For both the Jews ask for signs and the Greeks look for wisdom; 23 but we preach Christ impaled, to the Jews a cause for stumbling but to the nations foolishness; 24 however, to those who are the called, both Jews and Greeks, Christ the power of God and the wisdom of God. 25 Because a foolish thing of God is wiser than men, and a weak thing of God is stronger than men.

26 For YOU behold his calling of YOU, brothers, that not many wise in a fleshly way were called, not many powerful, not many of noble birth; 27 but God chose the foolish things of the world, that he might put the wise men to shame; and God chose the weak things of the world, that he might put the strong things to shame; 28 and God chose the ignoble things of the world and the things looked down upon, the things that are not, that he might bring to nothing the things that are, 29 in order that no flesh might boast in the sight of God. 30 But it is due to him that YOU are in union with Christ Jesus, who has become to us wisdom from God, also righteousness and sanctification and release by ransom; 31 that it may be just as it is written: “He that boasts, let him boast in Jehovah.”

1 Corinthians

5 Actually fornication is reported among YOU, and such fornication as is not even among the nations, that a wife a certain man has of his father. 2 And are YOU puffed up, and did YOU not rather mourn, in order that the man that committed this deed should be taken away from YOUR midst? 3 I for one, although absent in body but present in spirit, have certainly judged already, as if I were present, the man who has worked in such a way as this, 4 that in the name of our Lord Jesus, when YOU are gathered together, also my spirit with the power of our Lord Jesus, 5 YOU hand such a man over to Satan for the destruction of the flesh, in order that the spirit may be saved in the day of the Lord.

6 YOUR cause for boasting is not fine. Do YOU not know that a little leaven ferments the whole lump? 7 Clear away the old leaven, that YOU may be a new lump, according as YOU are free from ferment. For, indeed, Christ our passover has been sacrificed. 8 Consequently let us keep the festival, not with old leaven, neither with leaven of badness and wickedness, but with unfermented cakes of sincerity and truth.

9 In my letter I wrote YOU to quit mixing in company with fornicators, 10 not meaning entirely with the fornicators of this world or the greedy persons and extortioners or idolaters. Otherwise, YOU would actually have to get out of the world. 11 But now I am writing YOU to quit mixing in company with anyone called a brother that is a fornicator or a greedy person or an idolater or a reviler or a drunkard or an extortioner, not even eating with such a man. 12 For what do I have to do with judging those outside? Do YOU not judge those inside, 13 while God judges those outside? “Remove the wicked man from among yourselves.”

1 Corinthians

7 Now concerning the things about which YOU wrote, it is well for a man not to touch a woman; 2 yet, because of prevalence of fornication, let each man have his own wife and each woman have her own husband. 3 Let the husband render to his wife her due; but let the wife also do likewise to her husband. 4 The wife does not exercise authority over her own body, but her husband does; likewise, also, the husband does not exercise authority over his own body, but his wife does. 5 Do not be depriving each other of it, except by mutual consent for an appointed time, that YOU may devote time to prayer and may come together again, that Satan may not keep tempting YOU for YOUR lack of self-regulation. 6 However, I say this by way of concession, not in the way of a command. 7 But I wish all men were as I myself am. Nevertheless, each one has his own gift from God, one in this way, another in that way.

8 Now I say to the unmarried persons and the widows, it is well for them that they remain even as I am. 9 But if they do not have self-control, let them marry, for it is better to marry than to be inflamed with passion.

10 To the married people I give instructions, yet not I but the Lord, that a wife should not depart from her husband; 11 but if she should actually depart, let her remain unmarried or else make up again with her husband; and a husband should not leave his wife.

12 But to the others I say, yes, I, not the Lord: If any brother has an unbelieving wife, and yet she is agreeable to dwelling with him, let him not leave her; 13 and a woman who has an unbelieving husband, and yet he is agreeable to dwelling with her, let her not leave her husband. 14 For the unbelieving husband is sanctified in relation to his wife, and the unbelieving wife is sanctified in relation to the brother; otherwise, YOUR children would really be unclean, but now they are holy. 15 But if the unbelieving one proceeds to depart, let him depart; a brother or a sister is not in servitude under such circumstances, but God has called YOU to peace. 16 For, wife, how do you know but that you will save your husband? Or, husband, how do you know but that you will save your wife?

17 Only, as Jehovah has given each one a portion, let each one so walk as God has called him. And thus I ordain in all the congregations. 18 Was any man called circumcised? Let him not become uncircumcised. Has any man been called in uncircumcision? Let him not get circumcised. 19 Circumcision does not mean a thing, and uncircumcision means not a thing, but observance of God’s commandments does. 20 In whatever state each one was called, let him remain in it. 21 Were you called when a slave? Do not let it worry you; but if you can also become free, rather seize the opportunity. 22 For anyone in the Lord that was called when a slave is the Lord’s freedman; likewise he that was called when a freeman is a slave of Christ. 23 YOU were bought with a price; stop becoming slaves of men. 24 In whatever condition each one was called, brothers, let him remain in it associated with God.

25 Now concerning virgins I have no command from the Lord, but I give my opinion as one who had mercy shown him by the Lord to be faithful. 26 Therefore I think this to be well in view of the necessity here with us, that it is well for a man to continue as he is. 27 Are you bound to a wife? Stop seeking a release. Are you loosed from a wife? Stop seeking a wife. 28 But even if you did marry, you would commit no sin. And if a virgin person married, such one would commit no sin. However, those who do will have tribulation in their flesh. But I am sparing YOU.

29 Moreover, this I say, brothers, the time left is reduced. Henceforth let those who have wives be as though they had none, 30 and also those who weep be as those who do not weep, and those who rejoice as those who do not rejoice, and those who buy as those not possessing, 31 and those making use of the world as those not using it to the full; for the scene of this world is changing. 32 Indeed, I want YOU to be free from anxiety. The unmarried man is anxious for the things of the Lord, how he may gain the Lord’s approval. 33 But the married man is anxious for the things of the world, how he may gain the approval of his wife, 34 and he is divided. Further, the unmarried woman, and the virgin, is anxious for the things of the Lord, that she may be holy both in her body and in her spirit. However, the married woman is anxious for the things of the world, how she may gain the approval of her husband. 35 But this I am saying for YOUR personal advantage, not that I may cast a noose upon YOU, but to move YOU to that which is becoming and that which means constant attendance upon the Lord without distraction.

36 But if anyone thinks he is behaving improperly toward his virginity, if that is past the bloom of youth, and this is the way it should take place, let him do what he wants; he does not sin. Let them marry. 37 But if anyone stands settled in his heart, having no necessity, but has authority over his own will and has made this decision in his own heart, to keep his own virginity, he will do well. 38 Consequently he also that gives his virginity in marriage does well, but he that does not give it in marriage will do better.

39 A wife is bound during all the time her husband is alive. But if her husband should fall asleep in death, she is free to be married to whom she wants, only in the Lord. 40 But she is happier if she remains as she is, according to my opinion. I certainly think I also have God’s spirit.

1 Corinthians

12 Now concerning the spiritual gifts, brothers, I do not want YOU to be ignorant. 2 YOU know that when YOU were people of the nations, YOU were being led away to those voiceless idols just as YOU happened to be led. 3 Therefore I would have YOU know that nobody when speaking by God’s spirit says: “Jesus is accursed!” and nobody can say: “Jesus is Lord!” except by holy spirit.

4 Now there are varieties of gifts, but there is the same spirit; 5 and there are varieties of ministries, and yet there is the same Lord; 6 and there are varieties of operations, and yet it is the same God who performs all the operations in all persons. 7 But the manifestation of the spirit is given to each one for a beneficial purpose. 8 For example, to one there is given through the spirit speech of wisdom, to another speech of knowledge according to the same spirit, 9 to another faith by the same spirit, to another gifts of healings by that one spirit, 10 to yet another operations of powerful works, to another prophesying, to another discernment of inspired utterances, to another different tongues, and to another interpretation of tongues. 11 But all these operations the one and the same spirit performs, making a distribution to each one respectively just as it wills.

12 For just as the body is one but has many members, and all the members of that body, although being many, are one body, so also is the Christ. 13 For truly by one spirit we were all baptized into one body, whether Jews or Greeks, whether slaves or free, and we were all made to drink one spirit.

14 For the body, indeed, is not one member, but many. 15 If the foot should say: “Because I am not a hand, I am no part of the body,” it is not for this reason no part of the body. 16 And if the ear should say: “Because I am not an eye, I am no part of the body,” it is not for this reason no part of the body. 17 If the whole body were an eye, where would the sense of hearing be? If it were all hearing, where would the smelling be? 18 But now God has set the members in the body, each one of them, just as he pleased.

19 If they were all one member, where would the body be? 20 But now they are many members, yet one body. 21 The eye cannot say to the hand: “I have no need of you”; or, again, the head cannot say to the feet: “I have no need of YOU.” 22 But much rather is it the case that the members of the body which seem to be weaker are necessary, 23 and the parts of the body which we think to be less honorable, these we surround with more abundant honor, and so our unseemly parts have the more abundant comeliness, 24 whereas our comely parts do not need anything. Nevertheless, God compounded the body, giving honor more abundant to the part which had a lack, 25 so that there should be no division in the body, but that its members should have the same care for one another. 26 And if one member suffers, all the other members suffer with it; or if a member is glorified, all the other members rejoice with it.

27 Now YOU are Christ’s body, and members individually. 28 And God has set the respective ones in the congregation, first, apostles; second, prophets; third, teachers; then powerful works; then gifts of healings; helpful services, abilities to direct, different tongues. 29 Not all are apostles, are they? Not all are prophets, are they? Not all are teachers, are they? Not all perform powerful works, do they? 30 Not all have gifts of healings, do they? Not all speak in tongues, do they? Not all are translators, are they? 31 But keep zealously seeking the greater gifts. And yet I show YOU a surpassing way.

1 Corinthians

13 If I speak in the tongues of men and of angels but do not have love, I have become a sounding piece of brass or a clashing cymbal. 2 And if I have the gift of prophesying and am acquainted with all the sacred secrets and all knowledge, and if I have all the faith so as to transplant mountains, but do not have love, I am nothing. 3 And if I give all my belongings to feed others, and if I hand over my body, that I may boast, but do not have love, I am not profited at all.

4 Love is long-suffering and kind. Love is not jealous, it does not brag, does not get puffed up, 5 does not behave indecently, does not look for its own interests, does not become provoked. It does not keep account of the injury. 6 It does not rejoice over unrighteousness, but rejoices with the truth. 7 It bears all things, believes all things, hopes all things, endures all things.

8 Love never fails. But whether there are gifts of prophesying, they will be done away with; whether there are tongues, they will cease; whether there is knowledge, it will be done away with. 9 For we have partial knowledge and we prophesy partially; 10 but when that which is complete arrives, that which is partial will be done away with. 11 When I was a babe, I used to speak as a babe, to think as a babe, to reason as a babe; but now that I have become a man, I have done away with the traits of a babe. 12 For at present we see in hazy outline by means of a metal mirror, but then it will be face to face. At present I know partially, but then I shall know accurately even as I am accurately known. 13 Now, however, there remain faith, hope, love, these three; but the greatest of these is love.

1 Corinthians

14 Pursue love, yet keep zealously seeking the spiritual gifts, but preferably that YOU may prophesy. 2 For he that speaks in a tongue speaks, not to men, but to God, for no one listens, but he speaks sacred secrets by the spirit. 3 However, he that prophesies upbuilds and encourages and consoles men by his speech. 4 He that speaks in a tongue upbuilds himself, but he that prophesies upbuilds a congregation. 5 Now I would like for all of YOU to speak in tongues, but I prefer that YOU prophesy. Indeed, he that prophesies is greater than he that speaks in tongues, unless, in fact, he translates, that the congregation may receive upbuilding. 6 But at this time, brothers, if I should come speaking to YOU in tongues, what good would I do YOU unless I spoke to YOU either with a revelation or with knowledge or with a prophecy or with a teaching?

7 As it is, the inanimate things give off sound, whether a flute or a harp; unless it makes an interval to the tones, how will it be known what is being played on the flute or on the harp? 8 For truly, if the trumpet sounds an indistinct call, who will get ready for battle? 9 In the same way also, unless YOU through the tongue utter speech easily understood, how will it be known what is being spoken? YOU will, in fact, be speaking into the air. 10 It may be that there are so many kinds of speech sounds in the world, and yet no kind is without meaning. 11 If, then, I do not understand the force of the speech sound, I shall be a foreigner to the one speaking, and the one speaking will be a foreigner to me. 12 So also YOU yourselves, since YOU are zealously desirous of gifts of the spirit, seek to abound in them for the upbuilding of the congregation.

13 Therefore let the one who speaks in a tongue pray that he may translate. 14 For if I am praying in a tongue, it is my gift of the spirit that is praying, but my mind is unfruitful. 15 What is to be done, then? I will pray with the gift of the spirit, but I will also pray with my mind. I will sing praise with the gift of the spirit, but I will also sing praise with my mind. 16 Otherwise, if you offer praise with a gift of the spirit, how will the man occupying the seat of the ordinary person say “Amen” to your giving of thanks, since he does not know what you are saying? 17 True, you give thanks in a fine way, but the other man is not being built up. 18 I thank God, I speak in more tongues than all of YOU do. 19 Nevertheless, in a congregation I would rather speak five words with my mind, that I might also instruct others orally, than ten thousand words in a tongue.

20 Brothers, do not become young children in powers of understanding, but be babes as to badness; yet become full-grown in powers of understanding. 21 In the Law it is written: “‘With the tongues of foreigners and with the lips of strangers I will speak to this people, and yet not even then will they give heed to me,’ says Jehovah.” 22 Consequently tongues are for a sign, not to the believers, but to the unbelievers, whereas prophesying is, not for the unbelievers, but for the believers. 23 Therefore, if the whole congregation comes together to one place and they all speak in tongues, but ordinary people or unbelievers come in, will they not say that YOU are mad? 24 But if YOU are all prophesying and any unbeliever or ordinary person comes in, he is reproved by them all, he is closely examined by all; 25 the secrets of his heart become manifest, so that he will fall upon his face and worship God, declaring: “God is really among YOU.”

26 What is to be done, then, brothers? When YOU come together, one has a psalm, another has a teaching, another has a revelation, another has a tongue, another has an interpretation. Let all things take place for upbuilding. 27 And if someone speaks in a tongue, let it be limited to two or three at the most, and in turns; and let someone translate. 28 But if there be no translator, let him keep silent in the congregation and speak to himself and to God. 29 Further, let two or three prophets speak, and let the others discern the meaning. 30 But if there is a revelation to another one while sitting there, let the first one keep silent. 31 For YOU can all prophesy one by one, that all may learn and all be encouraged. 32 And gifts of the spirit of the prophets are to be controlled by the prophets. 33 For God is a God, not of disorder, but of peace.

As in all the congregations of the holy ones, 34 let the women keep silent in the congregations, for it is not permitted for them to speak, but let them be in subjection, even as the Law says. 35 If, then, they want to learn something, let them question their own husbands at home, for it is disgraceful for a woman to speak in a congregation.

36 What? Was it from YOU that the word of God came forth, or was it only as far as YOU that it reached?

37 If anyone thinks he is a prophet or gifted with the spirit, let him acknowledge the things I am writing to YOU, because they are the Lord’s commandment. 38 But if anyone is ignorant, he continues ignorant. 39 Consequently, my brothers, keep zealously seeking the prophesying, and yet do not forbid the speaking in tongues. 40 But let all things take place decently and by arrangement.

Galatians

2 Then after fourteen years I again went up to Jerusalem with Bar′na·bas, taking also Titus along with me. 2 But I went up as a result of a revelation. And I laid before them the good news which I am preaching among the nations, privately, however, before those who were outstanding men, for fear that somehow I was running or had run in vain. 3 Nevertheless, not even Titus, who was with me, was compelled to be circumcised, although he was a Greek. 4 But because of the false brothers brought in quietly, who sneaked in to spy upon our freedom which we have in union with Christ Jesus, that they might completely enslave us— 5 to these we did not yield by way of submission, no, not for an hour, in order that the truth of the good news might continue with YOU.

6 But on the part of those who seemed to be something—whatever sort of men they formerly were makes no difference to me—God does not go by a man’s outward appearance—to me, in fact, those outstanding men imparted nothing new. 7 But, on the contrary, when they saw that I had entrusted to me the good news for those who are uncircumcised, just as Peter had it for those who are circumcised— 8 for He who gave Peter powers necessary for an apostleship to those who are circumcised gave powers also to me for those who are of the nations; 9 yes, when they came to know the undeserved kindness that was given me, James and Ce′phas and John, the ones who seemed to be pillars, gave me and Bar′na·bas the right hand of sharing together, that we should go to the nations, but they to those who are circumcised. 10 Only we should keep the poor in mind. This very thing I have also earnestly endeavored to do.

11 However, when Ce′phas came to Antioch, I resisted him face to face, because he stood condemned. 12 For before the arrival of certain men from James, he used to eat with people of the nations; but when they arrived, he went withdrawing and separating himself, in fear of those of the circumcised class. 13 The rest of the Jews also joined him in putting on this pretense, so that even Bar′na·bas was led along with them in their pretense. 14 But when I saw they were not walking straight according to the truth of the good news, I said to Ce′phas before them all: “If you, though you are a Jew, live as the nations do, and not as Jews do, how is it that you are compelling people of the nations to live according to Jewish practice?”

15 We who are Jews by nature, and not sinners from the nations, 16 knowing as we do that a man is declared righteous, not due to works of law, but only through faith toward Christ Jesus, even we have put our faith in Christ Jesus, that we may be declared righteous due to faith toward Christ, and not due to works of law, because due to works of law no flesh will be declared righteous. 17 Now if we, in seeking to be declared righteous by means of Christ, have also ourselves been found sinners, is Christ in reality sin’s minister? May that never happen! 18 For if the very things that I once threw down I build up again, I demonstrate myself to be a transgressor. 19 As for me, through law I died toward law, that I might become alive toward God. 20 I am impaled along with Christ. It is no longer I that live, but it is Christ that is living in union with me. Indeed, the life that I now live in flesh I live by the faith that is toward the Son of God, who loved me and handed himself over for me. 21 I do not shove aside the undeserved kindness of God; for if righteousness is through law, Christ actually died for nothing.

Ephesians

2 Furthermore, it is YOU God made alive though YOU were dead in YOUR trespasses and sins, 2 in which YOU at one time walked according to the system of things of this world, according to the ruler of the authority of the air, the spirit that now operates in the sons of disobedience. 3 Yes, among them we all at one time conducted ourselves in harmony with the desires of our flesh, doing the things willed by the flesh and the thoughts, and we were naturally children of wrath even as the rest. 4 But God, who is rich in mercy, for his great love with which he loved us, 5 made us alive together with the Christ, even when we were dead in trespasses—by undeserved kindness YOU have been saved— 6 and he raised us up together and seated us together in the heavenly places in union with Christ Jesus, 7 that in the coming systems of things there might be demonstrated the surpassing riches of his undeserved kindness in his graciousness toward us in union with Christ Jesus.

8 By this undeserved kindness, indeed, YOU have been saved through faith; and this not owing to YOU, it is God’s gift. 9 No, it is not owing to works, in order that no man should have ground for boasting. 10 For we are a product of his work and were created in union with Christ Jesus for good works, which God prepared in advance for us to walk in them.

11 Therefore keep bearing in mind that formerly YOU were people of the nations as to flesh; “uncircumcision” YOU were called by that which is called “circumcision” made in the flesh with hands— 12 that YOU were at that particular time without Christ, alienated from the state of Israel and strangers to the covenants of the promise, and YOU had no hope and were without God in the world. 13 But now in union with Christ Jesus YOU who were once far off have come to be near by the blood of the Christ. 14 For he is our peace, he who made the two parties one and destroyed the wall in between that fenced them off. 15 By means of his flesh he abolished the enmity, the Law of commandments consisting in decrees, that he might create the two peoples in union with himself into one new man and make peace; 16 and that he might fully reconcile both peoples in one body to God through the torture stake, because he had killed off the enmity by means of himself. 17 And he came and declared the good news of peace to YOU, the ones far off, and peace to those near, 18 because through him we, both peoples, have the approach to the Father by one spirit.

19 Certainly, therefore, YOU are no longer strangers and alien residents, but YOU are fellow citizens of the holy ones and are members of the household of God, 20 and YOU have been built up upon the foundation of the apostles and prophets, while Christ Jesus himself is the foundation cornerstone. 21 In union with him the whole building, being harmoniously joined together, is growing into a holy temple for Jehovah. 22 In union with him YOU, too, are being built up together into a place for God to inhabit by spirit.

To the Philippians

1 Paul and Timothy, slaves of Christ Jesus, to all the holy ones in union with Christ Jesus who are in Phi·lip′pi, along with overseers and ministerial servants:

2 May YOU have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.

3 I thank my God always upon every remembrance of YOU 4 in every supplication of mine for all of YOU, as I offer my supplication with joy, 5 because of the contribution YOU have made to the good news from the first day until this moment. 6 For I am confident of this very thing, that he who started a good work in YOU will carry it to completion until the day of Jesus Christ. 7 It is altogether right for me to think this regarding all of YOU, on account of my having YOU in my heart, all of YOU being sharers with me in the undeserved kindness, both in my prison bonds and in the defending and legally establishing of the good news.

8 For God is my witness of how I am yearning for all of YOU in such tender affection as Christ Jesus has. 9 And this is what I continue praying, that YOUR love may abound yet more and more with accurate knowledge and full discernment; 10 that YOU may make sure of the more important things, so that YOU may be flawless and not be stumbling others up to the day of Christ, 11 and may be filled with righteous fruit, which is through Jesus Christ, to God’s glory and praise.

12 Now I desire YOU to know, brothers, that my affairs have turned out for the advancement of the good news rather than otherwise, 13 so that my bonds have become public knowledge in association with Christ among all the Prae·to′ri·an Guard and all the rest; 14 and most of the brothers in the Lord, feeling confidence by reason of my prison bonds, are showing all the more courage to speak the word of God fearlessly.

15 True, some are preaching the Christ through envy and rivalry, but others also through goodwill. 16 The latter are publicizing the Christ out of love, for they know I am set here for the defense of the good news; 17 but the former do it out of contentiousness, not with a pure motive, for they are supposing to stir up tribulation for me in my prison bonds. 18 What then? Nothing, except that in every way, whether in pretense or in truth, Christ is being publicized, and in this I rejoice. In fact, I will also keep on rejoicing, 19 for I know this will result in my salvation through YOUR supplication and a supply of the spirit of Jesus Christ, 20 in harmony with my eager expectation and hope that I shall not be ashamed in any respect, but that in all freeness of speech Christ will, as always before, so now be magnified by means of my body, whether through life or through death.

21 For in my case to live is Christ, and to die, gain. 22 Now if it be to live on in the flesh, this is a fruitage of my work—and yet which thing to select I do not make known. 23 I am under pressure from these two things; but what I do desire is the releasing and the being with Christ, for this, to be sure, is far better. 24 However, for me to remain in the flesh is more necessary on YOUR account. 25 So, being confident of this, I know I shall remain and shall abide with all of YOU for YOUR advancement and the joy that belongs to YOUR faith, 26 so that YOUR exultation may overflow in Christ Jesus by reason of me through my presence again with YOU.

27 Only behave in a manner worthy of the good news about the Christ, in order that, whether I come and see YOU or be absent, I may hear about the things which concern YOU, that YOU are standing firm in one spirit, with one soul striving side by side for the faith of the good news, 28 and in no respect being frightened by YOUR opponents. This very thing is a proof of destruction for them, but of salvation for YOU; and this indication is from God, 29 because to YOU the privilege was given in behalf of Christ, not only to put YOUR faith in him, but also to suffer in his behalf. 30 For YOU have the same struggle as YOU saw in my case and as YOU now hear about in my case.

To the Colossians

1 Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus through God’s will, and Timothy our brother 2 to the holy ones and faithful brothers in union with Christ at Co·los′sae:

May YOU have undeserved kindness and peace from God our Father.

3 We thank God the Father of our Lord Jesus Christ always when we pray for YOU, 4 since we heard of YOUR faith in connection with Christ Jesus and the love YOU have for all the holy ones 5 because of the hope that is being reserved for YOU in the heavens. This hope YOU heard of before by the telling of the truth of that good news 6 which has presented itself to YOU, even as it is bearing fruit and increasing in all the world just as it is doing also among YOU, from the day YOU heard and accurately knew the undeserved kindness of God in truth. 7 That is what YOU have learned from Ep′a·phras our beloved fellow slave, who is a faithful minister of the Christ on our behalf, 8 who also disclosed to us YOUR love in a spiritual way.

9 That is also why we, from the day we heard of it, have not ceased praying for YOU and asking that YOU may be filled with the accurate knowledge of his will in all wisdom and spiritual comprehension, 10 in order to walk worthily of Jehovah to the end of fully pleasing him as YOU go on bearing fruit in every good work and increasing in the accurate knowledge of God, 11 being made powerful with all power to the extent of his glorious might so as to endure fully and be long-suffering with joy, 12 thanking the Father who rendered YOU suitable for YOUR participation in the inheritance of the holy ones in the light.

13 He delivered us from the authority of the darkness and transferred us into the kingdom of the Son of his love, 14 by means of whom we have our release by ransom, the forgiveness of our sins. 15 He is the image of the invisible God, the firstborn of all creation; 16 because by means of him all other things were created in the heavens and upon the earth, the things visible and the things invisible, no matter whether they are thrones or lordships or governments or authorities. All other things have been created through him and for him. 17 Also, he is before all other things and by means of him all other things were made to exist, 18 and he is the head of the body, the congregation. He is the beginning, the firstborn from the dead, that he might become the one who is first in all things; 19 because God saw good for all fullness to dwell in him, 20 and through him to reconcile again to himself all other things by making peace through the blood he shed on the torture stake, no matter whether they are the things upon the earth or the things in the heavens.

21 Indeed, YOU who were once alienated and enemies because YOUR minds were on the works that were wicked, 22 he now has again reconciled by means of that one’s fleshly body through his death, in order to present YOU holy and unblemished and open to no accusation before him, 23 provided, of course, that YOU continue in the faith, established on the foundation and steadfast and not being shifted away from the hope of that good news which YOU heard, and which was preached in all creation that is under heaven. Of this good news I Paul became a minister.

24 I am now rejoicing in my sufferings for YOU, and I, in my turn, am filling up what is lacking of the tribulations of the Christ in my flesh on behalf of his body, which is the congregation. 25 I became a minister of this congregation in accordance with the stewardship from God which was given me in YOUR interest to preach the word of God fully, 26 the sacred secret that was hidden from the past systems of things and from the past generations. But now it has been made manifest to his holy ones, 27 to whom God has been pleased to make known what are the glorious riches of this sacred secret among the nations. It is Christ in union with YOU, the hope of his glory. 28 He is the one we are publicizing, admonishing every man and teaching every man in all wisdom, that we may present every man complete in union with Christ. 29 To this end I am indeed working hard, exerting myself in accordance with the operation of him and which is at work in me with power.

1 Thessalonians

5 Now as for the times and the seasons, brothers, YOU need nothing to be written to YOU. 2 For YOU yourselves know quite well that Jehovah’s day is coming exactly as a thief in the night. 3 Whenever it is that they are saying: “Peace and security!” then sudden destruction is to be instantly upon them just as the pang of distress upon a pregnant woman; and they will by no means escape. 4 But YOU, brothers, YOU are not in darkness, so that that day should overtake YOU as it would thieves, 5 for YOU are all sons of light and sons of day. We belong neither to night nor to darkness.

6 So, then, let us not sleep on as the rest do, but let us stay awake and keep our senses. 7 For those who sleep are accustomed to sleep at night, and those who get drunk are usually drunk at night. 8 But as for us who belong to the day, let us keep our senses and have on the breastplate of faith and love and as a helmet the hope of salvation; 9 because God assigned us, not to wrath, but to the acquiring of salvation through our Lord Jesus Christ. 10 He died for us, that, whether we stay awake or are asleep, we should live together with him. 11 Therefore keep comforting one another and building one another up, just as YOU are in fact doing.

12 Now we request YOU, brothers, to have regard for those who are working hard among YOU and presiding over YOU in the Lord and admonishing YOU; 13 and to give them more than extraordinary consideration in love because of their work. Be peaceable with one another. 14 On the other hand, we exhort YOU, brothers, admonish the disorderly, speak consolingly to the depressed souls, support the weak, be long-suffering toward all. 15 See that no one renders injury for injury to anyone else, but always pursue what is good toward one another and to all others.

16 Always be rejoicing. 17 Pray incessantly. 18 In connection with everything give thanks. For this is the will of God in union with Christ Jesus respecting YOU. 19 Do not put out the fire of the spirit. 20 Do not treat prophesyings with contempt. 21 Make sure of all things; hold fast to what is fine. 22 Abstain from every form of wickedness.

23 May the very God of peace sanctify YOU completely. And sound in every respect may the spirit and soul and body of YOU brothers be preserved in a blameless manner at the presence of our Lord Jesus Christ. 24 He who is calling YOU is faithful, and he will also do it.

25 Brothers, continue in prayer for us.

26 Greet all the brothers with a holy kiss.

27 I am putting YOU under the solemn obligation by the Lord for this letter to be read to all the brothers.

28 The undeserved kindness of our Lord Jesus Christ be with YOU.

1 Timothy

2 I therefore exhort, first of all, that supplications, prayers, intercessions, offerings of thanks, be made concerning all sorts of men, 2 concerning kings and all those who are in high station; in order that we may go on leading a calm and quiet life with full godly devotion and seriousness. 3 This is fine and acceptable in the sight of our Savior, God, 4 whose will is that all sorts of men should be saved and come to an accurate knowledge of truth. 5 For there is one God, and one mediator between God and men, a man, Christ Jesus, 6 who gave himself a corresponding ransom for all—this is what is to be witnessed to at its own particular times. 7 For the purpose of this witness I was appointed a preacher and an apostle—I am telling the truth, I am not lying—a teacher of nations in the matter of faith and truth.

8 Therefore I desire that in every place the men carry on prayer, lifting up loyal hands, apart from wrath and debates. 9 Likewise I desire the women to adorn themselves in well-arranged dress, with modesty and soundness of mind, not with styles of hair braiding and gold or pearls or very expensive garb, 10 but in the way that befits women professing to reverence God, namely, through good works.

11 Let a woman learn in silence with full submissiveness. 12 I do not permit a woman to teach, or to exercise authority over a man, but to be in silence. 13 For Adam was formed first, then Eve. 14 Also, Adam was not deceived, but the woman was thoroughly deceived and came to be in transgression. 15 However, she will be kept safe through childbearing, provided they continue in faith and love and sanctification along with soundness of mind.

1 Timothy

3 That statement is faithful.

If any man is reaching out for an office of overseer, he is desirous of a fine work. 2 The overseer should therefore be irreprehensible, a husband of one wife, moderate in habits, sound in mind, orderly, hospitable, qualified to teach, 3 not a drunken brawler, not a smiter, but reasonable, not belligerent, not a lover of money, 4 a man presiding over his own household in a fine manner, having children in subjection with all seriousness; 5 (if indeed any man does not know how to preside over his own household, how will he take care of God’s congregation?) 6 not a newly converted man, for fear that he might get puffed up with pride and fall into the judgment passed upon the Devil. 7 Moreover, he should also have a fine testimony from people on the outside, in order that he might not fall into reproach and a snare of the Devil.

8 Ministerial servants should likewise be serious, not double-tongued, not giving themselves to a lot of wine, not greedy of dishonest gain, 9 holding the sacred secret of the faith with a clean conscience.

10 Also, let these be tested as to fitness first, then let them serve as ministers, as they are free from accusation.

11 Women should likewise be serious, not slanderous, moderate in habits, faithful in all things.

12 Let ministerial servants be husbands of one wife, presiding in a fine manner over children and their own households. 13 For the men who minister in a fine manner are acquiring for themselves a fine standing and great freeness of speech in the faith in connection with Christ Jesus.

14 I am writing you these things, though I am hoping to come to you shortly, 15 but in case I am delayed, that you may know how you ought to conduct yourself in God’s household, which is the congregation of the living God, a pillar and support of the truth. 16 Indeed, the sacred secret of this godly devotion is admittedly great: ‘He was made manifest in flesh, was declared righteous in spirit, appeared to angels, was preached about among nations, was believed upon in the world, was received up in glory.’

1 Timothy

4 However, the inspired utterance says definitely that in later periods of time some will fall away from the faith, paying attention to misleading inspired utterances and teachings of demons, 2 by the hypocrisy of men who speak lies, marked in their conscience as with a branding iron; 3 forbidding to marry, commanding to abstain from foods which God created to be partaken of with thanksgiving by those who have faith and accurately know the truth. 4 The reason for this is that every creation of God is fine, and nothing is to be rejected if it is received with thanksgiving, 5 for it is sanctified through God’s word and prayer over it.

6 By giving these advices to the brothers you will be a fine minister of Christ Jesus, one nourished with the words of the faith and of the fine teaching which you have followed closely. 7 But turn down the false stories which violate what is holy and which old women tell. On the other hand, be training yourself with godly devotion as your aim. 8 For bodily training is beneficial for a little; but godly devotion is beneficial for all things, as it holds promise of the life now and that which is to come. 9 Faithful and deserving of full acceptance is that statement. 10 For to this end we are working hard and exerting ourselves, because we have rested our hope on a living God, who is a Savior of all sorts of men, especially of faithful ones.

11 Keep on giving these commands and teaching them. 12 Let no man ever look down on your youth. On the contrary, become an example to the faithful ones in speaking, in conduct, in love, in faith, in chasteness. 13 While I am coming, continue applying yourself to public reading, to exhortation, to teaching. 14 Do not be neglecting the gift in you that was given you through a prediction and when the body of older men laid their hands upon you. 15 Ponder over these things; be absorbed in them, that your advancement may be manifest to all persons. 16 Pay constant attention to yourself and to your teaching. Stay by these things, for by doing this you will save both yourself and those who listen to you.

2 Timothy

2 You, therefore, my child, keep on acquiring power in the undeserved kindness that is in connection with Christ Jesus, 2 and the things you heard from me with the support of many witnesses, these things commit to faithful men, who, in turn, will be adequately qualified to teach others. 3 As a fine soldier of Christ Jesus take your part in suffering evil. 4 No man serving as a soldier involves himself in the commercial businesses of life, in order that he may gain the approval of the one who enrolled him as a soldier. 5 Moreover, if anyone contends even in the games, he is not crowned unless he has contended according to the rules. 6 The hardworking farmer must be the first to partake of the fruits. 7 Give constant thought to what I am saying; the Lord will really give you discernment in all things.

8 Remember that Jesus Christ was raised up from the dead and was of David’s seed, according to the good news I preach; 9 in connection with which I am suffering evil to the point of prison bonds as an evildoer. Nevertheless, the word of God is not bound. 10 On this account I go on enduring all things for the sake of the chosen ones, that they too may obtain the salvation that is in union with Christ Jesus along with everlasting glory. 11 Faithful is the saying: Certainly if we died together, we shall also live together; 12 if we go on enduring, we shall also rule together as kings; if we deny, he also will deny us; 13 if we are unfaithful, he remains faithful, for he cannot deny himself.

14 Keep reminding them of these things, charging them before God as witness, not to fight about words, a thing of no usefulness at all because it overturns those listening. 15 Do your utmost to present yourself approved to God, a workman with nothing to be ashamed of, handling the word of the truth aright. 16 But shun empty speeches that violate what is holy; for they will advance to more and more ungodliness, 17 and their word will spread like gangrene. Hy·me·nae′us and Phi·le′tus are of that number. 18 These very men have deviated from the truth, saying that the resurrection has already occurred; and they are subverting the faith of some. 19 For all that, the solid foundation of God stays standing, having this seal: “Jehovah knows those who belong to him,” and: “Let everyone naming the name of Jehovah renounce unrighteousness.”

20 Now in a large house there are vessels not only of gold and silver but also of wood and earthenware, and some for an honorable purpose but others for a purpose lacking honor. 21 If, therefore, anyone keeps clear of the latter ones, he will be a vessel for an honorable purpose, sanctified, useful to his owner, prepared for every good work. 22 So, flee from the desires incidental to youth, but pursue righteousness, faith, love, peace, along with those who call upon the Lord out of a clean heart.

23 Further, turn down foolish and ignorant questionings, knowing they produce fights. 24 But a slave of the Lord does not need to fight, but needs to be gentle toward all, qualified to teach, keeping himself restrained under evil, 25 instructing with mildness those not favorably disposed; as perhaps God may give them repentance leading to an accurate knowledge of truth, 26 and they may come back to their proper senses out from the snare of the Devil, seeing that they have been caught alive by him for the will of that one.

2 Timothy

4 I solemnly charge you before God and Christ Jesus, who is destined to judge the living and the dead, and by his manifestation and his kingdom, 2 preach the word, be at it urgently in favorable season, in troublesome season, reprove, reprimand, exhort, with all long-suffering and art of teaching. 3 For there will be a period of time when they will not put up with the healthful teaching, but, in accord with their own desires, they will accumulate teachers for themselves to have their ears tickled; 4 and they will turn their ears away from the truth, whereas they will be turned aside to false stories. 5 You, though, keep your senses in all things, suffer evil, do the work of an evangelizer, fully accomplish your ministry.

6 For I am already being poured out like a drink offering, and the due time for my releasing is imminent. 7 I have fought the fine fight, I have run the course to the finish, I have observed the faith. 8 From this time on there is reserved for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge, will give me as a reward in that day, yet not only to me, but also to all those who have loved his manifestation.

9 Do your utmost to come to me shortly. 10 For De′mas has forsaken me because he loved the present system of things, and he has gone to Thes·sa·lo·ni′ca; Cres′cens to Ga·la′ti·a, Titus to Dal·ma′tia. 11 Luke alone is with me. Take Mark and bring him with you, for he is useful to me for ministering. 12 But I have sent Tych′i·cus off to Eph′e·sus. 13 When you come, bring the cloak I left at Tro′as with Carpus, and the scrolls, especially the parchments.

14 Alexander the coppersmith did me many injuries—Jehovah will repay him according to his deeds— 15 and you too be on guard against him, for he resisted our words to an excessive degree.

16 In my first defense no one came to my side, but they all proceeded to forsake me—may it not be put to their account— 17 but the Lord stood near me and infused power into me, that through me the preaching might be fully accomplished and all the nations might hear it; and I was delivered from the lion’s mouth. 18 The Lord will deliver me from every wicked work and will save me for his heavenly kingdom. To him be the glory forever and ever. Amen.

19 Give my greetings to Pris′ca and Aq′ui·la and the household of On·e·siph′o·rus.

20 E·ras′tus stayed in Corinth, but I left Troph′i·mus sick at Mi·le′tus. 21 Do your utmost to arrive before winter.

Eu·bu′lus sends you his greetings, and so do Pu′dens and Li′nus and Clau′di·a and all the brothers.

22 The Lord be with the spirit you show. His undeserved kindness be with YOU people.

To Titus

1 Paul, a slave of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ according to the faith of God’s chosen ones and the accurate knowledge of the truth which accords with godly devotion 2 upon the basis of a hope of the everlasting life which God, who cannot lie, promised before times long lasting, 3 whereas in his own due times he made his word manifest in the preaching with which I was entrusted, under command of our Savior, God; 4 to Titus, a genuine child according to a faith shared in common:

May there be undeserved kindness and peace from God the Father and Christ Jesus our Savior.

5 For this reason I left you in Crete, that you might correct the things that were defective and might make appointments of older men in city after city, as I gave you orders; 6 if there is any man free from accusation, a husband of one wife, having believing children that were not under a charge of debauchery nor unruly. 7 For an overseer must be free from accusation as God’s steward, not self-willed, not prone to wrath, not a drunken brawler, not a smiter, not greedy of dishonest gain, 8 but hospitable, a lover of goodness, sound in mind, righteous, loyal, self-controlled, 9 holding firmly to the faithful word as respects his art of teaching, that he may be able both to exhort by the teaching that is healthful and to reprove those who contradict.

10 For there are many unruly men, profitless talkers, and deceivers of the mind, especially those men who adhere to the circumcision. 11 It is necessary to shut the mouths of these, as these very men keep on subverting entire households by teaching things they ought not for the sake of dishonest gain. 12 A certain one of them, their own prophet, said: “Cre′tans are always liars, injurious wild beasts, unemployed gluttons.”

13 This witness is true. For this very cause keep on reproving them with severity, that they may be healthy in the faith, 14 paying no attention to Jewish fables and commandments of men who turn themselves away from the truth. 15 All things are clean to clean persons. But to persons defiled and faithless nothing is clean, but both their minds and their consciences are defiled. 16 They publicly declare they know God, but they disown him by their works, because they are detestable and disobedient and not approved for good work of any sort.

Titus

2 You, however, keep on speaking what things are fitting for healthful teaching. 2 Let the aged men be moderate in habits, serious, sound in mind, healthy in faith, in love, in endurance. 3 Likewise let the aged women be reverent in behavior, not slanderous, neither enslaved to a lot of wine, teachers of what is good; 4 that they may recall the young women to their senses to love their husbands, to love their children, 5 to be sound in mind, chaste, workers at home, good, subjecting themselves to their own husbands, so that the word of God may not be spoken of abusively.

6 Likewise keep on exhorting the younger men to be sound in mind, 7 in all things showing yourself an example of fine works; showing uncorruptness in your teaching, seriousness, 8 wholesome speech which cannot be condemned; so that the man on the opposing side may get ashamed, having nothing vile to say about us. 9 Let slaves be in subjection to their owners in all things, and please them well, not talking back, 10 not committing theft, but exhibiting good fidelity to the full, so that they may adorn the teaching of our Savior, God, in all things.

11 For the undeserved kindness of God which brings salvation to all sorts of men has been manifested, 12 instructing us to repudiate ungodliness and worldly desires and to live with soundness of mind and righteousness and godly devotion amid this present system of things, 13 while we wait for the happy hope and glorious manifestation of the great God and of the Savior of us, Christ Jesus, 14 who gave himself for us that he might deliver us from every sort of lawlessness and cleanse for himself a people peculiarly his own, zealous for fine works.

15 Keep on speaking these things and exhorting and reproving with full authority to command. Let no man ever despise you.

Hebrews

3 Consequently, holy brothers, partakers of the heavenly calling, consider the apostle and high priest whom we confess—Jesus. 2 He was faithful to the One that made him such, as Moses was also in all the house of that One. 3 For the latter is counted worthy of more glory than Moses, inasmuch as he who constructs it has more honor than the house. 4 Of course, every house is constructed by someone, but he that constructed all things is God. 5 And Moses as an attendant was faithful in all the house of that One as a testimony of the things that were to be spoken afterwards, 6 but Christ was faithful as a Son over the house of that One. We are the house of that One, if we make fast our hold on our freeness of speech and our boasting over the hope firm to the end.

7 For this reason, just as the holy spirit says: “Today if YOU people listen to his own voice, 8 do not harden YOUR hearts as on the occasion of causing bitter anger, as in the day of making the test in the wilderness, 9 in which YOUR forefathers made a test of me with a trial, and yet they had seen my works for forty years. 10 For this reason I became disgusted with this generation and said, ‘They always go astray in their hearts, and they themselves have not come to know my ways.’ 11 So I swore in my anger, ‘They shall not enter into my rest.’”

12 Beware, brothers, for fear there should ever develop in any one of YOU a wicked heart lacking faith by drawing away from the living God; 13 but keep on exhorting one another each day, as long as it may be called “Today,” for fear any one of YOU should become hardened by the deceptive power of sin. 14 For we actually become partakers of the Christ only if we make fast our hold on the confidence we had at the beginning firm to the end, 15 while it is being said: “Today if YOU people listen to his own voice, do not harden YOUR hearts as on the occasion of causing bitter anger.”

16 For who were they that heard and yet provoked to bitter anger? Did not, in fact, all do so who went out of Egypt under Moses? 17 Moreover, with whom did God become disgusted for forty years? Was it not with those who sinned, whose carcasses fell in the wilderness? 18 But to whom did he swear that they should not enter into his rest except to those who acted disobediently? 19 So we see that they could not enter in because of lack of faith.

Hebrews

7 For this Mel·chiz′e·dek, king of Sa′lem, priest of the Most High God, who met Abraham returning from the slaughter of the kings and blessed him 2 and to whom Abraham apportioned a tenth from all things, is first of all, by translation, “King of Righteousness,” and is then also king of Sa′lem, that is, “King of Peace.” 3 In being fatherless, motherless, without genealogy, having neither a beginning of days nor an end of life, but having been made like the Son of God, he remains a priest perpetually.

4 BEHOLD, then, how great this man was to whom Abraham, the family head, gave a tenth out of the chief spoils. 5 True, the men from the sons of Le′vi who receive their priestly office have a commandment to collect tithes from the people according to the Law, that is, from their brothers, even if these have issued from the loins of Abraham; 6 but the man who did not trace his genealogy from them took tithes from Abraham and blessed him who had the promises. 7 Now without any dispute, the less is blessed by the greater. 8 And in the one case it is men who are dying that receive tithes, but in the other case it is someone of whom it is witnessed that he lives. 9 And, if I may use the expression, through Abraham even Le′vi who receives tithes has paid tithes, 10 for he was still in the loins of his forefather when Mel·chiz′e·dek met him.

11 If, then, perfection were really through the Levitical priesthood, (for with it as a feature the people were given the Law,) what further need would there be for another priest to arise according to the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek and not said to be according to the manner of Aaron? 12 For since the priesthood is being changed, there comes to be of necessity a change also of the law. 13 For the man respecting whom these things are said has been a member of another tribe, from which no one has officiated at the altar. 14 For it is quite plain that our Lord has sprung up out of Judah, a tribe about which Moses spoke nothing concerning priests.

15 And it is still more abundantly clear that with a similarity to Mel·chiz′e·dek there arises another priest, 16 who has become such, not according to the law of a commandment depending upon the flesh, but according to the power of an indestructible life, 17 for in witness it is said: “You are a priest forever according to the manner of Mel·chiz′e·dek.”

18 Certainly, then, there occurs a setting aside of the preceding commandment on account of its weakness and ineffectiveness. 19 For the Law made nothing perfect, but the bringing in besides of a better hope did, through which we are drawing near to God. 20 Also, to the extent that it was not without a sworn oath, 21 (for there are indeed men that have become priests without a sworn oath, but there is one with an oath sworn by the One who said respecting him: “Jehovah has sworn (and he will feel no regret), ‘You are a priest forever,’”) 22 to that extent also Jesus has become the one given in pledge of a better covenant. 23 Furthermore, many had to become priests in succession because of being prevented by death from continuing as such, 24 but he because of continuing alive forever has his priesthood without any successors. 25 Consequently he is able also to save completely those who are approaching God through him, because he is always alive to plead for them.

26 For such a high priest as this was suitable for us, loyal, guileless, undefiled, separated from the sinners, and become higher than the heavens. 27 He does not need daily, as those high priests do, to offer up sacrifices, first for his own sins and then for those of the people: (for this he did once for all time when he offered himself up;) 28 for the Law appoints men high priests having weakness, but the word of the sworn oath that came after the Law appoints a Son, who is perfected forever.

Hebrews

8 Now as to the things being discussed this is the main point: We have such a high priest as this, and he has sat down at the right hand of the throne of the Majesty in the heavens, 2 a public servant of the holy place and of the true tent, which Jehovah put up, and not man. 3 For every high priest is appointed to offer both gifts and sacrifices; wherefore it was necessary for this one also to have something to offer. 4 If, now, he were upon earth, he would not be a priest, there being men who offer the gifts according to the Law, 5 but which men are rendering sacred service in a typical representation and a shadow of the heavenly things; just as Moses, when about to make the tent in completion, was given the divine command: For says he: “See that you make all things after their pattern that was shown to you in the mountain.” 6 But now Jesus has obtained a more excellent public service, so that he is also the mediator of a correspondingly better covenant, which has been legally established upon better promises.

7 For if that first covenant had been faultless, no place would have been sought for a second; 8 for he does find fault with the people when he says: “‘Look! There are days coming,’ says Jehovah, ‘and I will conclude with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah a new covenant; 9 not according to the covenant that I made with their forefathers in the day of my taking hold of their hand to bring them forth out of the land of Egypt, because they did not continue in my covenant, so that I stopped caring for them,’ says Jehovah.”

10 “‘For this is the covenant that I shall covenant with the house of Israel after those days,’ says Jehovah. ‘I will put my laws in their mind, and in their hearts I shall write them. And I will become their God, and they themselves will become my people.

11 “‘And they will by no means teach each one his fellow citizen and each one his brother, saying: “Know Jehovah!” For they will all know me, from the least one to the greatest one of them. 12 For I shall be merciful to their unrighteous deeds, and I shall by no means call their sins to mind anymore.’”

13 In his saying “a new covenant” he has made the former one obsolete. Now that which is made obsolete and growing old is near to vanishing away.

Hebrews

9 For its part, then, the former covenant used to have ordinances of sacred service and its mundane holy place. 2 For there was constructed a first tent compartment in which were the lampstand and also the table and the display of the loaves; and it is called “the Holy Place.” 3 But behind the second curtain was the tent compartment called “the Most Holy.” 4 This had a golden censer and the ark of the covenant overlaid all around with gold, in which were the golden jar having the manna and the rod of Aaron that budded and the tablets of the covenant; 5 but up above it were the glorious cherubs overshadowing the propitiatory cover. But now is not the time to speak in detail concerning these things.

6 After these things had been constructed this way, the priests enter the first tent compartment at all times to perform the sacred services; 7 but into the second compartment the high priest alone enters once a year, not without blood, which he offers for himself and for the sins of ignorance of the people. 8 Thus the holy spirit makes it plain that the way into the holy place had not yet been made manifest while the first tent was standing. 9 This very tent is an illustration for the appointed time that is now here, and in keeping with it both gifts and sacrifices are offered. However, these are not able to make the man doing sacred service perfect as respects his conscience, 10 but have to do only with foods and drinks and various baptisms. They were legal requirements pertaining to the flesh and were imposed until the appointed time to set things straight.

11 However, when Christ came as a high priest of the good things that have come to pass, through the greater and more perfect tent not made with hands, that is, not of this creation, 12 he entered, no, not with the blood of goats and of young bulls, but with his own blood, once for all time into the holy place and obtained an everlasting deliverance for us. 13 For if the blood of goats and of bulls and the ashes of a heifer sprinkled on those who have been defiled sanctifies to the extent of cleanness of the flesh, 14 how much more will the blood of the Christ, who through an everlasting spirit offered himself without blemish to God, cleanse our consciences from dead works that we may render sacred service to the living God?

15 So that is why he is a mediator of a new covenant, in order that, because a death has occurred for their release by ransom from the transgressions under the former covenant, the ones who have been called might receive the promise of the everlasting inheritance. 16 For where there is a covenant, the death of the human covenanter needs to be furnished. 17 For a covenant is valid over dead victims, since it is not in force at any time while the human covenanter is living. 18 Consequently neither was the former covenant inaugurated without blood. 19 For when every commandment according to the Law had been spoken by Moses to all the people, he took the blood of the young bulls and of the goats with water and scarlet wool and hyssop and sprinkled the book itself and all the people, 20 saying: “This is the blood of the covenant that God has laid as a charge upon YOU.” 21 And he sprinkled the tent and all the vessels of the public service likewise with the blood. 22 Yes, nearly all things are cleansed with blood according to the Law, and unless blood is poured out no forgiveness takes place.

23 Therefore it was necessary that the typical representations of the things in the heavens should be cleansed by these means, but the heavenly things themselves with sacrifices that are better than such sacrifices. 24 For Christ entered, not into a holy place made with hands, which is a copy of the reality, but into heaven itself, now to appear before the person of God for us. 25 Neither is it in order that he should offer himself often, as indeed the high priest enters into the holy place from year to year with blood not his own. 26 Otherwise, he would have to suffer often from the founding of the world. But now he has manifested himself once for all time at the conclusion of the systems of things to put sin away through the sacrifice of himself. 27 And as it is reserved for men to die once for all time, but after this a judgment, 28 so also the Christ was offered once for all time to bear the sins of many; and the second time that he appears it will be apart from sin and to those earnestly looking for him for their salvation.

James

3 Not many of YOU should become teachers, my brothers, knowing that we shall receive heavier judgment. 2 For we all stumble many times. If anyone does not stumble in word, this one is a perfect man, able to bridle also his whole body. 3 If we put bridles in the mouths of horses for them to obey us, we manage also their whole body. 4 Look! Even boats, although they are so big and are driven by hard winds, are steered by a very small rudder to where the inclination of the man at the helm wishes.

5 So, too, the tongue is a little member and yet makes great brags. Look! How little a fire it takes to set so great a woodland on fire! 6 Well, the tongue is a fire. The tongue is constituted a world of unrighteousness among our members, for it spots up all the body and sets the wheel of natural life aflame and it is set aflame by Ge·hen′na. 7 For every species of wild beast as well as bird and creeping thing and sea creature is to be tamed and has been tamed by humankind. 8 But the tongue, not one of mankind can get it tamed. An unruly injurious thing, it is full of death-dealing poison. 9 With it we bless Jehovah, even the Father, and yet with it we curse men who have come into existence “in the likeness of God.” 10 Out of the same mouth come forth blessing and cursing.

It is not proper, my brothers, for these things to go on occurring this way. 11 A fountain does not cause the sweet and the bitter to bubble out of the same opening, does it? 12 My brothers, a fig tree cannot produce olives or a vine figs, can it? Neither can salt water produce sweet water.

13 Who is wise and understanding among YOU? Let him show out of his fine conduct his works with a mildness that belongs to wisdom. 14 But if YOU have bitter jealousy and contentiousness in YOUR hearts, do not be bragging and lying against the truth. 15 This is not the wisdom that comes down from above, but is the earthly, animal, demonic. 16 For where jealousy and contentiousness are, there disorder and every vile thing are.

17 But the wisdom from above is first of all chaste, then peaceable, reasonable, ready to obey, full of mercy and good fruits, not making partial distinctions, not hypocritical. 18 Moreover, the fruit of righteousness has its seed sown under peaceful conditions for those who are making peace.

James

5 Come, now, YOU rich men, weep, howling over YOUR miseries that are coming upon YOU. 2 YOUR riches have rotted, and YOUR outer garments have become moth-eaten. 3 YOUR gold and silver are rusted away, and their rust will be as a witness against YOU and will eat YOUR fleshy parts. Something like fire is what YOU have stored up in the last days. 4 Look! The wages due the workers who harvested YOUR fields but which are held up by YOU, keep crying out, and the calls for help on the part of the reapers have entered into the ears of Jehovah of armies. 5 YOU have lived in luxury upon the earth and have gone in for sensual pleasure. YOU have fattened YOUR hearts on the day of slaughter. 6 YOU have condemned, YOU have murdered the righteous one. Is he not opposing YOU?

7 Exercise patience, therefore, brothers, until the presence of the Lord. Look! The farmer keeps waiting for the precious fruit of the earth, exercising patience over it until he gets the early rain and the late rain. 8 YOU too exercise patience; make YOUR hearts firm, because the presence of the Lord has drawn close.

9 Do not heave sighs against one another, brothers, so that YOU do not get judged. Look! The Judge is standing before the doors. 10 Brothers, take as a pattern of the suffering of evil and the exercising of patience the prophets, who spoke in the name of Jehovah. 11 Look! We pronounce happy those who have endured. YOU have heard of the endurance of Job and have seen the outcome Jehovah gave, that Jehovah is very tender in affection and merciful.

12 Above all things, though, my brothers, stop swearing, yes, either by heaven or by earth or by any other oath. But let YOUR Yes mean Yes, and YOUR No, No, so that YOU do not fall under judgment.

13 Is there anyone suffering evil among YOU? Let him carry on prayer. Is there anyone in good spirits? Let him sing psalms. 14 Is there anyone sick among YOU? Let him call the older men of the congregation to him, and let them pray over him, greasing him with oil in the name of Jehovah. 15 And the prayer of faith will make the indisposed one well, and Jehovah will raise him up. Also, if he has committed sins, it will be forgiven him.

16 Therefore openly confess YOUR sins to one another and pray for one another, that YOU may get healed. A righteous man’s supplication, when it is at work, has much force. 17 E·li′jah was a man with feelings like ours, and yet in prayer he prayed for it not to rain; and it did not rain upon the land for three years and six months. 18 And he prayed again, and the heaven gave rain and the land put forth its fruit.

19 My brothers, if anyone among YOU is misled from the truth and another turns him back, 20 know that he who turns a sinner back from the error of his way will save his soul from death and will cover a multitude of sins.

The Second of Peter

1 Simon Peter, a slave and apostle of Jesus Christ, to those who have obtained a faith, held in equal privilege with ours, by the righteousness of our God and the Savior Jesus Christ:

2 May undeserved kindness and peace be increased to YOU by an accurate knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord, 3 forasmuch as his divine power has given us freely all the things that concern life and godly devotion, through the accurate knowledge of the one who called us through glory and virtue. 4 Through these things he has freely given us the precious and very grand promises, that through these YOU may become sharers in divine nature, having escaped from the corruption that is in the world through lust.

5 Yes, for this very reason, by YOUR contributing in response all earnest effort, supply to YOUR faith virtue, to YOUR virtue knowledge, 6 to YOUR knowledge self-control, to YOUR self-control endurance, to YOUR endurance godly devotion, 7 to YOUR godly devotion brotherly affection, to YOUR brotherly affection love. 8 For if these things exist in YOU and overflow, they will prevent YOU from being either inactive or unfruitful regarding the accurate knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.

9 For if these things are not present in anyone, he is blind, shutting his eyes to the light, and has become forgetful of his cleansing from his sins of long ago. 10 For this reason, brothers, all the more do YOUR utmost to make the calling and choosing of YOU sure for yourselves; for if YOU keep on doing these things YOU will by no means ever fail. 11 In fact, thus there will be richly supplied to YOU the entrance into the everlasting kingdom of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ.

12 For this reason I shall be disposed always to remind YOU of these things, although YOU know them and are firmly set in the truth that is present in YOU. 13 But I consider it right, as long as I am in this tabernacle, to rouse YOU up by way of reminding YOU, 14 knowing as I do that the putting off of my tabernacle is soon to be, just as also our Lord Jesus Christ signified to me. 15 So I will do my utmost also at every time that, after my departure, YOU may be able to make mention of these things for yourselves.

16 No, it was not by following artfully contrived false stories that we acquainted YOU with the power and presence of our Lord Jesus Christ, but it was by having become eyewitnesses of his magnificence. 17 For he received from God the Father honor and glory, when words such as these were borne to him by the magnificent glory: “This is my son, my beloved, whom I myself have approved.” 18 Yes, these words we heard borne from heaven while we were with him in the holy mountain.

19 Consequently we have the prophetic word made more sure; and YOU are doing well in paying attention to it as to a lamp shining in a dark place, until day dawns and a daystar rises, in YOUR hearts. 20 For YOU know this first, that no prophecy of Scripture springs from any private interpretation. 21 For prophecy was at no time brought by man’s will, but men spoke from God as they were borne along by holy spirit.

The First of John

1 That which was from the beginning, which we have heard, which we have seen with our eyes, which we have viewed attentively and our hands felt, concerning the word of life, 2 (yes, the life was made manifest, and we have seen and are bearing witness and reporting to YOU the everlasting life which was with the Father and was made manifest to us,) 3 that which we have seen and heard we are reporting also to YOU, that YOU too may be having a sharing with us. Furthermore, this sharing of ours is with the Father and with his Son Jesus Christ. 4 And so we are writing these things that our joy may be in full measure.

5 And this is the message which we have heard from him and are announcing to YOU, that God is light and there is no darkness at all in union with him. 6 If we make the statement: “We are having a sharing with him,” and yet we go on walking in the darkness, we are lying and are not practicing the truth. 7 However, if we are walking in the light as he himself is in the light, we do have a sharing with one another, and the blood of Jesus his Son cleanses us from all sin.

8 If we make the statement: “We have no sin,” we are misleading ourselves and the truth is not in us. 9 If we confess our sins, he is faithful and righteous so as to forgive us our sins and to cleanse us from all unrighteousness. 10 If we make the statement: “We have not sinned,” we are making him a liar, and his word is not in us.

1 John

2 My little children, I am writing YOU these things that YOU may not commit a sin. And yet, if anyone does commit a sin, we have a helper with the Father, Jesus Christ, a righteous one. 2 And he is a propitiatory sacrifice for our sins, yet not for ours only but also for the whole world’s. 3 And by this we have the knowledge that we have come to know him, namely, if we continue observing his commandments. 4 He that says: “I have come to know him,” and yet is not observing his commandments, is a liar, and the truth is not in this person. 5 But whoever does observe his word, truthfully in this person the love of God has been made perfect. By this we have the knowledge that we are in union with him. 6 He that says he remains in union with him is under obligation himself also to go on walking just as that one walked.

7 Beloved ones, I am writing YOU, not a new commandment, but an old commandment which YOU have had from the beginning. This old commandment is the word which YOU heard. 8 Again, I am writing YOU a new commandment, a fact that is true in his case and in YOURS, because the darkness is passing away and the true light is already shining.

9 He that says he is in the light and yet hates his brother is in the darkness up to right now. 10 He that loves his brother remains in the light, and there is no cause for stumbling in his case. 11 But he that hates his brother is in the darkness and is walking in the darkness, and he does not know where he is going, because the darkness has blinded his eyes.

12 I am writing YOU, little children, because YOUR sins have been forgiven YOU for the sake of his name. 13 I am writing YOU, fathers, because YOU have come to know him who is from the beginning. I am writing YOU, young men, because YOU have conquered the wicked one. I write YOU, young children, because YOU have come to know the Father. 14 I write YOU, fathers, because YOU have come to know him who is from the beginning. I write YOU, young men, because YOU are strong and the word of God remains in YOU and YOU have conquered the wicked one.

15 Do not be loving either the world or the things in the world. If anyone loves the world, the love of the Father is not in him; 16 because everything in the world—the desire of the flesh and the desire of the eyes and the showy display of one’s means of life—does not originate with the Father, but originates with the world. 17 Furthermore, the world is passing away and so is its desire, but he that does the will of God remains forever.

18 Young children, it is the last hour, and, just as YOU have heard that antichrist is coming, even now there have come to be many antichrists; from which fact we gain the knowledge that it is the last hour. 19 They went out from us, but they were not of our sort; for if they had been of our sort, they would have remained with us. But they went out that it might be shown up that not all are of our sort. 20 And YOU have an anointing from the holy one; all of YOU have knowledge. 21 I write YOU, not because YOU do not know the truth, but because YOU know it, and because no lie originates with the truth.

22 Who is the liar if it is not the one that denies that Jesus is the Christ? This is the antichrist, the one that denies the Father and the Son. 23 Everyone that denies the Son does not have the Father either. He that confesses the Son has the Father also. 24 As for YOU, let that which YOU have heard from the beginning remain in YOU. If that which YOU have heard from the beginning remains in YOU, YOU will also abide in union with the Son and in union with the Father. 25 Furthermore, this is the promised thing that he himself promised us, the life everlasting.

26 These things I write YOU about those who are trying to mislead YOU. 27 And as for YOU, the anointing that YOU received from him remains in YOU, and YOU do not need anyone to be teaching YOU; but, as the anointing from him is teaching YOU about all things, and is true and is no lie, and just as it has taught YOU, remain in union with him. 28 So now, little children, remain in union with him, that when he is made manifest we may have freeness of speech and not be shamed away from him at his presence. 29 If YOU know that he is righteous, YOU gain the knowledge that everyone who practices righteousness has been born from him.

1 John

5 Everyone believing that Jesus is the Christ has been born from God, and everyone who loves the one that caused to be born loves him who has been born from that one. 2 By this we gain the knowledge that we are loving the children of God, when we are loving God and doing his commandments. 3 For this is what the love of God means, that we observe his commandments; and yet his commandments are not burdensome, 4 because everything that has been born from God conquers the world. And this is the conquest that has conquered the world, our faith.

5 Who is the one that conquers the world but he who has faith that Jesus is the Son of God? 6 This is he that came by means of water and blood, Jesus Christ; not with the water only, but with the water and with the blood. And the spirit is that which is bearing witness, because the spirit is the truth. 7 For there are three witness bearers, 8 the spirit and the water and the blood, and the three are in agreement.

9 If we receive the witness men give, the witness God gives is greater, because this is the witness God gives, the fact that he has borne witness concerning his Son. 10 The person putting his faith in the Son of God has the witness given in his own case. The person not having faith in God has made him a liar, because he has not put his faith in the witness given, which God as witness has given concerning his Son. 11 And this is the witness given, that God gave us everlasting life, and this life is in his Son. 12 He that has the Son has this life; he that does not have the Son of God does not have this life.

13 I write YOU these things that YOU may know that YOU have life everlasting, YOU who put YOUR faith in the name of the Son of God. 14 And this is the confidence that we have toward him, that, no matter what it is that we ask according to his will, he hears us. 15 Further, if we know he hears us respecting whatever we are asking, we know we are to have the things asked since we have asked them of him.

16 If anyone catches sight of his brother sinning a sin that does not incur death, he will ask, and he will give life to him, yes, to those not sinning so as to incur death. There is a sin that does incur death. It is concerning that sin that I do not tell him to make request. 17 All unrighteousness is sin; and yet there is a sin that does not incur death.

18 We know that every person that has been born from God does not practice sin, but the One born from God watches him, and the wicked one does not fasten his hold on him. 19 We know we originate with God, but the whole world is lying in the power of the wicked one. 20 But we know that the Son of God has come, and he has given us intellectual capacity that we may gain the knowledge of the true one. And we are in union with the true one, by means of his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God and life everlasting. 21 Little children, guard yourselves from idols.

The Second of John

1 The older man to the chosen lady and to her children, whom I truly love, and not I alone, but all those also who have come to know the truth, 2 because of the truth that remains in us, and it will be with us forever. 3 There will be with us undeserved kindness, mercy and peace from God the Father and from Jesus Christ the Son of the Father, with truth and love.

4 I rejoice very much because I have found certain ones of your children walking in the truth, just as we received commandment from the Father. 5 So now I request you, lady, as a person writing you, not a new commandment, but one which we had from the beginning, that we love one another. 6 And this is what love means, that we go on walking according to his commandments. This is the commandment, just as YOU people have heard from the beginning, that YOU should go on walking in it. 7 For many deceivers have gone forth into the world, persons not confessing Jesus Christ as coming in the flesh. This is the deceiver and the antichrist.

8 Look out for yourselves, that YOU do not lose the things we have worked to produce, but that YOU may obtain a full reward. 9 Everyone that pushes ahead and does not remain in the teaching of the Christ does not have God. He that does remain in this teaching is the one that has both the Father and the Son. 10 If anyone comes to YOU and does not bring this teaching, never receive him into YOUR homes or say a greeting to him. 11 For he that says a greeting to him is a sharer in his wicked works.

12 Although I have many things to write YOU, I do not desire to do so with paper and ink, but I am hoping to come to YOU and to speak with YOU face to face, that YOUR joy may be in full measure.

13 The children of your sister, the chosen one, send you their greetings.

Revelation

12 And a great sign was seen in heaven, a woman arrayed with the sun, and the moon was beneath her feet, and on her head was a crown of twelve stars, 2 and she was pregnant. And she cries out in her pains and in her agony to give birth.

3 And another sign was seen in heaven, and, look! a great fiery-colored dragon, with seven heads and ten horns and upon its heads seven diadems; 4 and its tail drags a third of the stars of heaven, and it hurled them down to the earth. And the dragon kept standing before the woman who was about to give birth, that, when she did give birth, it might devour her child.

5 And she gave birth to a son, a male, who is to shepherd all the nations with an iron rod. And her child was caught away to God and to his throne. 6 And the woman fled into the wilderness, where she has a place prepared by God, that they should feed her there a thousand two hundred and sixty days.

7 And war broke out in heaven: Mi′cha·el and his angels battled with the dragon, and the dragon and its angels battled 8 but it did not prevail, neither was a place found for them any longer in heaven. 9 So down the great dragon was hurled, the original serpent, the one called Devil and Satan, who is misleading the entire inhabited earth; he was hurled down to the earth, and his angels were hurled down with him. 10 And I heard a loud voice in heaven say:

“Now have come to pass the salvation and the power and the kingdom of our God and the authority of his Christ, because the accuser of our brothers has been hurled down, who accuses them day and night before our God! 11 And they conquered him because of the blood of the Lamb and because of the word of their witnessing, and they did not love their souls even in the face of death. 12 On this account be glad, YOU heavens and YOU who reside in them! Woe for the earth and for the sea, because the Devil has come down to YOU, having great anger, knowing he has a short period of time.”

13 Now when the dragon saw that it was hurled down to the earth, it persecuted the woman that gave birth to the male child. 14 But the two wings of the great eagle were given the woman, that she might fly into the wilderness to her place; there is where she is fed for a time and times and half a time away from the face of the serpent.

15 And the serpent disgorged water like a river from its mouth after the woman, to cause her to be drowned by the river. 16 But the earth came to the woman’s help, and the earth opened its mouth and swallowed up the river that the dragon disgorged from its mouth. 17 And the dragon grew wrathful at the woman, and went off to wage war with the remaining ones of her seed, who observe the commandments of God and have the work of bearing witness to Jesus.

Revelation

14 And I saw, and, look! the Lamb standing upon the Mount Zion, and with him a hundred and forty-four thousand having his name and the name of his Father written on their foreheads. 2 And I heard a sound out of heaven as the sound of many waters and as the sound of loud thunder; and the sound that I heard was as of singers who accompany themselves on the harp playing on their harps. 3 And they are singing as if a new song before the throne and before the four living creatures and the elders; and no one was able to master that song but the hundred and forty-four thousand, who have been bought from the earth. 4 These are the ones that did not defile themselves with women; in fact, they are virgins. These are the ones that keep following the Lamb no matter where he goes. These were bought from among mankind as firstfruits to God and to the Lamb, 5 and no falsehood was found in their mouths; they are without blemish.

6 And I saw another angel flying in midheaven, and he had everlasting good news to declare as glad tidings to those who dwell on the earth, and to every nation and tribe and tongue and people, 7 saying in a loud voice: “FEAR God and give him glory, because the hour of the judgment by him has arrived, and so worship the One who made the heaven and the earth and sea and fountains of waters.”

8 And another, a second angel, followed, saying: “She has fallen! Babylon the Great has fallen, she who made all the nations drink of the wine of the anger of her fornication!”

9 And another angel, a third, followed them, saying in a loud voice: “If anyone worships the wild beast and its image, and receives a mark on his forehead or upon his hand, 10 he will also drink of the wine of the anger of God that is poured out undiluted into the cup of his wrath, and he shall be tormented with fire and sulphur in the sight of the holy angels and in the sight of the Lamb. 11 And the smoke of their torment ascends forever and ever, and day and night they have no rest, those who worship the wild beast and its image, and whoever receives the mark of its name. 12 Here is where it means endurance for the holy ones, those who observe the commandments of God and the faith of Jesus.”

13 And I heard a voice out of heaven say: “Write: Happy are the dead who die in union with the Lord from this time onward. Yes, says the spirit, let them rest from their labors, for the things they did go right with them.”

14 And I saw, and, look! a white cloud, and upon the cloud someone seated like a son of man, with a golden crown on his head and a sharp sickle in his hand.

15 And another angel emerged from the temple sanctuary, crying with a loud voice to the one seated on the cloud: “Put your sickle in and reap, because the hour has come to reap, for the harvest of the earth is thoroughly ripe.” 16 And the one seated on the cloud thrust in his sickle on the earth, and the earth was reaped.

17 And still another angel emerged from the temple sanctuary that is in heaven, he, too, having a sharp sickle.

18 And still another angel emerged from the altar and he had authority over the fire. And he called out with a loud voice to the one that had the sharp sickle, saying: “Put your sharp sickle in and gather the clusters of the vine of the earth, because its grapes have become ripe.” 19 And the angel thrust his sickle into the earth and gathered the vine of the earth, and he hurled it into the great winepress of the anger of God. 20 And the winepress was trodden outside the city, and blood came out of the winepress as high up as the bridles of the horses, for a distance of a thousand six hundred furlongs.

Revelation

15 And I saw in heaven another sign, great and wonderful, seven angels with seven plagues. These are the last ones, because by means of them the anger of God is brought to a finish.

2 And I saw what seemed to be a glassy sea mingled with fire, and those who come off victorious from the wild beast and from its image and from the number of its name standing by the glassy sea, having harps of God. 3 And they are singing the song of Moses the slave of God and the song of the Lamb, saying:

“Great and wonderful are your works, Jehovah God, the Almighty. Righteous and true are your ways, King of eternity. 4 Who will not really fear you, Jehovah, and glorify your name, because you alone are loyal? For all the nations will come and worship before you, because your righteous decrees have been made manifest.”

5 And after these things I saw, and the sanctuary of the tent of the witness was opened in heaven, 6 and the seven angels with the seven plagues emerged from the sanctuary, clothed with clean, bright linen and girded about their breasts with golden girdles. 7 And one of the four living creatures gave the seven angels seven golden bowls that were full of the anger of God, who lives forever and ever. 8 And the sanctuary became filled with smoke because of the glory of God and because of his power, and no one was able to enter into the sanctuary until the seven plagues of the seven angels were finished.

Revelation

22 And he showed me a river of water of life, clear as crystal, flowing out from the throne of God and of the Lamb 2 down the middle of its broad way. And on this side of the river and on that side there were trees of life producing twelve crops of fruit, yielding their fruits each month. And the leaves of the trees were for the curing of the nations.

3 And no more will there be any curse. But the throne of God and of the Lamb will be in the city, and his slaves will render him sacred service; 4 and they will see his face, and his name will be on their foreheads. 5 Also, night will be no more, and they have no need of lamplight nor do they have sunlight, because Jehovah God will shed light upon them, and they will rule as kings forever and ever.

6 And he said to me: “These words are faithful and true; yes, Jehovah the God of the inspired expressions of the prophets sent his angel forth to show his slaves the things that must shortly take place. 7 And, look! I am coming quickly. Happy is anyone observing the words of the prophecy of this scroll.”

8 Well, I John was the one hearing and seeing these things. And when I had heard and seen, I fell down to worship before the feet of the angel that had been showing me these things. 9 But he tells me: “Be careful! Do not do that! All I am is a fellow slave of you and of your brothers who are prophets and of those who are observing the words of this scroll. Worship God.”

10 He also tells me: “Do not seal up the words of the prophecy of this scroll, for the appointed time is near. 11 He that is doing unrighteousness, let him do unrighteousness still; and let the filthy one be made filthy still; but let the righteous one do righteousness still, and let the holy one be made holy still.

12 “‘Look! I am coming quickly, and the reward I give is with me, to render to each one as his work is. 13 I am the Al′pha and the O·me′ga, the first and the last, the beginning and the end. 14 Happy are those who wash their robes, that the authority to go to the trees of life may be theirs and that they may gain entrance into the city by its gates. 15 Outside are the dogs and those who practice spiritism and the fornicators and the murderers and the idolaters and everyone liking and carrying on a lie.’

16 “‘I, Jesus, sent my angel to bear witness to YOU people of these things for the congregations. I am the root and the offspring of David, and the bright morning star.’”

17 And the spirit and the bride keep on saying: “Come!” And let anyone hearing say: “Come!” And let anyone thirsting come; let anyone that wishes take life’s water free.

18 “I am bearing witness to everyone that hears the words of the prophecy of this scroll: If anyone makes an addition to these things, God will add to him the plagues that are written in this scroll; 19 and if anyone takes anything away from the words of the scroll of this prophecy, God will take his portion away from the trees of life and out of the holy city, things which are written about in this scroll.

20 “He that bears witness of these things says, ‘Yes; I am coming quickly.’”

“Amen! Come, Lord Jesus.”

21 May the undeserved kindness of the Lord Jesus Christ be with the holy ones.